<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b109309f" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals: a comparative study of the reactivity of peroxyl radicals resulting from the α-cleavage of ketones</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Employing 2,2′-azinobis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt (ABTS2−) as a selective radical probe, nanosecond laser flash photolysis (LFP) and competitive kinetic methods have been used to investigate the reactions of acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals derived from the addition of oxygen to the α-cleavage products of various ketones in methanol.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The selectivity of ABTS2− for acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals (as opposed to alkylperoxyl radicals), under the experimental conditions used, is supported by the oxygen concentration dependence of the ABTS˙− radical ion absorption amplitudes for acyl radicals that undergo decarbonylation on sub-microsecond timescales.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The oxygen concentration dependence of the ABTS˙− transient absorption reflects the competition between decarbonylation and oxygen addition and therefore this data also provides information on decarbonylation and oxygen addition rates.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further evidence in support of the selectivity of ABTS2− for acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals is the agreement between results obtained from using different ketone precursors for specific acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The order of reactivity of the peroxyl radicals towards ABTS2− is found to be aroylperoxyl &gt; acylperoxyl ≫ alkylperoxyl.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The use of ABTS2− as a monitor for acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals has been exploited by using competitive kinetics to obtain rate constants for the reactions of various acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals with vitamin E and trolox.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Peroxyl radicals, in general, are strong oxidizing agents and play important roles in oxidative degradation of organic materials, such as in lipid peroxidation<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/> for example.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Peroxyl radicals vary in oxidising strength depending on the proximity of electron withdrawing/donating atoms and/or groups.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus trichloromethylperoxyl radical (CCl3O2˙ ), which has been shown to be responsible for the hepatotoxicity of carbon tetrachloride,<REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/> is well known to react rapidly with a number of substrates such as α-tocopherol,<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/> N,N,N′,N′-tetramethyl-p-phenylenediamine (TMPD),<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/> ascorbate<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit5"/>and ABTS<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit4"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit6"/> due to the electron withdrawing influence of the chlorine atoms.</text></s></P><P><s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Acyl and aroyl radicals are intermediates in many photochemical reactions e.g. the Fries rearrangement and the α-cleavage of ketones (Norrish type I).</text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals may be formed from the addition of oxygen to acyl/aroyl radicals (<XREF ID="sch1" TYPE="SCHEME-REF">Scheme 1</XREF>).</text></s></P><P><s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Recently, it has been reported that acetylperoxyl radical is generated from photolysis of biacetyl in aqueous aerosols, fogs and clouds<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit7"/> and this radical reacts rapidly with various organic pollutants present in such environments.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Acetylperoxyl radical is also an important intermediate in the oxidation of hydrocarbons.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit8"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Monitoring these peroxyl radicals directly by optical absorption methods presents some difficulties due to the fact that the absorption bands are weak and occur in the UV.<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There is very little work concerned with the reactions of these peroxyl radicals with other substances.<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit11"/><REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Roden et al<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit11"/>. have studied the epoxidation of acrolein by acetylperoxyl radical in the gas phase and report a rate constant of 1.3 × 104 M−1 s−1 at 383 K.</text></s></P><P><s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper, the use of ABTS2− as a selective probe for acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals is reported and through the use of competitive kinetics, the rate constants for reactions of various acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals with various phenolic substrates have been determined.</text></s></P><P><s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="None" advantage="Yes"/><text>One-electron oxidation of ABTS2− produces the highly coloured radical anion (ABTS˙−), which exhibits strong, distinctive absorption features at ∼415, 645 and 728 nm (ε = 34700 l M−1 cm−1 at 417 nm),<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit13"/> making it a convenient radical probe in polar solvents.<REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit14"/></text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The formation of ABTS˙− is via electron transfer (<XREF ID="eqn1" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (1)</XREF>)<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit16"/>.<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Previously, Schuchmann and Sonntag<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit12"/> produced acetylperoxyl radical by pulse radiolysis of aqueous acetaldehyde solutions containing oxygen and the rate constant for the reaction of this radical with ABTS2− was determined to be 1.8 × 109 M−1 s−1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="No"/><text>Photolysis of ketones in the presence of oxygen results in the production of both alkyl and acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals, which may lead to difficulties in interpretation of results.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Burton et al.,<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit17"/> studied the reactions of peroxyl radicals derived from the α-cleavage products of 2,2,4,4-tetramethyl-3-pentanone (TMP) with different phenol derivatives.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The authors attributed the observed reactions to both peroxyl radicals but proposed that pivaloylperoxyl radical is principally responsible, although this was not proven.</text></s></P><P><s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper, the oxygen concentration dependence of ABTS˙− transient absorption amplitudes is used to demonstrate that ABTS2− is a selective probe for acyl/aroylperoxyl radicals under the experimental conditions employed and that this oxygen concentration dependence also provides information relating to decarbonylation and oxygen addition rates.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, pinacolone (PIN) and 1,1-diphenylacetone (DPA) have been used as different sources of acetylperoxyl radical, and by comparison of the rate constants obtained for reaction with ABTS2− for both precursors, it is clear that acetylperoxyl radical is principally responsible for the observed reaction and that the alkylperoxyl radicals derived from pinacolone and 1,1-diphenylacetone do not make any significant contribution.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Similarly, α,α,α-trimethylacetophenone (TMA), benzopinacolone (BP) and benzoin methyl ether (BME) have been used as different sources of benzoylperoxyl radical and the results strongly suggest that benzoylperoxyl radical is principally responsible for the observed reaction with ABTS2−.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, the influence of substituents on the reactivity of acetylperoxyl radicals is discussed.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The structures of the peroxyl radical precursors and ABTS2− are given in <XREF ID="fig1" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 1</XREF>.</text></s></P><P><s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Abbreviations: ABTS2− = 2,2′-azinobis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonate); trolox = 6-hydroxy-2,5,7,8-tetramethylchroman-2-carboxylic acid; TMPD = N,N,N′,N′-tetramethyl-p-phenylenediamine; DBK = dibenzyl ketone; PAP = phenylacetylperoxyl; TMP = 2,2,4,4-tetramethyl-3-pentanone; PVP = pivaloylperoxyl; DMP = 2,4-dimethyl-3-pentanone; IBP = iso-butyrylperoxyl; PIN = pinacolone; DPA = 1,1-diphenylacetone; ACP = acetylperoxyl; TMA = α,α,α-trimethylacetophenone; BP = benzopinacolone; BME = benzoin methyl ether; BZP = benzoylperoxyl.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental section</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(i)">Materials</HEADER><P><s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Methanol (Aldrich, HPLC grade, or Riedel-de Haën, chromatographic grade) and acetonitrile (Riedel-de Haën, chromatographic grade) were used as received.</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Dibenzyl ketone, 2,2,4,4-tetramethyl-3-pentanone, pinacolone, 2, 4-dimethyl-3-pentanone, vitamin E 97percent, trolox and ABTS2− (Aldrich, highest purity available) were used as received.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>1,1-Diphenylacetone, α,α,α-trimethylacetophenone, benzopinacolone and benzoin methyl ether (Lancaster) were used as received.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>β-Carotene was supplied by Hoffmann-La Roche Ltd. Argon, oxygen and oxygen/nitrogen mixtures (1percent, 5percent, 50percent oxygen) were supplied by the British Oxygen Company (BOC).</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(ii)">Instrumentation</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The details of the laser flash photolysis system have been described previously.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit18"/></text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unless stated otherwise, 266 nm and 355 nm laser energies were in the range 0.4–1 mJ pulse−1 with a beam diameter of ∼4 mm.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Quartz sample cells (2 mm excitation pathlength × 10 mm monitoring pathlength) fitted with vacuum taps were employed for the laser flash photolysis measurements.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(i)">The influence of oxygen concentration</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Laser (266 nm) flash photolysis of dibenzyl ketone (DBK)</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The principal processes in the solution phase photolysis of DBK in the presence of oxygen are summarised in <XREF ID="sch2" TYPE="SCHEME-REF">Scheme 2</XREF>.</text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>DBK undergoes rapid intersystem crossing from the excited singlet state producing the triplet state (τT = 0.1 ns), which undergoes α–cleavage to give benzyl and phenylacetyl radicals.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Benzyl radical undergoes oxygen addition giving benzylperoxyl radical, while phenylacetyl radical undergoes decarbonylation<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit20"/><REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit21"/><REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit22"/> in competition with oxygen addition to give phenylacetylperoxyl (PAP) radical.</text></s></P><P><s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Following laser (266 nm) photolysis of DBK (A @ 266 nm = 0.2–0.4 in a 2 mm cell) in argon-saturated methanol containing ABTS2− (1 × 10−4 M) no ABTS˙− absorption is observed, suggesting that any reactions of ABTS2− with benzyl or phenylacetyl radicals are slow compared with radical combination to produce 1, 2-diphenylethane.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These observations are consistent with the reported redox potentials for ABTS˙−/ABTS2− (E = +0.68 V versus NHE<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit13"/>), benzyl/benzyl− (E = −1.16 V versus SHE<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit23"/>) and phenylacetyl/phenylacetyl− (E = −1.44 V versus SHE<REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit24"/>).</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, in the presence of oxygen a strong visible absorption, characteristic of ABTS˙−, is observed to grow-in on microsecond timescales at the concentrations of ABTS2− used.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the amplitude of the ABTS˙− transient absorption exhibits a strong dependence on oxygen concentration at oxygen concentrations less than ∼10−2 M, although the kinetics of the formation of ABTS˙− (mono-exponential) are unaffected by oxygen concentration (see <XREF ID="fig2" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 2</XREF>).</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The oxygen concentration dependence of the ABTS˙− transient absorption amplitude suggests that formation of the oxidising peroxyl radical (via oxygen addition) is competitive with another fast sub-microsecond process, namely decarbonylation.</text></s></P><P><s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>If both peroxyl radicals contribute to the observed reaction with ABTS2−, comparable absorption amplitudes would be predicted at low and high oxygen concentrations, since any phenylacetyl radical that escapes scavenging by oxygen will ultimately yield benzylperoxyl radical.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Alternatively, if it is only benzylperoxyl radical that reacts, then the size of the absorption signal due to ABTS˙− should decrease with increasing oxygen concentration.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The observed oxygen concentration dependence of the ABTS˙− absorption amplitude strongly suggests that the observed reaction is due solely to reaction of ABTS2− with PAP (<XREF ID="fig2" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 2</XREF>).</text></s></P><P><s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Using low (and constant) laser intensities to minimize contributions from 2nd order processes, the ABTS˙− transient absorbance (ΔA) is predicted to depend on the oxygen concentration as follows (providing the ABTS2− concentration is kept constant), <XREF ID="@" TYPE="GRAPHIC_POS"/>where kq is the rate constant for oxygen addition to the phenylacetyl radical (see <XREF ID="sch2" TYPE="SCHEME-REF">Scheme 2</XREF>) and C is a constant that includes factors such as the laser intensity, the fraction of the excitation light absorbed, the quantum yield for formation of phenylacetyl radical and the fraction of PAP radicals intercepted by ABTS2−.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This analysis predicts that a plot of 1/ΔA versus 1/[O2] (keeping the ABTS2− concentration and the laser intensity constant) should yield a straight line from which k–CO/kq can be obtained from the ratio of the slope to the intercept.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An example of such a plot is given in <XREF ID="fig3" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 3</XREF>, for which the slope is (9.9 ± 0.3) × 10−3 M and the intercept is 23.5 ± 1.4 giving a value for k–CO/kq of (4.2 ± 0.3) × 10−4 M for DBK in methanol at 298 K. Using a value for k–CO in methanol from the literature (2.5 × 106 s−1 at 296 K),<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit25"/> an estimate of kq (reported values of k–CO vary considerably; for example, in <REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit20"/> a value of 4.1 × 106 s−1 at 296 K is deduced from Arrhenius parameters for k–CO in methanol) is calculated as ∼6 × 109 M−1 s−1, which is consistent with reported rate constants for oxygen addition to many other carbon-centred radicals.<REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit17"/><REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit50"/></text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>If it is assumed that the rate constants for oxygen addition to different acyl/aroyl radicals are approximately equal then the information obtained from double-reciprocal plots for different carbonyl compounds may, in principle, be used to estimate relative rate constants for decarbonylation (see later).</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>It should be noted that the triplet lifetime of DBK (0.1 ns) precludes significant quenching by oxygen in the range of oxygen concentrations used.</text></s></P><P><s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The formation of ABTS˙− follows pseudo-first order kinetics and from the linear dependence of the observed rate constant on the ABTS2− concentration, a value of 3.7 × 108 M−1 s−1 (see <XREF ID="tab1" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 1</XREF>) was obtained for the rate constant for reaction of PAP with ABTS2−.</text></s></P><P><s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>An additional experiment was carried out in which β-carotene was used in place of ABTS2− in methanol.</text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The bleaching of the carotenoid ground state absorption at 450 nm displays similar oxygen concentration dependence to the ABTS˙− transient absorption and the observed first order rate constant for carotenoid bleaching is linearly dependent on carotenoid concentration.</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constant for the reaction between PAP and β-carotene was determined as (2.6 ± 0.3) × 109 M−1 s−1 from the slope of a plot of the observed first order rate constant for carotenoid bleaching at 450 nm versus carotenoid concentration.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This rate constant is comparable with the rate constant for reaction between another reactive peroxyl radical, CCl3O2˙, and β-carotene in aqueous 2percent Triton X-100 (2.1 × 109 M−1 s−1).<REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit26"/></text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>PAP bears a carbonyl group that exerts a strong electron withdrawing influence through inductive effects.<REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit27"/></text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The similarity between the reactivity of CCl3O2˙ and PAP towards β-carotene can be attributed to the similarity of the reduction potentials (E∼ + 1.1 V versus NHE) of acylperoxyl radicals and CCl3O2˙.<REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit28"/></text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The low rate constants (&lt;106 M−1 s−1) reported for the reactions of alkylperoxyl radicals with ABTS2−<REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit14"/> and β-carotene<REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit29"/> provides additional support for acylperoxyl radicals being solely responsible for the observed reactions with ABTS2− and β-carotene.</text></s></P><P><s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constants for reaction of PAP with the phenolic substrates trolox (6-hydroxy-2,5,7,8-tetramethylchroman-2-carboxylic acid, a derivative of α-tocopherol) and 2,6-di-t-butyl-4-methylphenol in methanol were determined using competitive kinetics<REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit30"/> (<XREF ID="eqn2" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (2)</XREF>) with ABTS2− as a reference (due to the low absorption coefficient of the phenoxyl radical derivative (λmax = 430 nm<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit15"/>)).</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn2"><EQ-S ID="s63">kobs = k1 + k2[standard] + k3[substrate]</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Here, k1 is the first order rate constant for the decay of PAP, k2 is the rate constant for reaction of PAP with ABTS2− and k3 is the rate constant for the reaction between PAP and substrate.</text></s></P><P><s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>By maintaining a constant concentration for the reference compound and ensuring pseudo-first order conditions, a plot of kobs versus substrate concentration yields a straight line with a slope equal to k3.</text></s></P><P><s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constant obtained in this manner for the reaction between PAP and trolox is (1.7 ± 0.1) × 108 M−1 s−1, which is five times larger than the rate constant reported for the reaction of CCl3O2˙ with trolox in methanol (3.1 × 107 M−1 s−1).<REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit31"/></text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, for 2,6-di-t-butyl-4-methylphenol no reaction with PAP is observed, even at substrate concentrations as high as 2.5 × 10−3 M. Zaikov et al<REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit32"/>. reported similar behaviour for the reactivity of acyl/aroylperoxyl radical with 2, 6-di-t-butyl-4-methylphenol, which they attributed to hydrogen bond formation between the phenolic hydrogen and the carbonyl oxygen of the acyl/aroylperoxyl radical.<REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit32"/></text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, Valgimigli et al<REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit33"/>. attribute the low rate constant (≤5 × 103 M−1 s−1) for the reaction between α–tocopheryl radical and 2,6-di-t-butyl-4-methylphenol to steric protection of the phenolic hydrogen.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Laser (266 nm) flash photolysis of 2,2,4,4-tetramethyl-3-pentanone (TMP)</HEADER><P><s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Following 266 nm laser excitation, TMP undergoes α-cleavage from the triplet state (τT = 0.13 ns).<REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit34"/><REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit35"/></text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The resulting radical products are t-butyl and pivaloyl radicals (<XREF ID="eqn3" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (3)</XREF>). <XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/>In the absence of oxygen no transient absorption due to ABTS˙− is observed following 266 nm laser photolysis of TMP and ABTS2− (1 × 10−4 M) in methanol.</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, in the presence of oxygen the growth in absorption of ABTS˙− is clearly evident on microsecond timescales and is attributed to reaction between pivaloylperoxyl (PVP) radical and ABTS2−.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constant for reaction between PVP and ABTS2− was obtained in the same way as for PAP (see <XREF ID="tab1" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 1</XREF>).</text></s></P><P><s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The oxygen concentration dependence of the ABTS˙− transient absorption amplitude was investigated in the same manner as for DBK and the plot of 1/ΔA versus 1/[O2] is shown in <XREF ID="fig3" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 3</XREF>.</text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From the ratio of the slope ((2.0 ± 0.1) × 10−3 M) to the intercept (33.2 ± 0.4), combined with the literature value for the decarbonylation rate constant of pivaloyl radical in methanol (4.2 × 105 s−1 at 296 K),<REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit25"/> a rate constant of ∼7 × 109 M−1 s−1 was estimated for the reaction between pivaloyl radical and oxygen in methanol.</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The ratio of the values for k–CO/kq for DBK (4.2 × 10−4 M) and TMP (6.0 × 10−5 M) gives 7.0 for the ratio of decarbonylation rate constants (k–CO(phenylacetyl)/k–CO(pivaloyl)), assuming the oxygen quenching rate constants (kq) are equal.</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is in fair agreement with the ratio of reported decarbonylation rate constants for phenylacetyl and pivaloyl radicals in methanol (k–CO(phenylacetyl)/k–CO(pivaloyl) = 6)<REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit25"/>.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Laser (266 nm) flash photolysis of 2, 4-dimethyl-3-pentanone (DMP)</HEADER><P><s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The triplet lifetime and triplet absorption spectrum of DMP have not been reported.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>No transient absorption changes were observed in the 300–600 nm region following 266 nm laser photolysis of DMP in argon-saturated methanol.</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Also, in the absence of oxygen, no transient absorption changes were observed following 266 nm laser photolysis of DMP and ABTS2− in methanol.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, in air-saturated solutions the growth in absorption due to ABTS˙− is observed, which is attributed to reaction between iso-butyrylperoxyl (IBP) radical and ABTS2−</text></s></P><P><s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The amplitude of the ABTS˙− transient absorption is not influenced by varying the oxygen concentration over the range 10−4 – 10−2 M, which is consistent with the low value of k–CO for iso-butyryl radical (3.2 × 104 s−1 in tetraethoxysilane at 300 K).<REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit36"/></text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The singlet oxygen quantum yield for DMP has been reported as 0.0003.<REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit37"/></text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This indicates that if 3DMP is formed, its triplet lifetime must be very short.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Comparing DMP with other compounds that have similar structures (PIN, TMP), it is expected that DMP undergoes α-cleavage mainly from the triplet state, although the possibility of α-cleavage from the singlet state cannot be excluded (<XREF ID="eqn4" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (4)</XREF>).<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/></text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(ii)">Studies of specific peroxyl radicals produced from different precursors</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Laser (266 nm) flash photolysis of pinacolone (PIN) and 1,1-diphenylacetone (DPA) as different sources of acetylperoxyl radical</HEADER><P><s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>In order to study acetylperoxyl (ACP) radical, PIN and DPA were used as precursors.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>PIN undergoes α-cleavage from its triplet state (τT &lt; 1 ns)<REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit38"/> to form acetyl and t-butyl radicals (<XREF ID="eqn5" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (5)</XREF>). <XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>DPA also undergoes α-cleavage to form acetyl and diphenylmethyl radicals (<XREF ID="eqn6" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. 6</XREF>).</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Diphenylmethyl radical exhibits strong absorption in the UV with λmax = 328 nm.<REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit17"/><REF ID="R-53" REFID="cit39"/></text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The triplet absorption spectrum and triplet lifetime of DPA have not been reported.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Following 266 nm laser photolysis of DPA in methanol in the absence of oxygen, no transient absorption changes were observed between 360–600 nm. <XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the absence of oxygen, 266 nm laser photolysis of methanol solutions of PIN or DPA containing ABTS2− (1 × 10−4 M) does not result in any transient absorption due to ABTS˙−.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This observation is consistent with the results of Schuchmann and Sonntag<REF ID="R-54" REFID="cit12"/> who showed that in aqueous solution, acetyl radical is unreactive towards ABTS2− and N,N,N′,N′-tetramethyl-p-phenylenediamine.</text></s></P><P><s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In air-saturated methanol solutions containing ABTS2− and either PIN or DPA, 266 nm laser photolysis leads to formation of ABTS˙− on microsecond timescales and is attributed to the reaction of ACP radical with ABTS2−.</text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constants determined for this reaction using PIN or DPA are in good agreement (0.17 and 0.19 × 109 M−1 s−1 respectively), which is consistent with ACP being the reactive species (<XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4A</XREF>).</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constant determined for reaction of ACP with ABTS2− in methanol is one order of magnitude lower than the literature value<REF ID="R-55" REFID="cit12"/> for the equivalent reaction in water (1.8 × 109 M−1 s−1), which is consistent with reports in the literature that rate constants for peroxyl radical electron transfer reactions in neat organic solvents are lower than in water by about one order of magnitude.<REF ID="R-56" REFID="cit31"/></text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In support of this, carrying out the experiment in a methanol–water (9∶1) mixture yields a larger rate constant of (0.35 ± 0.02) × 109 M−1 s−1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For PIN and DPA, the amplitude of the ABTS˙− transient absorption does not depend on the oxygen concentration over the concentration range used.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This result is expected due to the very low rate constants for decarbonylation (4 s−1 at 296 K, gas-phase)<REF ID="R-57" REFID="cit40"/> of the acetyl radical.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This result also indicates that if DPA undergoes α-cleavage from the triplet state the triplet lifetime must be very short, otherwise the size of the ABTS˙− absorption signal would decrease with increasing oxygen concentration.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Laser (266 &amp; 355 nm) flash photolysis of α,α,α-trimethylacetophenone (TMA), benzopinacolone (BP) and benzoin methyl ether (BME) as different sources of benzoylperoxyl (BZP) radical</HEADER><P><s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>In order to study BZP radical, TMA, BP and BME were used as precursors.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>TMA undergoes α-cleavage from the triplet state (τT = 370 ns in benzene, 500 ns in propan-2-ol)<REF ID="R-58" REFID="cit41"/> to form t-butyl and benzoyl radicals<REF ID="R-59" REFID="cit42"/> (<XREF ID="eqn7" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (7)</XREF>).</text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constant for decarbonylation of benzoyl radical is very small (7.8 × 10−8 s−1 in the gas phase).<REF ID="R-60" REFID="cit43"/><REF ID="R-61" REFID="cit44"/></text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>By monitoring the TMA triplet state absorption at 400 nm, the triplet lifetime of TMA in methanol was found to be 102 ± 5 ns.</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In air-saturated solution, BZP is formed and the rate constant for reaction with ABTS2− using TMA as a precursor is given in <XREF ID="tab1" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 1</XREF>.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Because of the longer triplet lifetime of TMA and the low rate of decarbonylation of benzoyl radical, the influence of oxygen concentration on the ABTS˙− transient absorption signal is such that the signal decreases as the oxygen concentration is raised, due to oxygen quenching of the TMA triplet state. <XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The triplet state absorption of BP is observed at 520 nm following 266 nm laser photolysis in argon-saturated methanol.</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Under these conditions the triplet lifetime was measured as 270 ± 15 ns.</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In <XREF ID="fig5" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 5</XREF>, at longer timescales, the maximum absorption is shifted to 550 nm.</text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Laser (266 nm) flash photolysis of BP in acetonitrile leads to the formation of 3BP only (τT ∼ 6.5 µs) and the triplet absorption maximum is at 480 nm (<XREF ID="fig6" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 6</XREF>).</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This result confirms that the band at 550 nm in methanol is due to the ketyl radical, which is not formed in acetonitrile due to its poor H-atom donor properties.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The short lifetime of 3BP in methanol is due to H-abstraction from the solvent.</text></s> <s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The absorption due to triphenylmethyl radical (also known as trityl radical) is also observed in methanol with λmax = 330 nm, which is close to the literature value of 338 nm.<REF ID="R-62" REFID="cit45"/></text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From these results it is concluded that BP undergoes α-cleavage from its triplet state to form benzoyl and trityl radicals (<XREF ID="eqn8" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (8)</XREF>) in competition with H-atom abstraction and intersystem crossing to the ground state.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constant of the reaction between BZP and ABTS2− using BP as a precursor is given in <XREF ID="tab1" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 1</XREF>. <XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>BME undergoes α-cleavage from the triplet state (τT &lt; 0.1 ns in benzene) to form benzoyl and α-methoxybenzyl radicals<REF ID="R-63" REFID="cit47"/><REF ID="R-64" REFID="cit48"/> (<XREF ID="eqn9" TYPE="EQUATION-REF">eqn. (9)</XREF>).</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Intramolecular H-atom abstraction from the methoxy group does not compete with the α-cleavage pathway<REF ID="R-65" REFID="cit46"/>.<XREF ID="@" TYPE="EQN_POS"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In air-saturated methanol, the rate constant for the reaction between BZP and ABTS2− has been determined at 415 and 645 nm and similar rate constants were obtained at both wavelengths (1.5 × 109 M−1 s−1, see <XREF ID="tab1" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 1</XREF>).</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same reaction was studied in the presence of 10percent water and the rate constant increases, as expected ((2.3 ± 0.2) × 109 M−1 s−1).</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Plots of pseudo-first order rate constants (kobs) versus ABTS2− concentration for the reaction of BZP with ABTS2−, using different sources of BZP, are shown in <XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4B</XREF>.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The consistency of the rate constants obtained for the reaction between ABTS2− and BZP using the three different sources (TMA, BP and BME) suggest that BZP is responsible for the observed reaction with ABTS2−.</text></s></P><P><s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The reactivity of BZP radical towards vitamin E and trolox was determined by competition kinetics using ABTS2− as a reference.</text></s> <s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate constants for the reaction of BZP with vitamin E and trolox were determined as (1.1 ± 0.1) × 109 M−1 s−1 and (0.53 ± 0.05) × 109 M−1 s−1 respectively (<XREF ID="fig7" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 7</XREF>).</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(iii)">Influence of substituents on the rate constant for reaction between acylperoxyl radicals and ABTS2−</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Comparison of the rate constants for the reactions between ABTS2− and ACP, PVP and IBP radicals suggest that alkyl substitution has little effect on the reactivity of ACP.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the introduction of a phenyl group (PAP) seems to have a significant effect (<XREF ID="tab1" TYPE="TABLE-REF">Table 1</XREF>), which may be due to the electron withdrawing effect of this group.</text></s> <s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Plots of pseudo-first order rate constants (kobs) for various acylperoxyl radicals (monitored at 415 nm) versus the concentration of ABTS2− are shown in <XREF ID="fig4" TYPE="FIGURE-REF">Fig. 4A</XREF>.</text></s></P><P><s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The fact that BZP is more reactive than PAP highlights the increased influence of the electron-withdrawing effect of the phenyl group in BZP, due to its closer proximity to the peroxyl functionality.</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Similar observations have been reported for halogen substituents; for example, the rate constant for the reaction between 1-chloroethylperoxyl radical and ascorbate ion (k = 9.2 × 107 M−1 s−1)<REF ID="R-66" REFID="cit49"/> is considerably higher than the equivalent rate constant for 2-chloroethylperoxyl radical (k = 5 × 106 M−1 s−1).<REF ID="R-67" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Also, 1,1-dichloroethylperoxyl radical reacts with ascorbate ion and ABTS2− (k = 4.6 and 4.3 × 108 M−1 s−1 respectively)<REF ID="R-68" REFID="cit49"/> faster than 1, 2-dichloroethylperoxyl radical (k = 1.9 and 1.1 × 108 M−1 s−1 respectively)<REF ID="R-69" REFID="cit49"/>.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Nanosecond laser flash photolysis studies of different ketones show that aroylperoxyl radicals are more reactive towards ABTS2− than acylperoxyl radicals by approximately one order of magnitude.</text></s> <s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Also, aroylperoxyl and acylperoxyl radicals are highly reactive relative to alkylperoxyl radicals.</text></s> <s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>By using product analysis methods, Zaikov et al<REF ID="R-70" REFID="cit32"/>. obtained the same order of reactivity for the reactions of peroxyl radicals with different hydrogen donors in chlorobenzene.</text></s></P><P><s sid="132"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From the results reported here, the reactions of acyl or aroylperoxyl radicals produced by photolysis of certain ketones can be studied with little or no interference from alkylperoxyl radicals due to the differences in reactivity.</text></s> <s sid="133"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of ABTS2− provides a convenient selective probe for studying the reactions of these radicals in polar solvents.</text></s></P><P><s sid="134"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From the oxygen concentration dependence of the ABTS˙− absorption amplitude it is possible to compare the rates of decarbonylation for different acyl radicals in certain cases, provided it is assumed that the rate constants for oxygen addition to these radicals are approximately equal.</text></s></P><P><s sid="135"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In principle, it should also be possible to adapt the methods reported in this paper to determine α-cleavage quantum yields (because the ABTS˙− absorption coefficients are well known) and Arrhenius parameters for decarbonylation reactions (from the temperature dependence of the ABTS˙− transient absorption amplitudes).</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>