<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b303244b" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Thin alumina films on Ni3Al(111): A template for nanostructured Pd cluster growth</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The growth of vapor deposited palladium on a well-ordered thin alumina film grown on a Ni3Al(111) surface was studied as a function of the sample temperature during deposition and the palladium flux.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The superstructure of the oxide film turns out to be an excellent template for the growth of nanostructured palladium cluster arrays.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>By taking advantage of the growth steering properties of the alumina film we were able to prepare nearly perfectly ordered hexagonal arrays of palladium clusters with a uniform distance of 4.5 nm between the particles.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore the dependence of the cluster height and diameter on the sample voltage as measured by STM has been investigated.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the range between 0.7 V and 2.0 V the measured cluster heights are nearly independent of the sample voltage whereas at voltages higher than 2 V they are continuously decreasing.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Metal oxides are of great interest because of their wide use in technical applications ranging from heterogeneous catalysis to microelectronics.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since most surface analysis techniques, which are based on charged particles like electrons and ions, require electrically conducting samples, the surfaces of most bulk oxides cannot easily be investigated by these methods.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>To circumvent this problem thin oxide films grown on a metallic support can be employed.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>On the one hand these films in many cases have similar physical and chemical properties as the corresponding bulk oxides.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>On the other hand the electric conductivity of oxide films with a thickness of not more than a few nanometers is high enough to prevent charging and, thus, allows the use of analytical techniques that require a conductive sample.</text></s></P><P><s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No"/><text>In the case of alumina it is not possible to prepare well-ordered crystalline thin films simply by oxidizing an aluminium single crystal since the high affinity of aluminium to oxygen leads to the development of relatively thick and amorphous films.<REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/></text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No"/><text>Furthermore, the annealing temperature needed to recrystallize such a film in order to form an ordered structure is higher than the melting point of aluminium (Tm = 933 K).</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Using single crystals of high melting point nickel–aluminium alloys, which easily withstand the annealing temperatures needed, can circumvent this problem.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>It has been shown by various groups that ordered and crystalline alumina films can be prepared by oxidizing single crystal surfaces of NiAl alloys in ultrahigh vacuum with a defined amount of oxygen.<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit4"/><REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit6"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Early studies of Bardi et al. had suggested that similar films of 5 Å thickness could also be produced on Ni3Al(111).<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Later we were able to show that these films resemble in unit lattice parameter and phonon spectra the films grown on NiAl(110).<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>STM images of these double-layer alumina films grown at a temperature of 1000 K on Ni3Al(111) show two different superstructures on the nanometer scale depending on the sample bias voltage.<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At voltages of 3.0 V and higher a hexagonal structure with a lattice constant of 2.6 nm (“network structure”) is visible, which can be explained by a superposition of the hexagonal Ni3Al(111) substrate lattice and the hexagonal oxygen layers of the alumina film.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Images acquired at a bias voltage around 2.3 V, in turn, show a hexagonal array of bright dots with a lattice constant of 4.5 nm (“dot structure”).</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unlike alumina films grown on other Ni/Al substrates, the films presented here are very homogeneous and extend over large surfaces areas without being subject to domain boundary formation.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An example for the quality of the films and the two different superstructures encountered in STM images is given in Fig. 1.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Using spatially resolved scanning tunneling spectroscopy (STS) on a variety of points in the unit cell of the superstructure the contrast reversal in the STM images has been shown to originate from distinct localized states in the band gap of the oxide.<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit11"/></text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since electronic and structural defects are known to play an important role as nucleation sites for metal growth on oxide surfaces<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit12"/> the question arises whether this applies also to the electronic superstructures of the alumina films presented here.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This questions has been partially answered in previous communications that included results on the influence of these superstructures on the nucleation and growth of vapor deposited metals such as silver, manganese, copper, and vanadium.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit14"/><REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit15"/></text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Depending on the metal one observes a preferential nucleation and growth of the clusters at sites determined by either the “dot structure” (silver, copper, and palladium) or at sites determined by the “network structure” (vanadium).</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Only the case of manganese sites belonging to both superstructures are decorated during the cluster growth.</text></s></P><P><s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results were quite promising in terms of preferential nucleation on specific sites but they fell, however, short of the goal of preparing ordered arrays of monodisperse clusters.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The latter can be regarded as the ultimate model catalysts since they would consist of identical particles in an identical environment.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This reduces the complexity of the respective system to a minimum; in this case a particular reaction under investigation would proceed identically on each particle.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This, in turn, allows one to separate two effects that play a crucial role in heterogeneous catalysis, namely the particle size dependence of the reaction<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit12"/> and the role of the reverse spillover.<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit16"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The aim of this work was to investigate the nucleation and growth of palladium clusters on the double-layer alumina film on Ni3Al(111) as a function of the deposition parameters such as palladium flux and sample temperature by scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) in order to produce homogeneous arrays of ordered Pd clusters.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It will be shown that, by choosing appropriate evaporation conditions, we can get very close to that goal.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The system Pd/Al2O3/Ni3Al(111) must, therefore, be considered as an excellent model for reactivity studies since it combines a very low degree of complexity with a realistic model of a heterogeneous catalyst.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, the problems encountered when imaging metal clusters on thin oxide films will be discussed.</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It will be shown that important changes in the apparent height and size of the Pd clusters occur as a function of the applied tunneling voltage.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All experiments were performed in an ultrahigh vacuum (UHV) chamber with a base pressure lower than 2 × 10−8 Pa equipped with an Auger electron spectrometer (AES), a quadrupole mass spectrometer (QMS) for residual gas analysis, a sputter gun for surface cleaning, and a scanning tunneling microscope (STM).</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The setup of the chamber has been described in detail elsewhere.<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit17"/><REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit18"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Ni3Al(111) single crystal was oriented and mechanically polished with a precision of &lt;0.5° (MaTeck, Jülich).</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sample was cleaned by repeated cycles of Ar+ ion sputtering (2.5 keV, 7.8 µA cm−2) and subsequent annealing for 7 min at 1150 K and 1000 K, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The temperature of the sample was monitored by a type K thermocouple, which was spot-welded to the back of the crystal.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The cleanliness and composition of the thus prepared Ni3Al(111) surface was checked by AES.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The morphology, especially the formation of large terraces, was monitored by STM.</text></s></P><P><s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The oxide film was prepared by exposing the sample surface to 40 L oxygen (99.998percent purity, Linde) at a sample temperature of 1000 K and an oxygen partial pressure of 2 × 10−6 Pa.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After the oxygen exposure the temperature of the sample was raised to 1050 K for 5–7 min.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The quality of the oxide film was then checked with STM at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>If necessary the oxidation procedure was repeated until a closed and well-ordered oxide film was obtained.</text></s></P><P><s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the vapor deposition of the palladium a homebuilt water-cooled evaporator was used, which was equipped with a rotary feed-through for operating a shutter.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The palladium (99.99percent purity, Goodfellow) was evaporated by direct heating from a filament, which was fabricated from a tungsten wire of 0.25 mm diameter.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The palladium flux was estimated at low palladium coverage from the apparent size of the clusters using the procedures described in sections 3.3.1 and 3.3.2.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For single layer clusters we assumed a flat and for all other clusters a hemispherical shape.</text></s></P><P><s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All STM images were acquired at room temperature with the bias voltage applied to the sample.</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The tunneling parameters are given for each image in the figure caption.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Results and discussions</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.1">Nucleation and growth</HEADER><P><s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In a first series of growth experiments we chose a sample temperature of 300 K and a palladium flux of about 0.002 ML s−1.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This low flux allowed us to follow the nucleation process in detail in order to pin down the nucleation sites.</text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 2 depicts a series of STM images showing the evolution of the alumina covered Ni3Al(111) surface with increasing palladium coverage.</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>While after 30 s of Pd deposition a hexagonal arrangement of the Pd clusters is already visible in the STM image (Fig. 2a) the corresponding autocorrelation image (Fig. 2a*) does not show a long-range order yet.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As can be seen in Fig. 2b this situation changes rapidly with increasing evaporation time.</text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Even at this relatively low Pd coverage (0.12 ML) a long-range hexagonal order of the clusters clearly develops in the STM image as well as in the autocorrelation image (Fig. 2b*).</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The order increases as the Pd clusters continue to grow (Figs. 2c* and 2d*).</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Closer inspection of the STM images leads to the conclusion that all clusters, which are visible in the image, grow at points of a hexagonal array with a lattice constant of 4.5 nm.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This size corresponds exactly to that of the “dot structure” of the oxide film<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit10"/> suggesting that the clusters grow on the protrusions of the “dot structure” as it has been observed earlier for other metal deposits.<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit14"/><REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit15"/></text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since in the presented series the bias voltage was chosen such that the oxide film appears flat and unstructured, a direct proof for this assumption is missing.</text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, adjusting the STM bias voltage in a way such that both the clusters and the alumina superstructure are visible allowed us to verify that the clusters, indeed, reside on the “dots”.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In Fig. 3a an STM image of the alumina film with a palladium coverage of approximately 0.06 ML measured at a bias voltage of 3.2 V is displayed.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At this sample voltage both the hexagonal 2.6 nm “network” superstructure of the film and the palladium clusters are visible.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The clusters (bright spots) grow exactly on the dark areas of the “network structure”, but occupying only a (√3 × √3)R30° subset of all “network” sites, a situation that is schematically depicted in Fig. 3b.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since it has been earlier established that the “dot structure” represents a (√3 × √3)R30° subset of the “network structure”<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit11"/> it can be safely concluded that the “dot structure” provides the nucleation centers for the growth of the palladium clusters.</text></s></P><P><s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The growth series in Fig. 2 nicely proves the preferential nucleation of the deposited Pd on the “dot structure”.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This results in a Pd cluster array where all clusters are hexagonally arranged and evenly spaced (d = 4.5 nm).</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this sense the surface produced under these conditions partially fulfills the requirements for a prefect model of a supported catalyst which were stated in the introduction.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, as yet the cluster size is far from being monodisperse.</text></s></P><P><s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to gain more insight in the nucleation and growth process we have analyzed the STM images in more detail.</text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>To this end we chose to classify the clusters in the series (Fig. 2) according to their heights in multiples of atomic layers.</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>As will be explained in section 3.3 this is a far more reliable measure than the apparent cluster diameter, which not only strongly depends on the bias voltage but is also subject to convolution effects with the STM tip.</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast to that the cluster height changes only weakly in the bias voltage range between 0.5 and 2.0 V. Additionally the cluster heights are integral multiples of about ≈0.2 nm, i.e. 0.195 nm on Pd(100) and 0.225 nm on Pd(111) surfaces, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Consequently it is possible to classify the clusters according to the number of atomic layers.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Such a classification of the cluster heights as a function of deposition time is shown in Fig. 4.</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this series ten different palladium coverages were prepared with a constant flux of 0.002 ML s−1.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The number density ni of clusters of thickness i is given in absolute numbers.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The summation of all quotas results in the total number density of clusters and, hence, nucleation sites n.</text></s></P><P><s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Before we analyze the evolution of the total number of occupied nucleation sites, however, let us discuss the growth behavior of the individual height classes in more detail.</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It can be seen in Fig. 4 that initially only 1- and 2-layer clusters are formed.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Only after the total density of clusters has reached its maximum, that is all nucleation sites are decorated, the thickness of the clusters starts to increase.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is evidenced by a sudden decrease in the density of 1-layer clusters accompanied by an increase of the number density of 2-layer clusters.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the same time the number density of 3- and 4-layer clusters starts to increase.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Taking this into account the process can be divided into two regimes, a nucleation regime, where the available nucleation centers are decorated with stable nuclei, and a growth regime, where the clusters increase in volume.</text></s></P><P><s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to get more insight into the mechanism of the nucleation and growth the total number density of clusters was fitted to the function n(t) = nstanh(t/τ), which was initially derived by Robinson and Robins to describe the random heterogeneous nucleation of Au on NaCl and KBr<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit19"/> under low flux/high temperature conditions.</text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Here ns signifies the saturation density of clusters (in our case: 0.055 nm−2), t is the deposition time, and τ is a parameter that depends on the substrate temperature and the flux of impinging Pd atoms.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This model was later successfully applied by Chapon et al. to the growth of Pd on MgO(100).<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit20"/></text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The full line in Fig. 4 nicely reproduces our data; therefore we conclude that in our case a heterogeneous nucleation mechanism is operative.</text></s></P><P><s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This reasoning is also supported by comparing our results to the work of Haas et al. on the nucleation and growth of Pd on Mg(100).</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These authors found that the saturation density of clusters does not depend on the substrate temperature for temperatures lower than 600 K.<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Above this temperature the saturation density of clusters is decreasing.</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is exactly the behavior that we encounter in our case.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As can be seen in Fig. 5, which shows STM images acquired for growth of Pd at different substrate temperatures, the saturation density of clusters stays constant for 400 K and 500 K. Only at a substrate temperature of 600 K does the saturation density of clusters start to decrease.</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition to that the formation of flatter Pd islands seems to be favored at elevated temperatures.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The strong analogy between the work of Haas et al. and our data suggests that the conclusions drawn by these authors equally apply to our system.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>They claimed that the nucleation behavior of Pd on defects on MgO(100) can be explained by the presence of strong trapping centers.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In our case that would imply that the “dot structure” provides these strong trapping centers for Pd nucleation and growth; its long-range electronic superstructure acts in the same way as random point defects on MgO(100) do.</text></s></P><P><s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore it can also be deduced from the images in Fig. 5 that the order of the cluster array is higher and the size distribution of clusters narrower for lower substrate temperatures during deposition.</text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From these measurements it is obvious that the most favorable substrate temperature seems to be 300 K.</text></s></P><P><s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to get better results concerning the cluster size distribution we chose to increase the impinging Pd flux R to 0.3 ML s−1.</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This gives us the advantage that the impinging flux per nucleation site will be much higher (3.0 nm−2 s−1 corresponding to ≈55 atoms per nucleation site per second) and, thus the rate of nucleation is much higher.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same result can be deduced from the parameter introduced by Robinson and Robins, which suggests a shorter induction period for higher flux.<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit19"/></text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The result of the corresponding experiment is displayed in Fig. 6a.</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>One observes a nearly perfectly ordered hexagonal cluster array as documented in the autocorrelation image (Fig. 6a*).</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Only a few locations on the surface can be seen where the order is not perfect.</text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These imperfections result most likely from missing “dots”, thus, missing nucleation centers, a situation that is depicted in Fig. 1b.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A narrow size distribution of the clusters is also evident in the STM image in Fig. 6a.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Evidently the distribution of particles in Fig. 6a is very close to the desired result.</text></s></P><P><s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We would expect that, instead of increasing the flux, reducing the sample temperature during deposition could produce a similar result.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This would result in a smaller diffusion coefficient D and, thus, a higher density of nuclei that could be stabilized at the trapping centers.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unfortunately our setup did not allow for sample temperatures lower than room temperature so that this has not been verified.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.2">Morphology of the islands grown at 600 K</HEADER><P><s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Since the majority of islands grown at 600 K are flat (Fig. 7), it is worthwhile taking a closer look at the morphology of these islands in relation to the underlying alumina film.</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As in the case of the clusters grown at 300 K the heights of these islands – measured at a sample voltage of 0.7 V – are again multiples of roughly 0.2 nm (see Fig. 7) so that they can also be classified according to the number of atomic layers.</text></s> <s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The lateral dimension of the islands grown at a sample temperature of 600 K is large enough for analyzing their surface topography by STM.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Even though we did not achieve atomic resolution on top of the palladium islands the influence of the underlying “network structure” of the alumina film on the topography of the islands is clearly discernible.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the middle of the STM image in Fig. 8a one can see palladium clusters in a hexagonal arrangement with an inter-particle distance of 4.5 nm, which is a hint to the fact that even at this elevated temperature the oxide superstructure partially determines the growth of the clusters, and that the clusters nucleate on the “dot structure”.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 8b shows larger islands that extend over several lattice constants of the alumina superstructure.</text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Together with these two STM images height profiles are shown that were acquired for three different bias voltages at the positions indicated in the STM images.</text></s> <s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The height profiles that were taken at a bias voltage of 3.2 V show pronounced minima within the Pd islands.</text></s> <s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is not surprising at all since the clusters reside on the network structure (see Fig. 3), which by itself possesses a large corrugation at the bias voltage indicated.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same feature is also apparent, however, in a less pronounced way, for the bias voltage of 2.3 V. Only at a bias voltage of 0.7 V do the Pd islands appear to be completely flat.</text></s> <s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Whereas for the latter bias voltage this is not unusual since the alumina film itself appears totally flat at this bias, the result for 2.3 V bias is intriguing.</text></s> <s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For this bias voltage protrusions (the so-called “dot structure”) appear in the STM image of the bare alumina film.</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This would suggest that a protrusion should be visible in the line scan at a bias of 2.3 V in Fig. 8I.</text></s> <s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, when covered by one layer of palladium this contrast reversal is not found.</text></s> <s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same features are visible in all height profiles along the main symmetry direction of the “network structure”, namely minima separated by 2.6 nm (see Fig. 8III), while height profiles along a direction 30° rotated show minima with a distance of √3 × 2.6 nm = 4.5 nm (see Fig. 8II).</text></s> <s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The possible orientations of the islands in Fig. 8 with respect to the alumina superstructure are schematically depicted in Fig. 9.</text></s> <s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It becomes evident that for bias voltages for which the apparent topography of the bare alumina film differs significantly namely 3.2 V and 2.3 V (see Fig. 1), the topography of larger Pd islands shows no distinct bias dependence.</text></s> <s sid="132"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The topography of the islands seems to be dominated by the “network structure”.</text></s> <s sid="133"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This leads us to the conclusion that this structure must be closely related to the real topography of the alumina film.</text></s> <s sid="134"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, it seems that the electronic structure of the film is modified by the presence of palladium islands in such a way that the “dot structure” is no longer visible in STM.</text></s> <s sid="135"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results confirm the assumption that the “dot structure” is merely an electronic superstructure of the alumina film as it has also been proposed in<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit11"/>.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3">Bias-dependence of the cluster height and size</HEADER><P><s sid="136"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>For the analysis of the growth process (see section 3.1) the cluster height at a bias voltage of 0.7 V was the appropriate parameter.</text></s> <s sid="137"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this section we will discuss the influence of the bias voltage on the apparent height and diameter of the clusters.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.1">Bias-dependence of the cluster height</HEADER><P><s sid="138"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>For measuring the height of deposited particles with STM a sufficiently large uncovered area between the particles is needed in order to establish the origin for the height measurement.</text></s> <s sid="139"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Taking this into account height measurements require a relatively low palladium coverage.</text></s> <s sid="140"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For 0.3 ML of palladium deposited at a flux of 0.002 ML s−1 a series of STM images of the same area on the surface for different bias voltages is shown in Fig. 10.</text></s> <s sid="141"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Care has to be taken to avoid tip changes, which frequently occur during scanning of metal clusters on oxide surfaces due to interactions between the tip and the clusters.</text></s> <s sid="142"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These tip changes are, however, easily recognizable since they result in a sudden change of the apparent cluster shape and size.</text></s> <s sid="143"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In Fig. 10 a series of STM images taken for different bias voltages at approximately the same position of the sample is shown.</text></s> <s sid="144"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The heights were determined from height profiles across the centre of the clusters.</text></s> <s sid="145"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The bias dependence of the measured heights of a 1-, a 2-, and a 4-layer cluster are shown in Fig. 11a.</text></s> <s sid="146"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The measured height of the three clusters (which are marked by circles in the STM images of Fig. 10) is nearly independent of the bias voltage in the range between 0.7 V and 2 V. In this range the imaged heights are multiples of approximately 0.2 nm, which is very close to the value of a mono atomic palladium step.</text></s> <s sid="147"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At bias voltages above 2 V the apparent heights are continuously decreasing.</text></s> <s sid="148"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This leads eventually to the complete disappearance of small 1-layer clusters visible at lower bias in Fig. 10 at a bias voltage of 3.2 V. In order to explain this behavior we have to consider the band structure of the oxide.</text></s> <s sid="149"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Earlier STS measurements have shown that in the bias voltage range above 2 V the contribution of the alumina states to the tunneling current becomes non-negligible.<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit11"/></text></s> <s sid="150"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is even more important for clusters sitting on the “dot structure” since these sites show a strong contribution to the tunneling current above 2 V. For bias voltages above ≈3 V the main contribution to the tunneling process comes from the alumina conduction band.</text></s> <s sid="151"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This leads to the assumption that at positive bias voltages below 2 V electrons mainly tunnel into palladium states so that the heights are imaged quite realistically.</text></s> <s sid="152"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The existence of two mesoscopic tunnel junctions coupled in series formed by the system tip/vacuum gap/cluster/oxide/crystal seems to have no crucial influence on the imaged cluster heights in this bias voltage range.</text></s> <s sid="153"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the case of small 1-layer palladium clusters and positive bias voltages above 3 V the main contribution to the tunneling current comes from the alumina conduction band.</text></s> <s sid="154"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This bias dependence of the palladium cluster heights on the oxidized Ni3Al(111) surface is in very good agreement with similar measurements on palladium clusters on the oxidized NiAl(110) surface<REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit22"/>.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.3.2">Bias-dependence of the cluster diameter</HEADER><P><s sid="155"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In principle it is impossible to measure the exact diameter of 3D particles with a scanning tunneling microscope because the measured diameter strongly depends on the tip quality and is in general larger than the real diameter due to a convolution of the cluster and the tip diameter, which are of the same order of magnitude.</text></s> <s sid="156"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>That is why cluster diameters are only comparable in a relative sense and only within a series of images without any tip changes.</text></s> <s sid="157"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, in order to get comparable results the following procedure was chosen: A height profile was measured across the centre of a cluster parallel to the scan direction in order to decrease the influence of thermal drift.</text></s> <s sid="158"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The height profile was numerically fitted by a Gaussian function and the full width at half height of the fit was assumed to be the relative diameter of the cluster.</text></s> <s sid="159"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The described procedure requires, as well as the height measurements in section 3.3.1, a sufficient non-covered area between the clusters and that is why it is only possible at low palladium coverage.</text></s> <s sid="160"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to exclude tip change influences and to achieve comparability with the height measurements we took the same three clusters for the determination of the bias dependence of the cluster diameter as we took for the bias dependence of the cluster height (see Fig. 11a).</text></s> <s sid="161"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As can be seen in Fig. 11b the apparent diameter of the clusters decreases when the bias is changed from 0.7 V to 1.5 V. Above that range the diameter starts to increase again before it finally drops rapidly for the single- and the four-layer clusters.</text></s> <s sid="162"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This leads eventually to an almost complete vanishing of the single-layer cluster.</text></s> <s sid="163"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Qualitatively the apparent size of the particles shows the same trend as for the height measurements.</text></s> <s sid="164"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, we suggest that the variations are also due to the complex tunneling junction.</text></s> <s sid="165"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to get a better understanding of the phenomena encountered here STS measurements could be very helpful because they would indicate to what extend the electronic states of the cluster and alumina, respectively, are involved in the tunneling process at a certain bias voltage.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Summary</HEADER><P><s sid="166"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We have investigated the influence of the long-range superstructure of a thin alumina film grown on the Ni3Al(111) surface on the nucleation and growth process of vapor deposited palladium.</text></s> <s sid="167"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It has been shown that the protrusions of the so-called “dot structure” present strong traps for the stable Pd nuclei and, hence, the sites for the Pd cluster growth.</text></s> <s sid="168"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A quantitative description of the nucleation process as a function of temperature and Pd flux suggests that heterogeneous nucleation is the dominant process.</text></s> <s sid="169"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The presented alumina film on Ni3Al(111) can be employed to fabricate nanostructured arrays of nearly monodisperse Pd clusters with a long-range hexagonal order.</text></s> <s sid="170"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It has also been shown that in order to grow the desired nanostructures a rapid decoration of the nucleation centers, e.g. by using a high flux, is crucial.</text></s></P><P><s sid="171"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore we have shown that due to the complex nature of the tunneling junction the bias voltage is an important parameter when imaging clusters on thin oxide films.</text></s> <s sid="172"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It appears that as long as the bias is chosen such that tunneling proceeds through the gap of the oxide the height of the clusters is only a little distorted whereas the apparent diameter of the clusters does not seem to be a reliable measure even under these circumstances.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>