<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b303587p" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Electron exchange between two electrodes mediated by two electroactive adsorbates</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Experimental data for electron exchange between two electrodes covered by electroactive films are presented and discussed in terms of the Gerischer model.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A model Hamiltonian is proposed for such indirect electron exchange involving two intermediate species.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Explicit model calculations are performed for the case in which the coupling between the two adsorbates is weak and determines the overall rate.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The calculations agree well with the experimental data, and can be used to determine the energy of reorganization associated with the electron transfer.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1">Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At present, much research is focused on the development of nanotechnology in general and of molecular-sized transistors in particular.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As early as 1974 Aviram and Rattner<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/> had pointed out that electron transfer through donor–acceptor systems may exhibit current rectification, an effect which could be used in nanoscale electronic devices.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A good view over the current activities in this field can be obtained from the collection of papers in and the theory is well summarized in the recent review by Nitzan.<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The construction of molecular electronic devices requires a source and a drain, and one or more localized electronic levels.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The roles of source and drain can be taken by two electrodes, which may take the form of tips of scanning tunneling microscopes.</text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>Working in an electrochemical environment has the advantage, that two potential differences can be controlled individually: the bias voltage between the two electrodes, and the potential drop between one electrode and the solution, in practice between one working and one reference electrode.</text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="None" advantage="Yes"/><text>Functionalized adsorbates attached to the electrodes can provide the electronic levels required to construct molecular devices on a nanotechnological scale.</text></s></P><P><s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this work we treat a particular system of interest to nanotechnological applications: two metal electrodes covered by films of adsorbates containing electroactive centers, and consider electron exchange mediated by these centers.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We have realized this process in a system consisting of two mercury electrodes covered by electroactive films and obtained unusual current-potential characteristics.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Various possibilities for electron exchange under such circumstances have recently been discussed by Kuznetsov and Ulstrup,<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit7"/> and a model for both elastic and inelastic transitions has been proposed by one of us.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The experimental situation corresponds to the case in which the coupling between the two adsorbed states is weaker than that of the adsorbates to their substrates.</text></s></P><P><s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rest of this paper is organized as follows: First we present our experimental results and discuss them qualitatively within the Gerischer model of electrochemical electron transfer.<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then we propose a model Hamiltonian for the indirect exchange via two adsorbates and present explicit model calculations for the experimental situation.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2">Experiments and qualitative discussions</HEADER><P><s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Full details of the experiments will be given elsewhere;<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit10"/> here we merely summarize those facts that are needed for understanding the electron transfer aspects.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The system consisted of two hanging mercury electrodes, whose relative position could be controlled by micrometers.</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Monolayers of [Ru(NH3)5(NC5H4CH2NHCO(CH2)10SH][PF6] were deposited onto the electrodes by self-assembly (see Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hg–SAM//SAM–Hg junctions were formed by bringing the two electrodes into intimate contact.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Ru-complexes served as intermediate states for electron exchange between the two electrodes.</text></s></P><P><s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Two kinds of experiments were performed: In the first experiment both electrodes were initially held at the same potential in the reduction region for the redox species.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The potential of the first electrode was kept fixed, while that of the other was scanned into the oxidation region (see Fig. 2).</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When the potential of the second electrode approached the equilibrium potential φ0 for the Ru2+/3+ couple, the current began to rise and reached a constant value when the potential was well beyond φ0.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, the whole current–potential curve has a sigmoidal shape.</text></s></P><P><s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the second experiment initially both electrodes were again held at a potential in the reduction region, but a bias of 100 mV was applied between them.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then, both potentials were swept at constant bias in the positive direction (see Fig. 3).</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This resulted in current potential-curves of a roughly Gaussian shape with a peak near the equilibrium potential φ0.</text></s></P><P><s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Qualitatively these results can be understood within the Gerischer model for electrochemical electron transfer.<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Here, an electroactive species is characterized by densities Dred(ε) of reduced and Dox(ε) oxidized states, which have the Gaussian form familiar from Marcus theory.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Each Gaussian has a width of (4λkBT)1/2, where λ is the energy of reorganization.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At equilibrium, Dred(ε) is centered at an energy of −λ below the Fermi level of the electrode, while Dox(ε) is centered at ε = λ.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the relation of this model to the Marcus theory, see .<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit11"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There are two equivalent sets of redox systems in these experiments.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since the self-assembled layers have a low conductivity, we may safely assume that both sets are at the same electrode potential; hence the densities D1red(ε) and D2red(ε) are the same, and so are the corresponding densities of oxidized states (see Fig. 4a).</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A change in the potential of either electrode simply shifts its Fermi level with respect to these densities of states.</text></s></P><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Electron transfer occurs from the reduced levels of system 1 to the oxidized levels of system 2, or vice versa, and is therefore determined by the product: where the common Fermi level of the two redox systems has been taken as the energy zero.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The current passing between the two tips is then proportional to the integral taken between the Fermi levels of the two electrodes (see Fig. 4b): From these considerations the two experiments outlined above are easy to understand: In the first experiment we start with the Fermi levels of both metals well above the center of Dp(ε), so there are no empty states to tunnel into, and the current is zero.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As the Fermi level of the second electrode is lowered, empty states become available, and the current rises until the Fermi level has passed well below the maximum of Dp(ε); all the states pertaining to system 1 are full, those belonging to system 2 are empty, and the current reaches a limiting value.</text></s></P><P><s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the second experiment the energy window between the two metal Fermi levels is kept constant and scanned across Dp(ε).</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hence the current practically maps Dp(ε) with some distortion caused by the finite width of the window.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Obviously, the second experiment is particularly suited to determine the energy of reorganization, since Dp(ε) has a width of (2λkBT)1/2.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3">Model Hamiltonian</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>While these qualitative considerations suffice to understand the experiments at hand it is desirable to have a quantitative formulation in terms of a model Hamiltonian.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For this purpose we introduce the following terminology: We label the two adsorbates ‘1’ and ‘2’; species 1 is adsorbed on a metal, whose electronic states are labeled by l, species 2 on a metal with electronic states k.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Let ni, i = 1, 2, l, k denote the corresponding number operators, and εi the associated energies; then the Hamiltonian for the non-interacting electrons is: Electrons can be exchanged along the chain: k → 1 → 2 → l and in the reverse direction.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is effected by the transfer Hamiltonian: where c* and c denote creation and annihilation operators, and V an appropriate coupling strength.</text></s></P><P><s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Electron exchange between the adsorbates involves reorganization of the solvent, and perhaps also of a few inner sphere modes.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These are represented by a phonon bath that interacts with the two electronic states on the adsorbates: Here, pν and qν denote the dimensionless momenta and coordinates of the phonons, and gν1, gν2 are the coupling constants for the indicated states.</text></s></P><P><s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total Hamiltonian for our system is given by the sum of the terms listed above: <EQN ID="eqn6"><EQ-S ID="s50">H = Hel + HT + Hph</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P><P><s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From this Hamiltonian, a few quantities can be defined.</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the two states we define reorganization energies through: λ1 = ∑νℏωνg2ν1/2, λ2 = ∑ν ħωνg2ν2/2.</text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper we will neglect a possible overlap of the solvation spheres and assume gν1gν2 = 0 for all ν.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This assumption is in accord with the simple interpretation in terms of the Gerischer model.</text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The effect of solvation overlap has been considered elsewhere.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit8"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The interaction of the two reactive species with the metals on which they are adsorbed can be characterized by: We employ the so-called wide band approximation,<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit12"/> in which Δ1 and Δ2 are taken as constant.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is a good approximation when these quantities are much smaller than the electronic bands in the two metals, which is generally the case.</text></s></P><P><s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In general, the densities of reduced and oxidized states are governed both by the energy of reorganization λ and by the energy width Δ.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, in our experimental situation the active species as separated from the electrodes by the alkanethiol chains; hence Δ ≪ λ, and the exact value for Δ that is chosen in any calculation is not important as long as it is sufficiently small.</text></s></P><P><s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As is common in electron-transfer theory, we have neglected spin.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is permissible if the energy widths Δ1 and Δ2 are much smaller than the repulsive interaction energy between two electrons on the same valence orbital.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="4">Model calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A full treatment of our model in terms of scattering theory has been given elsewhere.<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This includes also quantum effects such as inelastic electron transfer, which can be derived from our model Hamiltonian but will not be considered here.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the following we will limit ourselves to elastic transitions involving only classical modes, which can explain the experimental data at hand.</text></s></P><P><s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total reaction comprises three electronic transitions.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In accord with our qualitative discussion presented above we consider the case in which the coupling between the two adsorbates is weaker than the interaction of the two adsorbates with their respective substrates.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This entails electronic equilibrium between the adsorbates and their substrates, and the two states 1 and 2, including their solvation shells, move effectively on their adiabatic free-energy surfaces, which are given by:<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit13"/> where the i = 1, 2, and qi denotes the generalized solvent coordinate associated with the state i.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From standard statistical mechanics we can calculate the probability Pi(xi) that at a particular time the system i is at a coordinate xi.</text></s></P><P><s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since the two adsorbates are chemically identical, we have λ1 = λ2, Δ1 = Δ2, ε1 = ε2, but in general 〈n1〉 ≠ 〈n2〉 since the Fermi levels of the two electrodes differ by the bias potential.</text></s></P><P><s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To be specific, we consider electron transfer from system 1 to system 2.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The corresponding current is then given by:<EQN ID="eqn9"><EQ-S ID="s72">i ∝ ∫P1(x)〈n1〉P2(x)(1 − 〈n2〉)dx</EQ-S></EQN>where we have used the fact that electron transfer occurs elastically from an occupied to an empty state.</text></s></P><P><s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>With the aid of these equations, we have performed model calculations corresponding to the experimental data.</text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In Fig. 5 we show the effect of raising the bias while keeping the potential of electrode 1 fixed.</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In accord with the experiments and with the qualitative calculations, the current reaches a constant value for a large bias, and has an overall sigmoidal shape.</text></s></P><P><s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Of greater interest is the variation of the current with electrode potential at constant bias (see Fig. 6).</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The current response is roughly Gaussian, its width is the wider, the larger the energy of reorganization λ, and, of course, the larger the bias.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The dependence on λ makes it possible to compare experimental and theoretical curves, and extract the energy of reorganization from the data.</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As shown in Fig. 7, the experimental data can be fitted quite well to a value of λ ≈ 0.4 eV, which is a reasonable value for this redox system.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="5">Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Advances in the preparation of self-assembled monolayers and in the formation of pairs of electrode with an ultrathin gap has made it possible to study indirect electron exchange involving two intermediate species.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Such system exhibit current-potential characteristics that could, in principle, be used for molecular electronics.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In particular, scanning the bias can result in diode-like behavior.</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The presented experimental results can be understood within as semiclassical version of a theory for such processed proposed by one of us<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit8"/>.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>