<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b308699b" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Conductive thin films of θ-(BETS)4[Fe(CN)5NO] on silicon electrodes – new perspectives on charge transfer salts</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An alternate electrodeposition method using large surface silicon electrodes as anodes to prepare thin films of radical cation salts has been developed.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We report on its use for the preparation of the radical cation salt containing the BETS molecule [BETS = bis(ethylenedithio)tetraselenafulvalene] and the photochromic nitroprusside [Fe(CN)5NO]2− anion, i.e. θ-(BETS)4[Fe(CN)5NO].</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of various techniques, such as SEM/EDX, XPS, X-ray, IR and Raman, unambiguously confirmed that the film is made of the θ-(BETS)4[Fe(CN)5NO] phase previously obtained as single crystals on platinum electrodes.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results show that it is possible to electrodeposit cation radical salts on silicon wafers.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, this new method of electrodeposition proves to be extremely useful for preparing the large amounts of product (several hundreds of milligrams) often required for physical measurements.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A recent development in the research on molecular conductors concerns the possibility to create solids in which conductivity (or superconductivity) coexists with other physical phenomena.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An approach involving conducting radical cation salts with photochromic anions has been recently explored.<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/><REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The interest of new molecular conductors containing photochromic anions resides in the influence of the electronic excitation of the anions over the conducting (superconducting) electrons.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, one can imagine the design of a photochromic molecular conductor (or even a superconductor) in which the conducting properties can be tuned by light.</text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Moreover, the preparation of these materials as thin films is of high interest for potential device application.</text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Light-emitting diodes, nonlinear optical materials and field-effect transistors are a few examples of reported devices using thin organic film technology.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit7"/></text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Much effort is currently being devoted to the processing of thin films of molecule-based materials via thermal evaporation under high vacuum,<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit8"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit9"/> chemical vapour deposition,<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit11"/> dip-coating<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit12"/> or Langmuir–Blodgett techniques.<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit13"/></text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, these procedures have several limitations.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No"/><text>In particular, they cannot be used when an electrochemical process is involved.</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>In this context, Wang et al. have recently reported a new approach to the preparation of films of charge transfer salts such as (BEDT)2PF6 [BEDT = bis(ethylenedithio)tetrathiafulvalene] using a gold electrode (surface: 0.5 cm2).<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit14"/></text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Moreover, preparation of thin single crystals by confined electrocrystallisation has also been published.<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit15a"/><REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit15b"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In parallel, we have developed an alternate electrodeposition method using large surface silicon electrodes as anodes to prepare thin films of radical cation salts.</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Intrinsic-type silicon wafers have a high enough conductivity (10−3 S cm−1) to be used as electrodes.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>Doped-type silicon wafers can also be used as they may be of interest for specific applications.</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>As large surface electrodes are concerned, the use of silicon affords evident benefits versus platinum or gold in terms of maintenance and cost.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>Moreover, galvanostatic electrodeposition allows control of the deposited thickness, which mainly depends on electrolysis duration.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, we considered two different goals: (i) growth of a thin film and (ii) large scale preparation.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The first goal is of interest for future applications, silicon still being the substrate of choice in the electronic world for many years to come.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The second goal is extremely useful to prepare the large amounts of product (several hundreds of milligrams) often required for physical measurements, when electrolysis is the only possible synthetic route.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We illustrate this new application of silicon wafers in the case of the preparation of the radical cation salt containing the BETS molecule [BETS = bis(ethylenedithio) tetraselenafulvalene] and the photochromic nitroprusside [Fe(CN)5NO]2− anion, that is θ-(BETS)4[Fe(CN)5NO].</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>This compound is a typical example of molecule-based materials that would benefit from both thin film processing and large scale preparation to explore potential photochromic behaviour.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As a matter of fact, when associated with cations such as Na+, the nitroprusside anion is known to exhibit extremely long-lived metastable excited states at low temperatures that can be generated by laser irradiation.<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit16"/><REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit17"/></text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, in this paper, we will focus on the preparation method and compare the properties of the deposit versus those of the single crystals previously obtained on Pt wire electrodes<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit6"/>.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Electrodeposition procedure</HEADER><P><s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Electrodeposition is carried out using an intrinsic silicon (100) (Siltronix) one-face-polished wafer (diameter 5 cm, thickness 275 µm) as anode and a platinum wire as cathode.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The silicon wafer is stripped in a NH4F–HF solution (12.5percent HF 50percent and 87.5percent NH4F 40percent) then washed in distilled water before use.</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Cleaning of the cathode is performed by treatment with aqua regia, followed by successive anodic and cathodic polarisation of the electrode in dilute sulfuric acid.</text></s></P><P><s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(PPh4)2[Fe(CN)5NO] is obtained by reaction of Na2[Fe(CN)5NO] (Aldrich) with (PPh4)Cl in water.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>BETS is prepared as previously reported.<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit18"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Solutions of BETS (62 mg) and (PPh4)2[Fe(CN)5NO] (520 mg) in 1,1,2-trichloroethane (230 mL)–ethanol (22 mL) are introduced into a Schlenk-type cylindrical one-compartment (400 ml) electrochemical cell.</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solvents are freshly distilled and 1,1,2-trichloroethane is further run through Al2O3.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The galvanostatic oxidation of the donor is performed at 25 °C and at a current density of 0.1 µA cm−2.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Within 2 days, microcrystals are observable and grow homogeneously on the silicon electrode.</text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A 1 µm thin film is obtained after typically 7 days of electrolysis.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When the electrolysis is conducted for 4 weeks on a silicon surface (diameter 5 cm), typically 60 mg of product can be collected by scratching the substrate using a glass slide.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Characterisation methods</HEADER><P><s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Infrared spectra are obtained on powder (scratched from the Si surface) dispersed in KBr matrix, using a Perkin–Elmer Spectrum GX spectrophotometer.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Raman measurements are carried out at room temperature with a Raman spectrometer (DILOR XY micro Raman) equipped with a Kr laser (λ = 6472 Å, laser power density: 5 × 104 W cm−2).</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>XPS spectra were recorded using a VG Escalab Model MK2 spectrophotometer (Mg Kα radiation: 1253.6 eV).</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The SEM images are obtained on a JEOL model JSM 840A.</text></s></P><P><s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The X-Ray diffraction studies were performed both on the single crystal powder and film/substrate composite.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>XRD data were collected with a Seifert XRD 3000 TT, fitted with a diffracted beam monochromator and using Cu Kα radiation (1.5418 Å).</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the case of powder analysis, the diffractometer is in Bragg–Brentano configuration (θ/θ), while it is in grazing incidence configuration (ω = 2°) for film analysis.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The powder sample is spread on a glass sample holder and the film on the silicon sample is placed on a height adjustable holder.</text></s></P><P><s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Conductivity measurements were performed using the standard four-probe method between room temperature and 77 K. Electrical contacts between the gold wires and the film were made by using gold paste.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>They were drawn parallel to each other and the film morphology allowed a large inter-wire distance (≈1 mm).</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to compare the film conductivity with that of the substrate, the conductivity of the silicon wafer was measured separately and found to be 10−3 S cm−1, as given by the supplier (Siltronix) for intrinsic-type silicon.</text></s></P><P><s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Except for the IR investigation, all the characterisations are made on the film on substrate samples.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Crystals of θ-(BETS)4[Fe(CN)5NO], previously obtained by the electrocrystallisation technique using standard platinum wire electrodes, appear as thick blocks and a few other diamond- and hexagonal-plate shaped phases.</text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The compound behaves as a metal down to ca.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>40 K with σRT = 10−2 S cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Its crystal and electronic structures have already been reported.<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same cell parameters were found whatever the morphology of the crystals.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further characterisation under irradiation are under progress, but they are limited by the difficulty of obtaining sufficient amounts of compound.</text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A common electrocrystallisation experiment produces about 3 mg of product.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to increase the amount of product, we used a 5 cm diameter silicon wafer as the anode and a platinum wire as the cathode.</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The electrodes were placed in a one-compartment cell containing a solution of the donor and the nitroprusside salt.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Within few days, a deposit made up of microcrystals (Fig. 1) formed homogeneously on both the polished and non-polished faces of the silicon electrode.</text></s></P><P><s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sample was washed with ethanol and acetone; the deposit does not spontaneously peel off from the silicon surface.</text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of a large surface anode was effective in terms of quantity of product: about 60 mg of product is obtained for each experiment.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This quite large amount of product allowed us to use numerous techniques to characterise the film and compare its chemical nature to that of the crystals previously obtained.<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit6"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>SEM images showed that the deposit uniformly covers the surface of the substrate (Fig. 2).</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It consists of a thin film made of platelets of irregular shapes but also of diamond- and hexagonal-shaped single crystals as previously evidenced.<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>EDX analysis confirmed the presence of S, Se and Fe within the microcrystals.</text></s></P><P><s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>XPS analysis of the films gave atomic S/Se and Fe/N ratios of 1.09 and 0.19, respectively, in very good agreement with the theoretical values in the BETS (ratio 1) and Fe(CN)5NO (ratio 0.17) moieties.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A least-squares fit deconvolution with Gaussians of the S 2p signal rendered two components at 163.1 and 164.2 eV, very close to those observed for thin films of TTF derivatives.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit19a"/><REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit19b"/></text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A similar treatment for the N 1s signal gave two components at 397.7 and 398.8 eV (Fig. 3).</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The first line is attributed to the nitrogen atoms of the cyano ligands whereas the second peak is assigned to the nitrogen atom of the NO ligand.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fe 2p3/2 has a binding energy of 708.6 eV, in agreement with that of Feii or Feiii complexes bearing NO ligands.<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit20"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The structure of the film and that of a powder obtained by electrocrystallisation on a classical platinum wire electrode were analysed by X-ray powder diffraction at room temperature using Cu Kα radiation.</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In both cases, the diffraction patterns showed broad peaks, indicative of small particle sizes (Fig. 4).</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous calibration of the diffractometer and application of the Scherrer equation gave a crystallite mean size of ca.</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>80 Å.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In both diagrams, we noticed an extra diffraction line [at 2θ = 8.197°, (011) line] due to traces of BETS starting material (this was verified from the XRD diagram of a pure sample of BETS).</text></s></P><P><s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to compare the cell parameters of the powder sample to those previously found in the single crystal study,<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit6"/> the data were refined with the Checkcell program.<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The peak broadness (due to the small crystallite size and defocusing grazing configuration of the diffractometer) causes overlapping of the diffraction lines (added to the obvious preferred orientation of the film) and so prevents from getting a highly precise result.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the same C2/c space group determined for the single crystal, the calculated parameters for the film are: a = 40.01(5), b = 4.205(8), c = 11.775(9) Å, β = 97.55(3)° and U = 1964(6) Å3.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These are to be compared with: a = 40.259(8), b = 4.1768(7), c = 11.599(2) Å, β = 97.23(2)° and U = 1934.9(6) Å3 obtained in .<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From the powder diagram data, and in the C2/c space group, the calculated parameters are: a = 40.44(2), b = 4.190(2), c = 11.785(5) Å, β = 98.29(3)° and U = 1976(2) Å3.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As the single crystal study has been performed at 160 K and the powder and the film ones at room temperature, the slight expansion of the cell (≈42 Å3, 2percent) seems quite normal.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Even if the film diagram displays a preferential orientation (Fig. 4b), the similarity of the data (same position for the detected diffraction lines in film and powder) indicates that the two samples are identified with the same phase.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We can then conclude that the film contains the same θ-(BETS)4[Fe(CN)5NO] phase as the single crystal previously studied.</text></s></P><P><s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The infrared spectrum of crystals collected from the silicon electrode and dispersed in a KBr matrix evidenced two absorptions at 2963 and 2924 cm−1, identified as the CH2 stretching modes.</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the 2100–2200 cm−1 range, two bands are present (2144 and 2134 cm−1), which are assigned to the νCN stretching vibrations.</text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The presence of the NO ligand is confirmed by a νNO absorption at 1941 cm−1 (Fig. 5).</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the 1200–1500 cm−1 range, a triplet of bands is observed (1454, 1351 and 1261 cm−1).</text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A similar triplet, assigned to the coupling of the CC vibrations with the conduction electrons, has been evidenced for κ-(BETS)2FeCl4.<REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit22"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Raman spectra were recorded at VV polarisation after focusing the incident laser beam onto the deposit through the microscope objective, giving a spot size of 1 µm2.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>No major degradation of the sample was observed.</text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The data confirmed the presence of both the BETS and Fe(CN)5NO moieties within the deposit.</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The spectrum is dominated by a strong broad signal centred at 1470 cm−1 (Fig. 6), which is ascribed to the stretching of the double bonds in the central and peripheral fragments of BETS.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For neutral BETS, strong CC modes are observed in the 1490–1530 cm−1 range.<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit22"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The lower observed CC frequency for the films is in agreement with the cationic character of the BETS moiety.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A similar frequency shift due to the charge transfer between donor and acceptor molecules has been observed for thin films of TTF[Ni(dmit)2]2.<REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit23"/></text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Medium-intensity bands are evidenced at 439, 479 (νFe–C) and 638 (νFe–N) cm−1, assigned by comparison with the Raman spectrum of Na2[Fe(CN)5NO].<REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit16"/></text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Several medium- or low-intensity features are present in the 800–1000 cm−1 range.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>They are related to both νC–S and νC–Se stretching modes and to δC–C–S and δS–C–Se deformation modes present in the Raman spectrum of κ-(BETS)2FeCl4.<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Moreover, a weak band at 2134 cm−1 is assigned to the CN vibrational modes.</text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It should be pointed out that the orientation of the microcrystals on the substrate favours the presence of this latter band.</text></s></P><P><s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Conductivity has been measured directly on the microcrystalline film grown on the silicon wafer using the standard four-probe technique.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The conductivity of the film is about 1.6 S cm−1 at room temperature (Fig. 7), well above that of the Si substrate (10−3 S cm−1).</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This value shows the high intrinsic conductivity of the material compared to the 10−2 S cm−1 value obtained on a single crystal and the 5 × 10−2 S cm−1 measured on the compacted powder.</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Despite the low conductivity of inter-fiber or inter-grain contacts within the film, the two orders of magnitude variation observed between the crystal and the film is attributed to the fact that the measurement on the single crystal was not performed along the most favourable conductive direction.</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The shape and the size (0.4 × 0.2 × 0.05 mm3) of the crystal did not allow other orientations.</text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast, the microcrystals seem to grow on the silicon wafer in a favourable orientation versus the substrate plane.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Moreover, the semiconductive thermal behaviour (Ea = 0.03 eV) compared to the metallic one observed in the single crystal means that the overall electric behaviour of the material is affected by the inter-grain contacts.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This has been already observed in films of TTF–TCNQ<REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit24"/>.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusion</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We have reported on the use of silicon wafers as electrodes to grow thin films of molecule-based materials by electrodeposition.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This is illustrated in the case of the preparation and characterisation of a BETS-based radical cation salt containing the photochromic nitroprusside anion, obtained as an adherent thin film on a silicon wafer.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of various techniques, as SEM/EDX, XPS, X-Ray, IR and Raman, unambiguously confirmed that the film is made of the θ-(BETS)4[Fe(CN)5NO] phase previously obtained as single crystals on platinum electrodes.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results show that it is possible to electrodeposit cation radical salts on silicon wafers.</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, this new method of electrodeposition proved to be extremely useful for preparing the large amounts of product (several hundreds of milligrams) often required for physical measurements.</text></s> <s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This method can be extended to other molecular systems.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Growth and characterisation of other kinds of films are in progress.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>