<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b308032n" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Characterization of metal complexes with metallothioneins in the liver of the carp Cyprinus carpio by reversed-phase HPLC with ICP-MS and electrospray ionization (ESI)-MS</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Inductively coupled plasma time-of-flight mass spectrometry (ICP-TOFMS) and electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (ESI-MS) were used in parallel in combination with two-dimensional chromatography (size-exclusion followed by reversed-phase HPLC) for the characterization of metal complexes with metallothionein (MT) isoforms in hepatic cytosols of Cd exposed carp.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The cytosolic MT fraction was partially purified by size-exclusion (SE) HPLC, preconcentrated and de-salted by centrifugal microfiltration.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The separation of the metal complexes with MT isoforms was performed by reversed-phase (RP) HPLC using a gradient up to 30percent methanol in acetate buffer (pH 7.4).</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Two major and several minor chromatographic peaks were distinguished by RP-HPLC-ICP-TOFMS within a chromatographic run of 20 min.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Applying ESI-MS as a detector for RP HPLC allowed the identification of the two major signals detected by ICP-MS on the basis of the molecular mass determined on-line for the metallocomplex(es) and for the ligand.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Mass spectra taken at the peak apices indicated the co-elution of different metal (Cd, Cu, Zn and Pb) complexes with MT isoforms within each peak.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>A simple “in-source” protein oxidation procedure was used to obtain the ligand of the complexes (oxidized form) on arrival at the detector; direct information was obtained on the molecular mass of two MT isoforms in carp liver, allowing their identification.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>The efficiency and robustness of this method were demonstrated using a rabbit liver MT1 standard as test sample.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The development of analytical approaches to studying the bioavailability and the environmental impact of metal(loids) on living organisms offers a continuing challenge for environmental analytical chemistry and eco- and clinical toxicology.</text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To elucidate the mechanisms that control the uptake of metal(loids) by organisms exposed to environmental metal pollution as well as metal transport, metabolism and detoxification processes, reliable information is needed about trace-element speciation of biomolecules with specific functions in the cell.</text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>New analytical methodologies for detection, quantitation, identification and characterization of metal(loids) complexed with or incorporated into biomolecules are therefore required.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Metallothioneins (MT) are low-molecular weight proteins capable of binding trace metals in the cells of a wide range of prokaryotes and eukaryotes, including plants, invertebrates and vertebrates.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Environmental studies involving metallothioneins in aquatic organisms show the potential use of these biomolecules as specific biomarkers of trace metal exposure.<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/><REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit8"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The affinity of MT for heavy metals such as Zn, Cd, Hg, Pb and Cu, and their capacity for bioaccumulation in aquatic organisms, is well known.</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The exposure of aquatic organisms to excess essential and non-essential metals induces MT expression in different species and tissues.</text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The additional fact that MT are intrinsic to most species makes them a possible candidate to serve as an indicator of environmental exposure to metals and also as a biomarker of metal pollution.<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit4"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Most fish populations are considered less suitable candidates as bioindicators of environmental contamination gradients than many invertebrates because of their mobility and the strong influence of other conditions (e.g., water temperature and pH) besides metals, that could potentially result in MT induction in fish.</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the benefits of increased sensitivity and more readily measured responses to metals, in fish, outweigh these features.<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit7"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The number of investigations on the applicability of MT induction in fish species to assess the environmental toxicity of metals has aroused increasing interest in ecotoxicology and environmental monitoring during the last 10 years.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit11"/><REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Ideally, information about indicator species could be used to assess adverse effects on the species themselves, on other components of the ecosystem and on humans.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unfortunately, the information on multi-element metal speciation of MT and MT isoform composition in fish is still scarce, limiting the study of the function and metal binding capacity of the different MT isoforms.</text></s></P><P><s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The on-line coupling of size-exclusion liquid chromatography with inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS) for real-time element-specific detection of different molecular weight fractions in animal cytosols, together with further fractionation/purification of the MT fraction by complementary separation techniques (anion-exchange, reversed-phase (RP) HPLC or capillary electrophoresis (CE)), coupled with ICP-MS, has become a popular approach to detect and verify the chromatographic purity of MT species.<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit14"/><REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit15"/></text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>On-line isotope dilution in combination with the hyphenation of CE or reversed phase HPLC to ICP-MS has proved to be a reliable method for quantitative metal speciation of rat liver and standard rabbit liver MT isoforms.<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit16"/><REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit17"/></text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>Quantification of MT via sulfur measurements is possible with this approach when using ICP-sector field (SF) MS instruments.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit16"/></text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Identification and characterization of the metal complexes with MT isoforms detected by ICP-MS have been mostly performed by using electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (ESI-MS) as a molecule-specific detector for chromatography (CE or reversed-phase HPLC).<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit18"/><REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit19"/><REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit20"/><REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit21"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Most research on the characterization of MT polymorphism has been devoted to MT standard preparations and mammalian cytosols for which standards of MT are commercially available.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Despite several works using the powerful combination of element- and molecule-specific MS detectors with chromatography for investigations of MT and its isoforms in mammals, the characterization of MT isoforms in fish remains a challenging issue.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The characterization of MT isoforms is a difficult task because of (i) problems regarding the conservation of MT expression and the purification of this metalloprotein in the presence of other metal-binding ligands, and (ii) the possible influence of biotic and abiotic factors that are likely to interfere with MT synthesis in fish in response to metal exposure which should be controlled.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Moreover, the amount of sample obtained from target organs in fish is often very limited in comparison to mammals.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, a larger preconcentration than in the latter case may be required to prepare fish samples for LC-ESI-MS analysis.</text></s></P><P><s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper the complementarity of ICP-time-of-flight (TOF)MS and ESI-MS combined with two-dimensional chromatography (size-exclusion followed by reversed-phase HPLC) is investigated for the characterization of metal complexes with MT isoforms in hepatic cytosols of carp exposed to waterborne Cd.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The investigation of the origin of signals in chromatograms of fish cytosols (containing Cd, Zn, Cu and Pb) obtained by LC-ICP-MS was for the first time attempted using complementary ESI-MS detection.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>A simple “in-source” oxidation procedure using a Cs-coated electrospray capillary allowed the ligand of the complexes (the oxidized form) to be obtained on arrival at the detector.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>The efficiency and robustness of this approach were tested through the identification of metal complexes with MT1 standard from rabbit liver.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Instrumentation</HEADER><P><s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>HPLC was performed with a Shimadzu (Kyoto, Japan) PEEK solvent delivery module LC-10Ai equipped with a FCV-10AL quaternary valve and a Rheodyne Model 7125 PEEK sample injector (Rohnert Park, CA, USA) fitted with a 50 µl eluent loop.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Size-exclusion HPLC was performed with a SUPELCO (Bornem, Belgium) TSK gel G 3000 PWxL gel-filtration column (7.8 mm id × 30 cm, 6 µm particle size).</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Reversed-phase HPLC was performed with a Spherisorb ODS 2 column (250 mm × 4.6 mm, 5 µm particle size: type PEEK) (Alltech, Lokeren, Belgium).</text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The reversed-phase HPLC column was directly connected to the nebulizer of the ICP-MS instrument via PEEK tubing (0.5 mm id × 7 cm).</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The effluent of the RP HPLC column (0.6 ml min−1) was split by a laboratory-made splitter (split ratio 1 ∶ 50) and fed into the electrospray source.</text></s></P><P><s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>ESI-MS experiments were performed using an Autospec-oa-TOF mass spectrometer (Micromass, Manchester, UK) of SF/TOF configuration, equipped with an ESI source.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>For direct analysis, analyte solutions were introduced into the source by means of a 100 µl syringe (Hamilton, Reno, NV, USA) and a Harvard Apparatus (South Natick, MA, USA) Model 22 syringe infusion pump at a constant flow rate of 5 µl min−1.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Data acquisition and processing were performed using OPUS V3.6X Software (Micromass).</text></s></P><P><s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>An axial ICP-TOFMS (Renaissance, LECO, St. Joseph, MI, USA), fitted with a Meinhard nebulizer, was used as the element-specific detector.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>The optimal ICP-TOFMS, ESI-MS and chromatographic separation conditions are summarized in Table 1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Microcon centrifugal filters (3000 Da membranes) (Millipore, Brussels, Belgium) and an Eppendorf centrifuge Model 5804 R (VWR International, Leuven, Belgium) were used for sample preconcentration and desalting.</text></s></P><P><s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The instrumentation for preparation of cytosols was as described in a previous paper<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit10"/>.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Reagents and standards</HEADER><P><s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Methanol (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) was of LC gradient grade.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Doubly de-ionized water (18.2 MΩ cm) obtained from a Milli-Q water system (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA) was used throughout.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All the reagents used were of the highest available purity.</text></s></P><P><s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Metallothionein 1 (80K7012) and metallothionein 2 (052K7002) preparations (isolated from rabbit liver and essentially salt-free; Cd content 7.9 and 6.5percent; Zn content 1.4 and 1.6percent) were purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA).</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sample vial contents were dissolved in ultra-pure water (to prepare 1 mg ml−1 MT solution), kept in a refrigerator at 4 °C and filtered using 0.45 µm cellulose acetate syringe filters (Alltech) just before use.</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Ammonium acetate, used for preparation of the mobile phase, and phenylmethanesulfonylfluoride (PMSF; protease inhibitor) and 2-mercaptoethanol (antioxidant), used for preparation of cytosols, were purchased from Sigma.</text></s></P><P><s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The buffer solution was prepared by dissolving 30 mmol l−1 of ammonium acetate in water containing 1percent (v/v) methanol (buffer A) and in methanol (buffer B), adjusting the pH to 7.4 with concentrated ammonia and acetic acid and degassing with helium for 20 min before use.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Suprapur acetic acid (100percent m/m) and ammonia (25percent m/m) used for pH adjustment of the mobile phases were purchased from Merck.</text></s></P><P><s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A 0.1percent (v/v) trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) solution, used for obtaining the apo-MT by off-line acidification, was prepared by dissolving concentrated TFA (Spectroscopy grade, Uvasol, Merck) in water–methanol (1 + 1, v/v).</text></s></P><P><s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For mass calibration of the ESI-MS instrument and for “in-source” oxidation of the MT species, a 10 mg l−1 caesium iodide (CsI) solution was prepared by dissolving an appropriate aliquot of CsI (Merck) in water–methanol (1 + 1, v/v).</text></s></P><P><s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the daily optimization of the ICP and TOFMS parameters a mass calibration solution of 100 µg l−1 Li, Mg, Sc, Co, Y, In, Ce, Ba, Pb, Bi and U, prepared from a 1000 mg l−1 multielement stock standard solution (Z-TEK, Amsterdam, The Netherlands), was used.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Procedures</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Carp samples pre-treatment</HEADER><P><s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fifteen carp were exposed to Cd (as CdCl2) in water (5 carp in a 25 l aquarium) at a concentration of 1 mg l−1 (as Cd), at 25 °C for 96 h.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Five carp, exposed to a concentration of 0 mg l−1 Cd under the same conditions, were used as control fish.</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The procedures used to expose the carp to waterborne Cd as well as to prepare and preserve the liver cytosols were as described elsewhere.<REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this work, precautions were taken to minimize analyte dilution at every step of the sample preparation procedure; liver tissues were homogenized in 2 volumes (v/m) of homogenization buffer.<REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Mercaptoethanol was used as antioxidant and phenylmethanesulfonylfluoride (PMSF) as protease inhibitor.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>MT fraction collection, preconcentration and desalting</HEADER><P><s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Freshly prepared cytosol samples of 50 µl were filtered (0.45 µm) and applied to the size-exclusion column.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The separation and elution of the different size fractions was achieved using 30 mmol l−1 Tris–HCl (pH 7.4, flow rate 0.8 ml min−1) as mobile phase, as described elsewhere.<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The HPLC effluent was collected in vials for 1.5 min (starting at 8.5 min) for partial purification of the MT fraction.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>De-gassing of this solution with helium just before desalting and preconcentration was performed to minimize risks of MT oxidation.</text></s></P><P><s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>500 µl of the MT cytosolic fraction (isolated by SE HPLC) were pipetted into the sample reservoir (containing a 3000 Da membrane) of a Microcon centrifugal filter device.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reservoir, inserted into a vial, was sealed with a cap and the assembly was then centrifuged at 13 000 g for 60 min at 4 °C.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>With the reservoir placed upside down in a new vial, centrifugation at 100 g for 5 min at 4 °C was performed to transfer the concentrate to the vial.</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Different concentrates were pooled and the centrifugal filtration procedure was repeated to achieve a maximum of 20-fold sample preconcentration.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>RP HPLC-ESI-MS analysis</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>“In-source” oxidized MT</HEADER><P><s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A 10 mg l−1 CsI solution was introduced at 5 µl min−1 by direct infusion into the electrospray source for 30 min in order to guarantee the efficient sorption of Cs on the electrospray capillary.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The ESI source was rinsed with a water-methanol (1 + 1, v/v) solution for 5 min and coupled with LC for monitoring of oxidized species.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>MT–metal complexes</HEADER><P><s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Prior to LC-ESI-MS analysis of the metallated MT species, the system was checked for the presence of remaining Cs and precautions were taken to avoid the presence of the element.</text></s></P><P><s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For analysis of both the metallated isoforms and the oxidized MT, 50 µl of the concentrate were injected and the separation and elution of the MT fractions was achieved by using a concentration gradient (1–30percent) of methanol within 20 min (see conditions in Table 1).</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A m/z range of 800–1800 was scanned, which allowed the observation of the +4 and +5 ionization states.</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Mass spectra were acquired with an accelerating voltage of 4000 V, a cone voltage of 40 V and using the magnetic sector at a scan speed of 1 decade s−1.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Nitrogen was used as bath gas (flow 250 l h−1) and as nebulizer gas (flow 15 l h−1).</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After analysis, buffer A was switched off for 20 min in order to re-equilibrate the column and the ESI source was rinsed with a water–methanol (1 + 1, v/v) solution before the next injection.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The common carp (Cyprinus carpio) was chosen as the test organism because of its abundance and wide distribution in Europe and its economic importance.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, the common carp has been approved as a test organism by the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), allowing the use of this fish species as “sentinel” organisms in monitoring programs.</text></s></P><P><s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The toxic metal cadmium, which has been recognized as one of the most deleterious heavy metals, has proved to be one of the most potent MT inducers in carp.</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous investigations of the importance of MT in the detoxification of Cd in common carp (Cyprinus carpio) after waterborne Cd exposure have demonstrated that the role of this protein in the detoxification process is clearly both organ- and isoform-specific.<REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Quantitative and qualitative speciation differences that were encountered between control and Cd exposed fish and the correlation of the speciation data with (i) MT concentrations in tissue and (ii) total Cd concentrations in water and tissue led to the conclusion that kidney is a more important organ than liver to be studied when using MT de novo synthesis in carp as an indicator of Cd exposure; the concentration of Cd bound to MT increases earlier in kidney than in the liver.<REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the induction of MT–metal complexes occurs at a significantly higher level in liver (after short-term exposure to 1 mg l−1 Cd) since this organ is more capable of sequestering the incoming Cd to MT than the kidney.</text></s></P><P><s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The full elucidation of the role that this metal-complexing metabolite plays in the cell requires, however, the identification of the MT isoforms that are specifically induced in carp tissue owing to metal stress.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper, identification of metal complexes with MT in hepatic cytosols of carp exposed to waterborne Cd was for the first time attempted using the combination of reversed-phase HPLC in parallel with ICP-TOFMS and ESI-MS.</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Previous size-exclusion HPLC-ICP-TOFMS analysis of control fish cytosols allowed checking for non-induced Cd–MT levels in liver; a very small amount of Cd appears to be associated to the MT fraction of control cytosols as found elsewhere.<REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The analysis of kidney concentrates by RP HPLC-ESI-MS was not undertaken due to the lack of sensitivity for detection of the metallofractions.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="New" advantage="No"/><text>The significantly lower concentration of MT in kidney compared with liver along with the poorer sensitivity of ESI-MS in comparison with ICP-MS did not allow the identification of MT–metal complexes in carp kidney.</text></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>RP HPLC-ICP-TOFMS of carp liver MT</HEADER><P><s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>MT cytosolic samples of 50 µl were chromatographed immediately after being isolated by SE-HPLC and preconcentrated and desalted by centrifugal microfiltration.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To find compatibility between the ICP-TOFMS and the ESI-MS as detection systems, the conditions for separation and elution of the MT fractions were selected as summarized in Table 1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The effect of the pH of the mobile phases on the retention time of the MT isoforms was investigated at varying pH values between 6.0 and 7.4.</text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This pH interval was selected to avoid possible changes of in vivo species of Cd and Zn by dissociation of these metals from the MT–metal complexes.<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit14"/><REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit19"/><REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit20"/><REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A dependence of the solutes’ retention times on the pH of the mobile phases was observed: an increase in the pH resulted in a decrease in the retention times of the MT fractions.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Higher pH values than 7.4 were not tried following instructions for the use of the column as given by the manufacturer.</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>A physiological pH of 7.4 was finally selected for their speciation.</text></s></P><P><s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of ammonium acetate and Tris–HCl buffers both with buffering capacity in the pH range studied led to similar ICP-TOFMS metal profiles for the liver samples under similar chromatographic conditions.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, ammonium acetate buffer was preferred because of its higher compatibility with electrospray ionization.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Concentrations of methanol of up to 30percent (v/v) were well tolerated by the ICP-TOFMS system with no significant changes in sensitivity or occurrence of serious plasma instability.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This was achieved after a careful optimization of the ICP parameters (e.g., using a high Rf power as shown in Table 1) without need for a cooled spray chamber or addition of oxygen to the auxiliary gas.</text></s></P><P><s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We investigated Cd, Zn, Cu and Pb profiles by RP HPLC-ICP-TOFMS for carp liver MT under different elution gradients.</text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 1 shows the presence of two major and several minor chromatographic peaks separated within a chromatographic run of 20 min under the conditions given in Table 1.</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The two main species with retention times of 14.4 min (peak 1) and 16.6 min (peak 2) apparently contain the four metals as indicated by the simultaneous mass spectra obtained with the ICP-TOFMS instrument.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Pb elution profile clearly shows that only a very small amount of Pb appears to be associated to these fractions in comparison with the Zn, Cd and Cu profiles.</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The next step is the identification of these ICP-MS signals.</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>For this purpose, application of electrospray ionization MS as detector for RP HPLC was addressed.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Identification of the HPLC-ICP-MS signals using ESI-MS detection</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Detection of carp MT-metal complexes</HEADER><P><s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>On-line molecular mass determination of the eluting MT–metal complexes was undertaken by analyzing the carp hepatic MT concentrates using RP HPLC-ESI-MS.</text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total ion current (TIC) chromatogram obtained under the conditions given in Table 1 is shown in Fig. 2.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As can be observed the detection and analysis of minor HPLC-ICP-MS signals in the chromatogram shown in Fig. 1 seems to be hampered by the loss of sensitivity during the electrospray ionization of the metalloforms.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the two main MT peaks detected by ICP-MS can be distinguished.</text></s> <s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Mass spectra taken at the apices of these peaks are shown in Fig. 3(a).</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>They indicate the co-elution of different metal complexes with MT isoforms within each chromatographic peak.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mass chromatogram obtained for the ion (m/z 1333) observed as the most abundant for the 5+ ionization state clearly indicates the presence of the two species (peaks 1 and 2 in Fig. 3(a)), as illustrated in Fig. 3(b).</text></s></P><P><s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The three signal pairs at m/z (1324, 1655), (1333, 1667) and (1343, 1680) present in the mass spectrum of peak 1 and those indicated for peak 2 (Fig. 3(a)) show a mass difference between two consecutive peaks within each charge state envelope that likely originates from the substitution of one Cu or Zn atom by Cd.</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Note that it is difficult to distinguish between Cu and Zn because their atomic masses are very similar and the ESI (SF)MS instrument is operated at low resolution to increase sensitivity.</text></s> <s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Assumptions on the identification of these mixed metal complexes cannot be based exclusively on the mass spectra obtained since no data on the molecular masses of the common carp hepatic MT isoforms (e.g., masses of apo–MT and metal–MT complexes calculated according to the sequence) were previously reported.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Besides, preliminary information on the molecular mass of the apo-forms by direct ESI-MS analysis (after acidification off-line with 0.1percent TFA) could not be obtained due to the lack of sensitivity which makes it difficult to differentiate their signal from the noise along with the insufficient resolution of the mass spectra and the presence of impurities.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous work has shown that the stoichiometry of mixed metal complexes may be elucidated with repeated analyses at varying pH values; unfortunately, we had insufficient sample to attempt such analyses.<REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit20"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Proof of direct correlation of the molecular mass of the complex and the molecular mass of the demetallated isoform obtained for independent chromatographic signals has been used by other authors for identification of mammalian MT–metal complexes of ambiguous stoichiometry.<REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit19"/><REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit20"/><REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The on-line molecular mass determination of the demetallated MT isoforms was then attempted.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Detection of demetallated MT isoforms</HEADER><P><s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>An approach based on the post-column acidification of the eluate (to a final pH of 1.9) was used in previous studies to obtain the apo-MT isoforms on arrival at the ESI-MS detector.<REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit19"/><REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit23"/></text></s> <s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The demetallation efficiency appeared to be critically dependent on parameters that affect the mixing of the acidic solution with the eluate.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In fact, the demetallation of the Cd7–MT complexes of horse kidney turned out to be irreproducible and incomplete without the use of a mixing coil placed between the T-piece where the eluate is mixed with the acidic solution and the electrospray MS instrument.<REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit19"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Following these previous studies, demetallation of MT–metal complexes with rabbit liver MT1 by post-column acidification was first investigated by mixing a flow of a TFA solution at 0.1 ml min−1 with the HPLC effluent (flow 0.8 ml min−1) via a zero-dead-volume T-piece (PEEK, Alltech).</text></s> <s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A PEEK mixing coil (250 mm × 250 µm id) was placed behind the T-piece and the pH of the solution was measured to guarantee a final value of 1.9.</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As a result, Cd4–MT complexes were still detected by ESI-MS, pointing to a low efficiency of post-column formation of the apo-form.</text></s> <s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The acidic solution-to-eluate flow ratio is similar to that used in previous studies but, in this work, the efficiency of the demetallation process is probably affected by the shorter time and lower velocity of mixing (due to a 15-fold higher HPLC flow rate).</text></s> <s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After this result, all efforts were directed to finding an alternative method that allows an efficient on-line demetallation of MT without affecting the conformation of the ligand.</text></s></P><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>“In-source” oxidation of MT</HEADER><P><s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The thiol groups of MT, normally involved in metal binding, are highly reactive and render the protein particularly sensitive to oxidation.</text></s> <s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Oxidation of MT (by formation of disulfide bonds) may also allow the determination of the molecular mass of the demetallated MT isoforms by ESI-MS, subject to retaining the conformation of the ligand.</text></s> <s sid="132"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, no data on the identification of demetallated MT isoforms based on protein oxidation procedures were previously reported.</text></s></P><P><s sid="133"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Direct analysis of rabbit liver MT2.</text></s> <s sid="134"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After introduction of a 10 mg l−1 CsI solution into the electrospray source and rinsing the system with water–methanol (1 + 1, v/v) as described in procedures, a 0.1 mg ml−1 MT2 standard solution (pH 6.0) was fed into the ESI-MS instrument by direct infusion.</text></s> <s sid="135"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mass spectrum obtained under the conditions of Table 1 is shown in Fig. 4(a).</text></s></P><P><s sid="136"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 4(b) shows the mass spectrum of the apo-MT2 obtained by acidification off-line with 0.1percent (v/v) TFA dissolved in methanol–water (30 + 70, v/v).</text></s> <s sid="137"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Prior to analysis of the apo-form the system was checked for the presence of remaining Cs and all precautions were taken to avoid it.</text></s> <s sid="138"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This mass spectrum shows many similarities with those obtained for apo-MT2 in previous studies.<REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit23"/><REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit24"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="139"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The signals at m/z 1222.2 (for the 5+ ionization state) and m/z 1527.2 (for the 4+ ionization state) in Fig. 4(a) do not correspond with those of the apo-form (Fig. 4(b)) but with those of the oxidised MT2.</text></s> <s sid="140"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The apo-form for a Cd7–MT is formed by substitution of the divalent metal atom by two protons.</text></s> <s sid="141"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Based on this knowledge, and in order to further verify results, the difference in terms of m/z for the 5+ ionization state between the two mass spectra was calculated (m/z 1225.0 − 1222.2 = m/z 2.8).</text></s> <s sid="142"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The resultant m/z 2.8 corresponds with that calculated for 14 protons that substitute 7 divalent metal atoms (14 H/5 = 2.8).</text></s> <s sid="143"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This result suggests that the oxidation of MT that involves formation of disulfide bonds is favoured by the presence of CsI in the system.</text></s></P><P><s sid="144"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Research has been devoted to studying the electron acceptor properties of Cs coatings.</text></s> <s sid="145"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The capabilities of Cs films coating different surfaces (including metals) for taking up electrons regardless of the electron donor and for electron exchange with the local surface area have been demonstrated previously.<REF ID="R-53" REFID="cit25"/><REF ID="R-54" REFID="cit26"/></text></s> <s sid="146"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This effect certainly favours the oxidation of the electron donor.</text></s> <s sid="147"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It could, in principle, be assumed that the contact of the MT solution with the Cs-coated electrospray capillary is responsible for MT oxidation.</text></s> <s sid="148"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Other possibilities of how the Cs adsorbed on the capillary could influence the analyte in the sprayed solution were pointed out by Cech and Enke.<REF ID="R-55" REFID="cit27"/></text></s> <s sid="149"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For instance, the electrochemical oxidation/reduction processes at the conductive electrospray probe tip can provide an alternative explanation for our observations.</text></s> <s sid="150"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further studies should be pursued to elucidate the mechanisms that control the overall oxidation process.</text></s></P><P><s sid="151"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The efficiency and robustness of the “in-source” oxidation method were tested through the identification of metal complexes with MT1 standard from rabbit liver before analyzing carp liver.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Identification of metal complexes with rabbit liver MT1</HEADER><P><s sid="152"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>RP HPLC was combined in parallel with ICP-TOFMS and ESI-MS and the analysis of a 0.1 mg ml−1 MT1 standard solution was carried out under the conditions given in Table 1.</text></s> <s sid="153"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The RP HPLC-ICP-TOFMS profile of Cd is represented in Fig. 5(a).</text></s> <s sid="154"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As shown, five fractions are relatively well separated within a run of 25 min.</text></s> <s sid="155"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The retention times of the main fractions found for rabbit liver MT1 (peaks 2, 3 and 4) are longer than those observed for the carp species (see Fig. 1), which indicates that the rabbit species are more hydrophobic than the latter.</text></s> <s sid="156"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For each of the peaks detected by ICP-TOFMS (2, 3 and 4) a pair of ESI-MS signals were produced: one for the complex and one for the oxidized form.</text></s> <s sid="157"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mass spectra taken at the apices of the peaks are shown in Fig. 5(b).</text></s> <s sid="158"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The oxidation method followed permitted the identification of the metal–MT1 complexes: the data obtained are very similar to those reported in the literature.<REF ID="R-56" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="159"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The subtraction of the m/z 157.5 of 7 divalent Cd (for the 5+ ionization state) from the m/z 1383 of the Cd7–MT-1a complex identified for the peak 2 leads to the same m/z as that of the oxidized form (the ligand) for the same ionization state (1383 − (7 × 112.5/5) = 1225.5).</text></s> <s sid="160"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This constitutes a proof of the direct correlation of the molecular mass of the complex and the molecular mass of the ligand.</text></s> <s sid="161"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of this approach for on-line oxidation of MT led to repeatable results for four consecutive chromatographic runs.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Identification of metal–MT complexes in carp liver</HEADER><P><s sid="162"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The oxidized MT isoforms for carp liver were obtained using the proposed method and the mass spectra taken at the apices of the peaks 1 and 2 detected by ICP-MS (see Fig. 1) are shown in Figs. 6(1) and 6(2), respectively.</text></s> <s sid="163"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As expected these mass spectra are simpler than those represented in Fig. 3(a) which were obtained for the metal–MT complexes; they permit calculation of the molecular mass of the ligand for the complexes that co-eluted within each of the two peaks (5986.5 ± 0.3 Da for peak 1 and 6025.2 ± 0.5 Da for peak 2).</text></s> <s sid="164"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>After proving and analyzing the correlation between the molecular mass of the complexes (as calculated from the mass spectra shown in Fig. 3(a)) and the molecular mass of the ligand for the 4+ and 5+ ionization states, the preliminary identification of the metal complexes with MT induced in carp liver was addressed.</text></s> <s sid="165"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Table 2 summarizes the calculated molecular mass of the MT complexes and the tentative formulae.</text></s> <s sid="166"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The complexity of the mass spectra at the apices of signals of metallated species along with the lack of sensitivity to detect the metallofractions (in spite of 20-fold sample preconcentration) is responsible for ambiguity in the identification.</text></s> <s sid="167"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>A separation of the MT (partially purified by SE-HPLC) fractions by anion-exchange prior to the RP HPLC-ESI-MS analysis may allow further purification of the MT complexes.</text></s> <s sid="168"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="New" advantage="No"/><text>However, such an extensive multidimensional separation usually leads to over-dilution and possible variations in the original composition of the sample.</text></s></P><P><s sid="169"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To the best of our knowledge, Pb was found here for the first time associated with MT isoforms in animal cytosols.</text></s> <s sid="170"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although traces of Pb associated with peak 2 were found by ICP-TOFMS, the electrospray results did not allow the identification of complexes of Pb other than the compounds present in peak 1.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="171"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of two-dimensional chromatography (size-exclusion followed by reversed phase HPLC) with parallel detection by ICP-MS and ESI-MS is an attractive approach for preliminary identification of metal complexes with MT isoforms induced in fish tissue owing to metal stress.</text></s></P><P><s sid="172"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An efficient, robust and simple “in-source” oxidation method in combination with RP HPLC-ESI-MS permits one to obtain information on the molecular mass of the ligand (oxidized form) without post-column sample dilution and formation of artefacts that frequently occur due to the existence of several mixed metallocomplexes of the same isoform.</text></s> <s sid="173"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Using this method, direct information is, for the first time, obtained on the molecular mass of two MT isoforms in carp liver, allowing their identification.</text></s> <s sid="174"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further studies should be pursued to elucidate the mechanism of the “in-source” oxidation observed for MT.</text></s></P><P><s sid="175"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mass difference between co-eluted MT complexes with MT isoforms, pointing to the substitution of one Cu or Zn atom by Cd, is indicative of the significant role that MT in hepatic carp cytosols play in Cd sequestration after short term exposure to high levels of this toxic metal (1 mg l−1 Cd) in water.</text></s> <s sid="176"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Distinction between Cu and Zn, both present in the complexes detected, could not be accomplished.</text></s> <s sid="177"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It would require a higher accuracy and sensitivity in the molecular mass measurement by ESI-MS, achieved by using, for example, a TOF mass analyzer.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY><cmlPile><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml1"><molecule id="m1"><name>Methanol</name><name>methanol</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/CH4O/c1-2/h2H,1H3</identifier>
  <atomArray>
    <atom id="a0" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="3"/>
    <atom id="a1" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a2" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
  </atomArray>
  <bondArray>
    <bond id="b1" atomRefs2="a1 a0" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b2" atomRefs2="a1 a2" order="S"/>
  </bondArray>
</molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml2"><molecule id="m1"><name>acetate</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/C2H4O2/c1-2(3)4/h1H3,(H,3,4)/p-1/fC2H3O2/q-1</identifier>
  <atomArray>
    <atom id="a0" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="3"/>
    <atom id="a1" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="0"/>
    <atom id="a2" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="0"/>
    <atom id="a3" elementType="O" formalCharge="-1" hydrogenCount="0"/>
  </atomArray>
  <bondArray>
    <bond id="b1" atomRefs2="a1 a0" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b2" atomRefs2="a2 a1" order="D"/>
    <bond id="b3" atomRefs2="a3 a1" order="S"/>
  </bondArray>
</molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml3"><molecule id="m1"><name>water</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/H2O/h1H2</identifier>
  <atomArray>
    <atom id="a0" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="2"/>
    <atom id="a1" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a2" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
  </atomArray>
  <bondArray>
    <bond id="b1" atomRefs2="a0 a1" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b2" atomRefs2="a0 a2" order="S"/>
  </bondArray>
</molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml4"><molecule id="m1"><name>ammonium acetate</name><name>Ammonium acetate</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/C2H4O2.H3N/c1-2(3)4;/h1H3,(H,3,4);1H3/fC2H3O2.H4N/h;1H/q-1;+1</identifier><atomArray><atom id="a1" elementType="N" formalCharge="1"/><atom id="a2" elementType="C"/><atom id="a3" elementType="C"/><atom id="a4" elementType="O"/><atom id="a5" elementType="O" formalCharge="-1"/></atomArray><bondArray><bond atomRefs2="a2 a3" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a4 a2" order="2"/><bond atomRefs2="a5 a2" order="1"/></bondArray></molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml5"><molecule id="m1"><name>2-mercaptoethanol</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/C2H6OS/c3-1-2-4/h3-4H,1-2H2</identifier><atomArray><atom id="a1" elementType="C"/><atom id="a2" elementType="C"/><atom id="a3" elementType="O"/><atom id="a4" elementType="S"/></atomArray><bondArray><bond atomRefs2="a1 a2" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a3 a1" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a4 a2" order="1"/></bondArray></molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml6"><molecule id="m1"><name>ammonia</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/H3N/h1H3</identifier>
  <atomArray>
    <atom id="a0" elementType="N" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="3"/>
    <atom id="a1" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a2" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a3" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
  </atomArray>
  <bondArray>
    <bond id="b1" atomRefs2="a0 a1" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b2" atomRefs2="a0 a2" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b3" atomRefs2="a0 a3" order="S"/>
  </bondArray>
</molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml7"><molecule id="m1"><name>acetic acid</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/C2H4O2/c1-2(3)4/h1H3,(H,3,4)/f/h3H</identifier>
  <atomArray>
    <atom id="a0" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="3"/>
    <atom id="a1" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="0"/>
    <atom id="a2" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a3" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="0"/>
    <atom id="a4" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
  </atomArray>
  <bondArray>
    <bond id="b1" atomRefs2="a1 a0" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b2" atomRefs2="a2 a1" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b3" atomRefs2="a3 a1" order="D"/>
    <bond id="b4" atomRefs2="a2 a4" order="S"/>
  </bondArray>
</molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml8"><molecule id="m1"><name>trifluoroacetic acid</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/C2HF3O2/c3-2(4,5)1(6)7/h(H,6,7)/f/h6H</identifier><atomArray><atom id="a1" elementType="C"/><atom id="a2" elementType="C"/><atom id="a3" elementType="O"/><atom id="a4" elementType="O"/><atom id="a5" elementType="F"/><atom id="a6" elementType="F"/><atom id="a7" elementType="F"/></atomArray><bondArray><bond atomRefs2="a1 a2" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a3 a1" order="2"/><bond atomRefs2="a4 a1" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a5 a2" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a6 a2" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a7 a2" order="1"/></bondArray></molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml9"><molecule id="m1"><name>caesium iodide</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/Cs.HI/h;1H/q+1;/p-1/fCs.I/h;1h/qm;-1</identifier><atomArray><atom id="a1" elementType="Cs" formalCharge="1"/><atom id="a2" elementType="I" formalCharge="-1"/></atomArray><bondArray/></molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml10"><molecule id="m1"><name>Mercaptoethanol</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/C2H6OS/c1-2(3)4/h2-4H,1H3</identifier><atomArray><atom id="a1" elementType="C"/><atom id="a2" elementType="C"/><atom id="a3" elementType="O"/><atom id="a4" elementType="S"/></atomArray><bondArray><bond atomRefs2="a1 a2" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a3 a1" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a4 a1" order="1"/></bondArray></molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml11"><molecule id="m1"><name>Tris</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/C4H11NO3/c5-4(1-6,2-7)3-8/h6-8H,1-3,5H2</identifier>
  <atomArray>
    <atom id="a0" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="2"/>
    <atom id="a1" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="2"/>
    <atom id="a2" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="2"/>
    <atom id="a3" elementType="C" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="0"/>
    <atom id="a4" elementType="N" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="2"/>
    <atom id="a5" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a6" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a7" elementType="O" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a8" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a9" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a10" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a11" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a12" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
  </atomArray>
  <bondArray>
    <bond id="b1" atomRefs2="a3 a0" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b2" atomRefs2="a3 a1" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b3" atomRefs2="a3 a2" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b4" atomRefs2="a4 a3" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b5" atomRefs2="a5 a0" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b6" atomRefs2="a6 a1" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b7" atomRefs2="a7 a2" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b8" atomRefs2="a5 a8" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b9" atomRefs2="a4 a9" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b10" atomRefs2="a4 a10" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b11" atomRefs2="a6 a11" order="S"/>
    <bond id="b12" atomRefs2="a7 a12" order="S"/>
  </bondArray>
</molecule></cml><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml12"><molecule id="m1"><name>HCl</name><identifier convention="iupac:inchi">InChI=1/ClH/h1H</identifier>
  <atomArray>
    <atom id="a0" elementType="Cl" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
    <atom id="a1" elementType="H" formalCharge="0" hydrogenCount="1"/>
  </atomArray>
  <bondArray>
    <bond id="b1" atomRefs2="a0 a1" order="S"/>
  </bondArray>
</molecule></cml><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml1">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
1%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3EMethanol%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cname%3Eme
thanol%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cidentifier+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3E
InChI%3D1%2FCH4O%2Fc1-2%2Fh2H%2C1H3%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%0A++%3CatomArra
y%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a0%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+formalCharge%3D
%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%223%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+element
Type%3D%22O%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A+++
+%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hy
drogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FatomArray%3E%0A++%3CbondArray%3E%0A++
++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b1%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a1+a0%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A+++
+%3Cbond+id%3D%22b2%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a1+a2%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2F
bondArray%3E%0A%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml2">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
2%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3Eacetate%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cidentifi
er+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FC2H4O2%2Fc1-2%283%29
4%2Fh1H3%2C%28H%2C3%2C4%29%2Fp-1%2FfC2H3O2%2Fq-1%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%0A++%3Cato
mArray%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a0%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+formalCh
arge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%223%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+el
ementType%3D%22C%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%220%22+%2F
%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+formalCharge%3D%22
0%22+hydrogenCount%3D%220%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a3%22+elementT
ype%3D%22O%22+formalCharge%3D%22-1%22+hydrogenCount%3D%220%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C
%2FatomArray%3E%0A++%3CbondArray%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b1%22+atomRe
fs2%3D%22a1+a0%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b2%22+atomRef
s2%3D%22a2+a1%22+order%3D%22D%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b3%22+atomRefs
2%3D%22a3+a1%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FbondArray%3E%0A%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C
%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml3">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
3%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3Ewater%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cidentifier
+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FH2O%2Fh1H2%3C%2Fidenti
fier%3E%0A++%3CatomArray%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a0%22+elementType%3D
%22O%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cato
m+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydroge
nCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+fo
rmalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FatomArray%3E
%0A++%3CbondArray%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b1%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a0+a1%22
+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b2%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a0+a2%22+
order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FbondArray%3E%0A%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml4">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
4%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3Eammonium+acetate%3C%2Fname%3E
%3Cname%3EAmmonium+acetate%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cidentifier+conventio
n%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FC2H4O2.H3N%2Fc1-2%283%294%3B%2Fh1H3%2C
%28H%2C3%2C4%29%3B1H3%2FfC2H3O2.H4N%2Fh%3B1H%2Fq-1%3B%2B1%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%3Ca
tomArray%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22N%22+formalCharg
e%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22
a3%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a4%22+elementType%3D%22O
%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a5%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+formalCharge%3D%22-1
%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FatomArray%3E%3CbondArray%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a2+a3%22
+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a2%22+order%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%3C
bond+atomRefs2%3D%22a5+a2%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FbondArray%3E%3C%2Fm
olecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml5">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
5%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3E2-mercaptoethanol%3C%2Fname
%3E%3Cidentifier+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FC2H6
OS%2Fc3-1-2-4%2Fh3-4H%2C1-2H2%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%3CatomArray%3E%3Cat
om+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+element
Type%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a3%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+i
d%3D%22a4%22+elementType%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FatomArray%3E%3CbondArray%3E%3Cb
ond+atomRefs2%3D%22a1+a2%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D
%22a3+a1%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a2%22+order%3D
%221%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FbondArray%3E%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml6">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
6%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3Eammonia%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cidentifi
er+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FH3N%2Fh1H3%3C%2Fiden
tifier%3E%0A++%3CatomArray%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a0%22+elementTyp
e%3D%22N%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%223%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Ca
tom+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydro
genCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+
formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id
%3D%22a3%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCou
nt%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FatomArray%3E%0A++%3CbondArray%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+i
d%3D%22b1%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a0+a1%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id
%3D%22b2%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a0+a2%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D
%22b3%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a0+a3%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FbondArray%3E
%0A%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml7">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
7%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3Eacetic+acid%3C%2Fname%3E%3Ciden
tifier+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FC2H4O2%2Fc1-
2%283%294%2Fh1H3%2C%28H%2C3%2C4%29%2Ff%2Fh3H%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%0A++%3CatomArray
%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a0%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+formalCharge%3D%22
0%22+hydrogenCount%3D%223%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+elementT
ype%3D%22C%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%220%22+%2F%3E%0A++++
%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hyd
rogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a3%22+elementType%3D%22O
%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%220%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+
id%3D%22a4%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenC
ount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FatomArray%3E%0A++%3CbondArray%3E%0A++++%3Cbond
+id%3D%22b1%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a1+a0%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+
id%3D%22b2%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a2+a1%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+i
d%3D%22b3%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a3+a1%22+order%3D%22D%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id
%3D%22b4%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a2+a4%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FbondArray
%3E%0A%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml8">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
8%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3Etrifluoroacetic+acid%3C%2Fn
ame%3E%3Cidentifier+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FC
2HF3O2%2Fc3-2%284%2C5%291%286%297%2Fh%28H%2C6%2C7%29%2Ff%2Fh6H%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%3C
atomArray%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id
%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a3%22+elementType%3D
%22O%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a4%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a5
%22+elementType%3D%22F%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a6%22+elementType%3D%22F%22+
%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a7%22+elementType%3D%22F%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FatomArray%3E%3Cbon
dArray%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a1+a2%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+a
tomRefs2%3D%22a3+a1%22+order%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a
1%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a5+a2%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F
%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a6+a2%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRef
s2%3D%22a7+a2%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FbondArray%3E%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcm
l%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml9">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
9%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3Ecaesium+iodide%3C%2Fname%3E%3Ci
dentifier+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FCs.HI%2Fh
%3B1H%2Fq%2B1%3B%2Fp-1%2FfCs.I%2Fh%3B1h%2Fqm%3B-1%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%3CatomArr
ay%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22Cs%22+formalCharge%3D%221%22
+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22I%22+formalCharge%3D%22-1%22
+%2F%3E%3C%2FatomArray%3E%3CbondArray+%2F%3E%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml10">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
10%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3EMercaptoethanol%3C%2Fname%3E
%3Cidentifier+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FC2H6O
S%2Fc1-2%283%294%2Fh2-4H%2C1H3%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%3CatomArray%3E%3Catom+
id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementTyp
e%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a3%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22
a4%22+elementType%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FatomArray%3E%3CbondArray%3E%3Cbond
+atomRefs2%3D%22a1+a2%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a3
+a1%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a1%22+order%3D%221%22
+%2F%3E%3C%2FbondArray%3E%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml11">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
11%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3ETris%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cidentifier
+convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FC4H11NO3%2Fc5-4%281-
6%2C2-7%293-8%2Fh6-8H%2C1-3%2C5H2%3C%2Fidentifier%3E%0A++%3CatomArray%3E
%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a0%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+formalCharge%3D%220
%22+hydrogenCount%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+elementTy
pe%3D%22C%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3C
atom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydr
ogenCount%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a3%22+elementType%3D%22C%22
+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%220%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+i
d%3D%22a4%22+elementType%3D%22N%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCo
unt%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a5%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+forma
lCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a6%22
+elementType%3D%22O%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221
%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a7%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+formalCharg
e%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a8%22+eleme
ntType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A+
+++%3Catom+id%3D%22a9%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+
hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a10%22+elementTyp
e%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Ca
tom+id%3D%22a11%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydr
ogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a12%22+elementType%3D%22H
%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FatomAr
ray%3E%0A++%3CbondArray%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b1%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a3
+a0%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b2%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a3+
a1%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b3%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a3+a
2%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b4%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a3
%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b5%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a5+a0%22
+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b6%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a6+a1%22+
order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b7%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a7+a2%22+o
rder%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b8%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a5+a8%22+or
der%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b9%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a9%22+ord
er%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b10%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a10%22+or
der%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b11%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a6+a11%22+o
rder%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Cbond+id%3D%22b12%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a7+a12%22+
order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FbondArray%3E%0A%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml12">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
12%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3EHCl%3C%2Fname%3E%3Cidentifier+
convention%3D%22iupac%3Ainchi%22%3EInChI%3D1%2FClH%2Fh1H%3C%2Fidentifi
er%3E%0A++%3CatomArray%3E%0A++++%3Catom+id%3D%22a0%22+elementType%3D%22C
l%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogenCount%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++++%3Catom
+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22H%22+formalCharge%3D%220%22+hydrogen
Count%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FatomArray%3E%0A++%3CbondArray%3E%0A++++%3Cbon
d+id%3D%22b1%22+atomRefs2%3D%22a0+a1%22+order%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%0A++%3C%2FbondA
rray%3E%0A%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml%3E</cmlUrlEnc></cmlPile></PAPER>