<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b309893a" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>An inventory-based carbon budget for forest and woodland ecosystems of Turkey</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Environmental monitoring of national-level comparisons of CO2 emissions is needed to quantify sources and sinks of carbon (C) in national ecosystems.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In this study, a national forest inventory database was used to estimate the past and current pools and fluxes of C in deciduous and coniferous forest and woodland ecosystems (20.7 × 106 ha) of Turkey.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Growing C stock was 12.63 t C ha−1 in 1960 and 16.55 t C ha−1 in 1995.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Total C store in the whole live woody biomass was estimated at 22.77 t C ha−1 in 1996.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total flux of C from the atmosphere into the forest and woodland ecosystems driven by primary productivity was about 1.46 t C ha−1 (or 30.2 Mt C) in 1996.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The estimated net release of C from the forest and woodland ecosystems of Turkey to the atmosphere was about 1.34 t C ha−1 (or 21.5 Mt C) in 1996.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When C released was taken into account, net ecosystem sequestration (NES) resulted in 0.12 t C ha−1 per year.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Such analytical tools as national forest C budgets are needed to improve our preventive and mitigative strategies for dealing with global climate change.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Carbon (C) is one of the principal elemental components of ecosystems and intimately coupled with biogeochemical cycles of other major elements such as nitrogen, phosphorus, sulfur, oxygen, and hydrogen.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Primary productivity, herbivory, litterfall, plant and soil respiration, and natural and human disturbances are the primary ecosystem processes that control the global C cycle.<REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Soils contain approximately twice as much C (1580 Pg) as the atmosphere (750 Pg) or terrestrial vegetation (610 Pg).<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Globally, the amounts of C entering soil by litterfall and leaving soil by respiration are 61.4 Pg C and 60 Pg C annually, respectively.<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Primary productivity of forests cycles approximately one-twelfth of the atmospheric stock of C annually.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Globally, forests and woodlands cover about 3.4 Gha (22.9percent) and 1.7 Gha (11.5percent) of the total land surface, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Forests account for approximately 50percent (1146 Pg C) of the total terrestrial C pool, with two-thirds (787 Pg C) of this residing in forest soils and the rest (359 Pg C) in vegetation.<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit5"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Local human activities modifying C pools and fluxes have the potential to alter the global C cycle and climate.</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The injection of 480 Pg C into the atmosphere through fossil-fuel combustion and land-use and land-cover (LULC) changes since the Industrial Revolution has disturbed the natural global cycling of C among vegetation, soil, atmosphere, and oceans.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Deforestation is one of the major LULC changes that released 2.24 Pg C per year to the atmosphere in the 1990s.<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit7"/></text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Quantification of C stocks and fluxes of forest ecosystems is of considerable interest in the context of mitigation of global climate change for the following reasons: (1) forest ecosystems store larger quantities of atmospheric CO2 for a longer period of time in vegetation and soil than the other terrestrial ecosystems, (2) countries seek to comply with agreements under the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change; and (3) scientists seek to account for the imbalance in the global C budget (termed as missing sink comprising up to 1.8 Pg C per year in the 1980s).<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>National budgets of forest C sequestration may be a practical way of monitoring reductions and increases in atmospheric CO2 concentration and at the same time may contribute to sustainable biological productivity of ecosystems.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, forest C sequestration should be regarded as a component of a mitigation strategy, not as a substitute for the changes required in energy supply, use and technology if atmospheric CO2 concentration is to be stabilized.</text></s></P><P><s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Turkey (36–42°N, 26–45°E) has a land area of 779 452 km2 with 20 million ha located in arid and 31 million ha located in semi-arid climatic regions.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Turkey is a predominantly mountainous country, and true lowland is confined to the coastal fringes, with an average altitude of 1250 m and the highest point of 5137 m (Mount Ararat) above sea level near the Iranian border.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Gently rolling, fertile plains cover Thrace and extend along the Black Sea coast of Anatolia.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Along the coast of the Aegean Sea are broad, fertile river valleys.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A narrow strip of fertile land lies along the Mediterranean Sea.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The prevailing climate varies among the Aegean, Mediterranean, Central, East and Southeast regions of Turkey.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There are two main climate belts: (1) ‘Temperate’ characterized by cold winters and warm summers with a year-round precipitation, and (2) ‘Mediterranean’ characterized by mild winters and hot and dry summers with more than 65percent of the mean annual precipitation occuring in the winter.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The temperature reaches a maximum of 45 °C in the south and southeast during the summer and a minimum of −40 °C in the east and central Anatolia during the winter, with a mean annual temperature of 19 °C.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Annual precipitation ranges from 250 mm in the central and southeastern regions to 2500 mm in the northeastern coastal plains and mountain regions, with a mean annual precipitation of 650 mm.</text></s></P><P><s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rapid population growth, increased human consumption, conversion of forests to agricultural and urban-industrial lands, overgrazing, overharvesting, prevailing semi-arid conditions, poverty, economic crises, rapid urbanization-industrialization, and migration of rural populations to urban areas have had significant adverse impacts on conservation and sustainable management of forest resources, thus causing an increase in degradation and destruction of forest ecosystem productivity.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Many forests are exploited by the rural population as a source of fuelwood and charcoal for their domestic needs.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The percentage of total roundwood production consumed for fuel was 44percent in Turkey.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>About 2000 fires have occurred in Turkey in the last ten years, burning about 12 500 ha annually.<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The land area of forests degraded due to overexploitation and urban-industrial expansions was estimated at 11.7 Mha.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit10a"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit10b"/></text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Conversion of forest, pasture, and wetlands into agricultural lands between 1948 and 1994 has amounted to 21.5 Mha.<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit10a"/><REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit10b"/><REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit11"/></text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Regenerating and C sequestration capacities of forest in Turkey are restricted by soil erosion and shallow soils in that 75percent of the total land area is prone to different levels of erosion, and only 14percent of the total land area has a soil depth of 90 cm or more.<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit10a"/><REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit10b"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Sharp et al.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(1975) calculated forest biomass of North Carolina in the USA, based on forest inventory data and a constant biomass expansion factor (BEF) of 2.0 t m−3.<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Brown and Lugo (1984) used two different BEF values of 1.6 for closed tropical forests and 3.0 for open tropical forests.<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit13"/></text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Kauppi et al.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(1992) quantified a C budget of European forests by applying a BEF range of 0.6 to 0.8.<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit14"/></text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Turner et al.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(1995) estimated C budget for forests in the USA by using a constant ratio of whole-tree C to merchantable-bole C across age classes within a forest type.<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit15"/></text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In the work presented here, carbon budget for forest and woodland ecosystems in Turkey was calculated separately for coniferous and deciduous tree groups, based on UN-ECE/FAO national forest inventory data in 1996.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Methods</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Ecological description of study region</HEADER><P><s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>According to the Ministry of Forestry in Turkey, forest is defined as land with tree crown cover (or equivalent stocking level) of more than 10percent, area of more than 0.5 ha, and a minimum tree height of 5 m at maturity and may consist of closed and open forest formations, young natural stands, all forestry plantations, forest nurseries, seed orchards, forest roads, cleared tracts, firebreaks, and windbreaks and shelterbelts with an area of more than 0.5 ha and width of more than 20 m.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Woodland is defined as land either with tree crown cover (or equivalent stocking level) of 5–10percent and a minimum tree height of 5 m at maturity or with tree crown cover (or equivalent stocking level) of more than 10percent and a maximum tree height of 5 m at maturity.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Temperate and Mediterranean forest ecosystems cover approximately 12 937 × 103 ha (16.9percent) and 7 776 × 103 ha (10.2percent) of the total land surface in Turkey, respectively.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit17"/></text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Due to the prevailing semi-arid conditions of Turkey, forests mostly comprise open woodlands and lands with scattered trees and xerophytic shrubs except for the highlands where temperate and moist forests are found.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>About 51percent of the forest and woodland area is classified as productive and the rest as degraded or severely degraded forests and rangelands.<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit9"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Turkey is an important center of floristic diversity where three phytogeographical regions of Euro-Siberian, Mediterranean and Irano-Turanian meet, with approximately 8792 vascular and 4734 non-vascular plant species, 2656 endemic plant species, and 1889 animal species identified.<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit18"/></text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Dominant dry forest species of the Irano-Turanian floristic region include Pinus nigra subsp.</text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Pallasiana, P. sylvestris, Quercus cerris, Q. pubescens, and Juniperus oxycedrus.<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit19"/></text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Dominant sub-humid forest species of the Euro-Siberian or Euxine floristic region include Fagus orientalis, Castanea sativa, Carpinus spp., Picea orientalis, Pinus nigra, P. brutia, P. sylvestris, Abies bornmulleriana, A. equi-trojani.<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit18"/></text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Sclerophyllous forest species of the Mediterranean floristic region include Quercus ilex, Q. calliprinos, Pistacia lentiscus, Cercis siliquastrum, Ceratonia siliqua, Pinus brutia, P. pinea, P. halepensis, Cupressus sempervirens, and Cedrus libani.<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit11"/><REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit19"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The present total area of nature conservation constitutes 4.8percent (3.7 Mha) of the country's land area.<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit10a"/><REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit10b"/></text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since 1955, reforestation of 2.5 Mha, erosion control of 284 000 ha, and range improvement of 80 000 ha have been carried out, and the current annual anti-desertification activities are 50 000 ha for reforestation and 25 000 ha for erosion control.<REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The National Afforestation and Erosion Control Mobilization law passed in 1995 increased the rate of afforestation for industrial and protective purposes in addition to fuelwood and charcoal production to around 300 000 ha annually.<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The share of the forestry sector in the gross national product (GNP) is about 0.9percent which would increase to 1.8percent if undeclared firewood consumption, and private sector wood production were included in the calculation.</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Nevertheless, this calculation excludes intangible benefits from the ecosystem services of forests such as regulation of hydrological cycle, sequestration of greenhouse gases (GHGs), soil stability, recreation, and scientific information as well as their role in generating higher income and employment for 7.2 million forest-dependent villagers living in or close to the natural forests.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Calculation procedures of carbon budget</HEADER><P><s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Construction of C budgets (see Fig. 1) can facilitate environmental monitoring of national-level comparisons of CO2 emissions and sequestration in the global C cycle as well as improving national preventive and mitigative measures against global climate change.</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>First, the data of Raev et al<REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit20"/>. concerning annual increment, annual felling, net increment, and growing stock of above-ground woody biomass of Turkish forests between 1960 and 1995 were used to calculate temporal changes in C stocks and fluxes, based on regression analysis.</text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Second, total carbon budget for forest and woodland ecosystems of Turkey was quantified as the sum of above- and below-ground dry woody biomass of coniferous forests, deciduous forests, coniferous woodlands, and deciduous woodlands, based on UN-ECE/FAO inventory data.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>UN-ECE/FAO data include areas of deciduous and coniferous forests, woodland area, gross annual increment, net annual increments, natural losses, fellings, removals, felling residues and growing stock measured in m3 over bark, and above-stump biomass, and stump and root woody biomass measured in dry weight t.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Aggregate data for woodlands of Turkey in the inventory were separated into coniferous and deciduous woodlands, relative to the overall proportion of coniferous and deciduous forests since biomass expansion factors and C storage vary between coniferous and deciduous trees.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This procedure improved the first approximation of C storage and accumulation in Turkish forest ecosystems given the limited data availability.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The following equation from UN-ECE/FAO was used to estimate C storage in the entire live woody biomass of branch, stem, and coarse roots of the forest and woodland ecosystems: where CTWB = C content in total tree dry woody biomass (TWB) in C t−1; BEFAG = biomass expansion factor for converting stemwood volume (V) of coniferous (E) or deciduous forests (D) to above-ground dry woody biomass (AG); nation-specific BEFAG-E and BEFAG-D were assumed to be equal to 0.5 t m−3 and 0.64 t m−3, respectively; BEFBG = biomass expansion factor for converting stem volume of coniferous and deciduous forests (ED) to below-ground dry woody biomass (BG) and was assumed as 0.09 t m−3 in Turkey; and carbon density (CD) = 0.5 C t−1 expressed as tonnes (t) of carbon per tonne (t) of dry biomass.<REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit21"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since the UN-ECE/FAO data did not distinguish between coniferous and deciduous woodlands, the relative proportions of the reported stock or flux figures of coniferous (VEF) and deciduous (VDF) trees on forest were assumed to be the same on woodland (VEDW), and the total coniferous and deciduous C stocks/fluxes (TCED) of forest and woodland were estimated as follows:where VBG-FW = total below-ground woody biomass stock or flux (m3) of coniferous and deciduous trees on forest and woodland.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This total biomass volume was disaggregated proportionally into the components of forest (VBG-F) and woodland (VBG-W) and later into coniferous forest (VBG-EF) and woodland (VBG-EW) and deciduous forest (VBG-DF) and woodland (VBG-DW) separately as follows: </text></s></P><P><s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>To complete the C budgets, initial carbon stocks in soil and wood products, and total litterfall rate were estimated from the relevant literature data.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The carbon in wood products from the forests is brought back to the atmosphere by product decomposition in long-term.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total amount of C in wood products was assumed to be constant, and thus, the average amount of C removed is equal to the amount of C released in product decomposition.<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Soil organic C (SOC) pool was assumed to be in steady-state and contained the average forest SOC stock of 27 European countries of 47 t C ha−1 to a depth of 30 cm.<REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit23"/></text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Decomposition rate of the SOC pool was assumed to be in steady state with the flow rate of litterfall into the soil.</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Total litterfall rate from above- and below-ground woody biomass of living trees was estimated by multiplying woody biomass by compartment-specific turnover rates (r) as follows: <EQN ID="eqn6"><EQ-S ID="s72">LFTB-EF = (AGBEF × rAGB-EF) + (BGBEF × rBGB-EF)</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn7"><EQ-S ID="s73">LFTB-DF = (AGBDF × rAGB-DF) + (BGBDF × rBGB-DF)</EQ-S></EQN>where LFTB-EF and LFTB-DF refer to litterfall from total woody biomass of living coniferous and deciduous trees, respectively; rAGB-EF and rBGB-EF refer to above- and below-ground turnover rates for coniferous trees, respectively; rAGB-EF was assumed to be equal to 0.0087 per year for stem;<REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit24"/> rBGB-EF for coarse roots was assumed to be equal to rAGB-EF for branches of 0.025 per year;<REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit25"/> rAGB-DF and rBGB-DF refer to above- and below-ground turnover rates for deciduous trees, respectively; rAGB-DF was assumed to be equal to 0.0043 per year for stems;<REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit24"/> rBGB-DF for coarse roots was assumed to be equal to rAGB-DF for branches of 0.027 per year<REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit25"/>.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Carbon budget</HEADER><P><s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total forest and woodland area (20.7 Mha) of Turkey comprises 26.5percent of the country land area and is less than 1percent of the world's native forest area (3.4 Gha).</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Forest, plantations, and woodland cover 8100 × 103 ha, 1854 × 103, and 10 759 × 103 ha, with about 38.8percent and 26percent of the forest area consisting of pines and oaks, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Total forest cover increased in Turkey with a rate of 0.2percent (22 000 ha) and decreased globally with a rate of 0.2percent (9.3 Mha) between 1990 and 2000.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The forest and woodland area per capita is 0.3 ha, ca.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>45percent of the world average.</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Coniferous and deciduous forests and woodlands with approximately 800 woody taxa occupy 11.1 Mha and 9.6 Mha, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Annual increments of above-ground woody biomass of forest and woodland ecosystems increased from 0.39 t C ha−1 per year in 1960 to 0.46 t C ha−1 per year in 1995.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Growing C stock was 12.63 t C ha−1 in 1960 and 16.55 t C ha−1 in 1995.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When annual fellings were taken into account, a net C increment was estimated at 0.17 t C ha−1 per year in 1960 and 0.21 t C ha−1 per year in 1995.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Five-year average time series data and best-fitted regression equations of annual increments and felling, net increments, and growing C stock are shown for the period of 1960 to 1995 in Table 1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Total C storage in living woody biomass of coniferous and deciduous trees was estimated at 471.6 Mt C, with about 91percent on forest and 9percent on woodland.</text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Coniferous trees make up about 60percent of the total C stock of forest and woodland.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Total tree C density was 39.8 t C ha−1 for the coniferous forest, 49.2 t C ha−1 for the deciduous forest, 5.5 t C ha−1 for the coniferous woodland, 2.8 t C ha−1 for the deciduous woodland, and 22.8 t C ha−1 for the whole forest and woodland ecosystems.</text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Above-ground C density was estimated at 36.8 t C ha−1 on forest and 3.4 t C ha−1 on woodland, and below-ground C density at 6.2 t C ha−1 on forest and 0.6 t C ha−1 on woodland.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The world and European averages for above- and below-ground C density of forest were about 86 t C ha−1 in 1994 and 53.5 t C ha−1 in 1995, respectively.<REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit23"/></text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Carbon budgets for deciduous and evergreen forest and woodland ecosystems in Turkey are shown separately in Table 2.</text></s></P><P><s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total flux of C from the atmosphere into the forest and woodland ecosystems driven by primary productivity was about 30.2 Mt C per year.</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Plant respiration of C accounted for half of this gross primary productivity (GPP),<REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit21"/> thus leaving total net primary productivity (NPP) of 15.1 Mt C per year (0.73 t C ha−1 per year), with a ratio of total NPP of forest to that of woodland of 4.6.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Approximately 85percent and 15percent of NPP were sequestered in the above- and below-ground woody biomass of Turkish forest and woodland, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>About 48percent of the total NPP was felled, and 36percent was transferred into the soil organic C (SOC) pool through litterfall and natural losses.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The remaining 16percent (0.12 t C ha−1 per year) was sequestered in the live woody biomass of the forest and woodland.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>About 88.5percent of fellings (0.35 t C ha−1 per year) were removed from the forest and woodland, and the remaining 11.5percent was transferred as felling residues to the SOC pool.</text></s></P><P><s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Soil respiration (Rh) was assumed to be equal to the total input rate of plant residues of 0.30 t C ha−1 per year.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Net ecosystem productivity (NEP) as the difference between NPP and soil respiration was estimated at 0.43 t C ha−1 per year.</text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The estimated net release of C was about 1.34 t C ha−1 (or 21.5 Mt C) from plant and soil respirations and decay of wood products of the forest and woodland ecosystems of Turkey to the atmosphere in 1996.</text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When biomass removed out of the forest ecosystems was taken into account, net ecosystem sequestration (NES) resulted in 0.12 t C ha−1 per year (Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Total C stock in wood products in 2001 was estimated at 0.64 t C ha−1.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Karjalainen et al<REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit23"/>. found in the calculation of the C budget of 27 European countries between 1995 and 2000 that average NPP, Rh, NEP and NES were 3.18 t C ha−1 per year, 1.9 t C ha−1 per year, 1.28 t C ha−1 per year, and 0.66 t C ha−1 per year, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For only productive forests of Turkey, Nabuurs and Schelhaas<REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit26"/> reported, on average, a C stock in vegetation of 24.73 t C ha−1, NEP of 0.53 t C ha−1 per year, and NES of 0.25 t C ha−1 per year.</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The above average values reported by Karjalainen et al., and Nabuurs and Schelhaas may be used as a proxy for the estimation of the magnitude of uncertainties involved in this study.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>National C budgets of forest ecosystems provide a means of monitoring CO2 emissions to the atmosphere and managing forests to strengthen C sinks.</text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As with any quantification of C budget, uncertainty in the presented results stems from the quality of the national forest inventory and aggregation of spatial-temporal variations in the forest ecosystem by conversion factors.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The range of studies needed to reduce uncertainties in the present analysis includes the employment of geographic information systems (GIS), remote sensing, and processed-based modelling in estimates of forest growth.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this budget, the foliage and fine root pools were not included due to the lack of data and high uncertainties associated with the inclusion of these compartments.</text></s> <s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fires, droughts, insect and pathogen outbreaks, and introduced invasive species interact, exerting significant qualitative and quantitative influences on the structure and function of forests and consequently on their C budgets.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The national C budget presented in the study reflects consequences of past and present human land-use and land-cover changes and disturbance regimes of forest and woodland ecosystems.</text></s></P><P><s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Reducing vulnerability to human-induced disturbances of forests, and speeding their recovery from the disturbances require the continued monitoring of the structure and function of forest ecosystems to update risk assessments and actions in an adaptive management system.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Actions needed to be undertaken for sustainable forest management and conservation in Turkey range from forest policy reviews, new legal instruments, restructuring of institutions, and public participation to implementation of ecological indicators, quantification of the ecosystem services including C sequestration capacity of forests, and rehabilitation of damaged forest ecosystems.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>