<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310125h" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Effects of organic ligands and pH on the leaching of copper from brake wear debris in model environmental solutions</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Copper leaching from a disc brake wear debris sample was examined in a variety of aqueous solutions to simulate potential leaching processes during rain events and in surface waters.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Synthetic rainwater leached 40percent of the total copper present in the brake wear debris into solution after 18 h in batch reactors, which was approximately three times more copper than that extracted by the US Environmental Protection Agency's Synthetic Precipitation Leaching Procedure.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Formate and acetate were responsible for the enhanced copper leaching, as demonstrated by higher average amounts of leached copper in synthetic rainwater with- versus without the organic acids (40 versus 31percent recovery).</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This observation suggests leaching tests that do not incorporate the appropriate types and concentrations of organic ligands present in rainwater will likely underestimate copper mobilization from brake wear debris during rain events.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Leaching of copper from the brake wear debris ranged from 23 to 40percent in solutions containing 3 to 15 mg C L–1 dissolved humic substances, and was higher still in solutions containing relatively high concentrations of the synthetic metal chelating agent ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Static pH tests demonstrated that copper leaching from brake wear debris is highly pH dependent, with more leaching occurring at lower solution pH values.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Leaching rate studies revealed that equilibrium generally was not attained within 48 h in the model solutions, indicating that additional copper can be expected to be released in environments where brake wear debris is exposed to long-term leaching processes.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Storm water runoff has been recognized as a major non-point source of pollutants in watersheds near urban areas.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, rainfall runoff from urban roadways often contains appreciable concentrations of metals that have adverse effects on ecological systems and human health.<REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A substantial portion of the metals contained in roadway runoff is believed to originate from vehicle component wear (brake and tire) and fluid leakage.<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although there have been reports of roadway runoff water quality, particularly those examining correlations between metal concentrations and factors such as rainfall intensity and traffic volume,<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit4"/> we still lack adequate information on important environmental processes such as metal leaching characteristics from specific non-point sources.</text></s></P><P><s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Wear debris from automobile brake pads have been identified as a potential non-point source of copper in surface waters.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, based on field measurements, laboratory studies and simplified estimated annual loadings, Davis et al<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit1"/>. concluded that brake wear debris would be a major source of copper in non-industrial urban storm water runoff.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Because of its potential contribution to copper impairments in streams and urban watersheds, brake wear debris characterization with respect to loadings, transport, fate, and environmental effects is becoming more of a pressing issue worldwide.</text></s></P><P><s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In a companion study,<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit5"/> we conducted two common standardized leaching tests, the US Environmental Protection Agency's (US EPA) Toxicity Characteristic Leaching Procedure (TCLP) and the State of California's Waste Extraction Test (WET), to quantify the rates and extents of copper mobilization from a disc brake wear debris sample.</text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although results from these two standardized tests are expected to help predict the potential for long-term copper leaching in urban watersheds, additional knowledge of the leaching characteristics by more environmentally relevant solutions is still needed.</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, the chemical composition and component concentrations in rainwater or storm water runoff are highly different from the TCLP and WET leaching solutions.</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Of common regulatory leaching tests, the US EPA's Synthetic Precipitation Leaching Procedure (SPLP) may be an alternative method to evaluate copper leaching from brake wear debris by storm water runoff.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The SPLP simulates the extraction of elements from wastes by percolating rainfall, utilizing a 60∶40 weight percent mixture of sulfuric acid and nitric acid.<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, because of its strictly inorganic composition, the SPLP may underestimate metal leaching by actual environmental solutions.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, reported chemical compositions of rainwater in urban areas reveal that organic ligands such as formate and acetate are typically present at concentrations ranging up to 100 µM.<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit8"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Urban storm water runoff often contains appreciable concentrations of natural and synthetic ligands that can complex metals.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It has been reported that concentrations of dissolved organic carbon (DOC) in runoff tend to increase as the rainfall passes through plants and soils before reaching surface waters.<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This process thus explains the sharp increase in surface water DOC concentrations generally observed with rainfall events.<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit11"/></text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As typical natural organic ligands, humic substances (HS) contain various moieties such as carboxyl, hydroxyl and amino groups that can complex metal cations in various ways.<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Consequently, the solubility and mobility of toxic metals are strongly influenced by the amounts and types of HS and other naturally-occurring and/or synthetic ligands.</text></s></P><P><s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Another factor of expected importance for metal mobilization is solution pH, because it is a critical parameter in determining the solubility and speciation of metals.<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit13"/></text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, one might expect copper leaching from brake wear debris to be highly dependent on pH.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A wide range of pH values (3.0 to 8.0) has been reported in rainfall near urban areas, the lower values resulting from acidification of rainfall by anthropogenic input of SO2 and NO2 from industrial and traffic activities.<REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit14"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To date, only a few studies have actually quantified copper leaching from brake wear debris.<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, to our knowledge, the importance of environmentally-relevant concentrations of the organic ligands present in rainwater and storm water runoff has not been evaluated.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, the objective of this study was to investigate the short-term copper leaching behavior from brake wear debris in model environmental solutions.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In particular, we focused on the role played by organic ligands typically found in rainwater, storm water runoff, and surface waters in this process.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Copper leaching in 18 h tests was examined in various aqueous solutions, including the SPLP solution, acidified deionized distilled water (DDW), synthetic rainwater, HS solutions, and solutions with ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid (EDTA).</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Static pH and kinetic leaching tests were also conducted to examine the effects of solution pH and contact time on the copper leaching process.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, because iron was the most abundant element present in the brake wear debris and could have potentially interfered with copper leaching,<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit5"/> its leaching from the wear debris was also examined.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Materials and reagents</HEADER><P><s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Details of the generation and characterization of the brake wear debris sample used in this study have been previously reported.<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total copper and iron contents of the brake wear debris were 10.8 and 28.6percent (g/g), respectively.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All solutions were prepared using DDW (Mega-Pure System MP-6A, Corning, NY) having a resistivity &gt;18.0 MΩ cm.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Reagents used to prepare synthetic rainwater solutions were potassium sulfate (K2SO4, EM Science), sodium nitrate (NaNO3, EM Science), magnesium sulfate (MgSO4, Sigma), ammonium chloride (NH4Cl, Sigma), calcium chloride (CaCl2·2H2O, EM Science), sodium formate (HCOONa, Sigma), and sodium acetate (C2H3O2Na, Sigma).</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All purchased chemical reagents were of analytical grade or better.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The chemical composition of the synthetic rainwater was based on a report of the species in typical rainwater collected in Los Angeles (USA) from 1985 to 1991.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit7"/></text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Concentrations of the chemical species contained in the synthetic rainwater are shown in Table 1.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To maximize the effects of the organic acids (formate and acetate) on copper leaching, concentrations near the reported maxima were used for the synthetic rainwater in this study.</text></s></P><P><s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The SPLP solution was prepared following standard procedures<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit6"/> to obtain leaching solutions of pH 5.0.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Two types of HS, a terrestrial HS and an aquatic HS, were utilized for this study.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Soil humic acid (SHA) and Suwannee River fulvic acid (SRFA) were obtained from the International Humic Substances Society (IHSS) and used without further purification.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Both HS were dissolved in DDW and stored at 4 °C at concentrations of ∼5 g C L–1.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>General physicochemical characteristics of the HS have been previously reported.<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit15"/></text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The carboxyl group contents of SHA and SRFA, determined by the IHSS, were 7.57 and 10.44 meq g–1 C, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>EDTA (EM Science, &gt;99.0percent), a synthetic organic metal chelating agent commonly found as a pollutant in surface waters,<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit16"/> was used for comparison with the HS solutions.</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>EDTA is a tetraprotic acid that can occupy up to six coordinating positions (i.e., hexadentate ligand) of a central metal ion.<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit16"/></text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>New high density polyethylene (HDPE) plastic bottles (Wheaton, Millville, NJ) were used for each extraction without additional treatment.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All other bottles and glassware used were soaked in 10percent HNO3 overnight and then rinsed with copious amounts of DDW.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Leaching tests</HEADER><P><s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Because of the small quantity of brake wear debris available,<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit5"/> a low solid-to-liquid ratio (1∶104) was maintained for all leaching experiments.</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the 18 h leaching tests, an appropriate mass (0.0025 g) of brake wear debris was weighed out in each bottle-point reactor (30 mL, Wheaton HDPE bottles) before transferring a fixed volume (25 mL) of leaching solution to each bottle.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These tests were conducted in triplicate using three separate reactors containing the same leaching solution.</text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All reactor bottles were equilibrated in the dark at room temperature (21 ± 2 °C) on an end-over-end tumbler rotating at approximately 25 rpm.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the end of the 18 h leaching tests, particulate materials were removed from the samples using an acid-washed 0.2 µm nylon membrane syringe filter (Gelman Laboratory), and the first 2 to 3 mL of each filtrate was discarded before collecting a filtered sample for copper and iron analyses.</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The pH of each filtered sample was measured to monitor pH changes during the leaching process.</text></s></P><P><s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The static pH leaching procedure was similar to that used above for the regular 18 h leaching tests, except for maintaining constant solution pH values by periodic adjustment with 0.1 N HNO3 or 0.1 N NaOH as needed during mixing.</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Once the pH deviation for each sample was confirmed to be less than ±0.2 from its target value, an additional 18 h mixing period was conducted for a total combined nominal leaching time of 48 h.</text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All static pH leaching tests were conducted with duplicate samples.</text></s></P><P><s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the kinetic leaching studies, an appropriate mass (0.02 g) of brake wear debris was added to 250 mL reactors (Nalgene HDPE bottles) followed by 200 mL of leaching solution.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Nominal sampling times for the kinetic studies (0.3, 1, 3, 10, 24, and 48 h) were selected based on preliminary experiments and encompassed the standard SPLP time period of 18 h.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At appropriate times, each reactor was vigorously shaken to achieve sample uniformity before taking a fixed volume (12 mL) of total sample (i.e. solution plus particulate brake wear debris).</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="Yes"/><text>This procedure ensured that a constant solid-to-liquid ratio was maintained throughout the kinetic leaching experiments despite the reduced total sample volume.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="Yes"/><text>In addition, the absence of measurable heterogeneity in the particulate brake wear debris<REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit5"/> ensured that each sample collected did not skew the later sampling results due to fractionation effects.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After sampling was completed, each reactor was then placed back on the tumbler for additional mixing and the samples were filtered and analyzed as described above.</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All kinetic leaching tests were conducted with duplicate samples.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Analytical methods</HEADER><P><s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All filtered samples were transferred to clean 15 mL plastic bottles (Wheaton HDPE bottle), acidified to pH 3 by adding 0.1 N nitric acid, and then analyzed for total copper and iron by inductively coupled plasma atomic emission spectrometry.<REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Operational parameters and conditions for the ICP analyses and quality control/assurance procedures have been previously reported.<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In all cases, external standard calibration curves were prepared in the corresponding leaching solutions.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>pH change in 18 h leaching tests</HEADER><P><s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although the initial pH of each leaching solution was nominally 5.0, sample pH values generally increased by the end of the 18 h tests (Table 2) due to the alkaline nature of the brake wear debris.</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, it has been reported that phenolic resins and metal oxides are common materials in brake pads.<REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit17"/></text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Final pH values ranged from 5.8 to 6.2 for most of the leaching solutions, with the exception of the concentrated synthetic rainwater (pH = 5.3) and the higher EDTA concentration (pH = 5.0).</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The high ligand concentrations used in the latter two solutions apparently kept these samples reasonably well buffered.</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The pH values for the two 15 mg C L–1 HS solutions increased even with this relatively high concentration, but the carboxyl contents of the solutions (i.e., 0.114 and 0.157 meq L–1 for SHA and SRFA, respectively) were still much lower than those of the concentrated rainwater and the 0.01 M EDTA solutions (4.5 and 40 meq L–1, respectively).</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Copper leaching in model rainwater solutions</HEADER><P><s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Table 2 presents the 18 h copper leaching results for model rainwater solutions.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The SPLP solution, designed by the US EPA to simulate the leaching expected due to percolating rainfall, showed the least amount of copper leaching among all the model rainwater solutions tested.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The lower degree of copper leaching observed with the SPLP solution is likely due in part to its higher final pH value, although it should be noted that this value was statistically equivalent to the final pH measured for DDW (p value of 0.0532 based on a t-test of the means for α = 0.05 using a two-tailed t distribution).</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results appear to be consistent with a previous report<REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit18"/> that lower leaching of arsenic, chromium and copper from a contaminated soil was observed with SPLP solutions than with DDW adjusted to the same pH values.</text></s></P><P><s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The synthetic rainwater solution leached approximately two and three times more copper from the brake wear debris than DDW and the SPLP solution, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The higher leaching with the synthetic rainwater was statistically significant as demonstrated by the respective p values of 0.0115 and 0.00028 based on t-tests of the means for α = 0.05 using a two-tailed t distribution.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The most plausible explanation for the enhanced leaching by synthetic rainwater over DDW and the SPLP solution is that it contained formate and acetate, two organic acids typically found in urban rainwater samples.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further confirmation of their ability to enhance copper leaching from the brake wear debris can be seen by comparing the average leaching results for the synthetic rainwater with and without organic acids present (40 versus 31percent, p value of 0.0074, Table 2).</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The combined results above suggest that leaching tests<REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit19"/> that have used DDW or aqueous solutions containing only inorganic anions (e.g., SPLP) likely have underestimated actual copper leaching from brake wear debris during rainfall events and/or in storm water runoff.</text></s></P><P><s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The inorganic anions present in the synthetic rainwater did not appear to have a major effect on the leaching of copper from the brake wear debris.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, although a factor of 50 increase in the concentration of ions in the inorganic synthetic rainwater increased copper leaching from 30.74 to 34.20percent, the increase was not statistically significant (p value = 0.0850; Table 2).</text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, when the formate and acetate concentrations were also increased by a factor of 50, copper leaching increased dramatically from 40.07 to 71.67percent (p value = 0.00092).</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This result corroborates the predominant role that organic ligands play in copper leaching from brake wear debris versus the inorganic anions present in rainwater.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, it should be noted that the increase in copper leaching observed with the concentrated synthetic rainwater may also be attributed in part to the lower final pH value (i.e., 5.3 versus 5.8), because previous studies have shown dramatic differences in metal leaching with changes in pH.<REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit18"/><REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit20"/></text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The influence of pH on copper leaching from brake wear debris will be addressed later.</text></s></P><P><s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Despite its high abundance in the brake wear debris sample, iron was generally leached only in very small amounts (0.02 to 1.2percent) by the SPLP and other model rainwater solutions (Table 2).</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, little to no competition between copper and iron for the organic ligands would be expected because of the relatively low dissolved iron concentrations present.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Copper leaching in HS and EDTA solutions</HEADER><P><s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The two different HS showed similar copper leaching abilities at both the lower and higher concentrations tested (3 and 15 mg C L–1, respectively; Table 2).</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This finding was unexpected, because the higher carboxyl group content of SRFA versus SHA should have provided more copper binding ligands and, thus, higher average copper leaching values.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For both HS, the amount of copper leached did not exceed 40percent at the higher concentration tested.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the higher HS concentration did result in nearly a factor of 2 increase in copper leaching, indicating that large HS concentration variations in storm water runoff and surface waters will likely influence copper release from brake wear debris.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Such temporal variations in dissolved organic carbon concentrations in runoff are known to be highly dependent on precipitation volumes and hydrological pathways.<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit21"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>EDTA is a strong metal chelating agent that can form very stable and soluble complexes with metals.<REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit16"/></text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is a common synthetic organic ligand often found in natural waters because of its widespread use and resistance to degradation.<REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit16"/><REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, Bedsworth and Sedlak<REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit22"/> reported EDTA concentrations in effluent samples from water pollution control plants in the San Francisco Bay area ranging from 0.1 to 2 µM.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Xue et al<REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit16"/>. reported EDTA concentrations of 20–60 nM in the Glatt River (Switzerland).</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although EDTA concentrations in storm water runoff are likely to be low to non-existent,<REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit22"/> its presence in many surface waters worldwide suggests an assessment be made of its ability to mobilize copper from brake wear debris.</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From Table 2, it can be observed that more than 50percent of the total copper present in the brake wear debris was mobilized by the relatively high EDTA concentration of 80 µM, suggesting that copper leaching from brake wear debris may be facilitated by EDTA in natural waters.</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the very high EDTA concentration of 10 mM, most (∼90percent) of the copper was leached from the brake wear debris.</text></s></P><P><s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Similarly to the model rainwater results, only a small fraction of iron was leached from the brake wear debris by HS and the lower EDTA concentration tested (0.1–0.5 and 1percent, respectively).</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Only at the very high EDTA concentration was a large amount of iron (44percent) leached into solution.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The results observed here for copper versus iron leaching are reasonably consistent with the findings of our previous study,<REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit5"/> in which copper leaching ranged from a factor of 3 to 10 times higher than iron in standard extraction solutions.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Copper leaching in static pH tests</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Static pH leaching tests covering a wide range of pH values were performed with the SPLP, synthetic rainwater with and without organic acids, and the two HS solutions to investigate its effects on copper mobilization from the brake wear debris (Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In all five solutions, copper leaching was strongly dependent on pH, with higher copper leaching generally occurring at lower pH values.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The observed decrease in copper mobilization with increasing pH can be explained by its effect on total copper solubility.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, dissolved copper concentrations are typically limited by the solubility of a solid phase such as copper oxide (tenorite) and/or copper chloride hydroxide (atacamite) at pH values above 6.<REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit13"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>More copper was leached from the brake wear debris by the formate- and acetate-containing synthetic rainwater versus the SPLP solution over most of the pH range examined (Fig. 1a), consistent with results from the 18 h leaching tests discussed above.</text></s> <s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The importance of the two organic acids is highlighted by the higher copper leaching observed in their presence versus their absence for most pH values.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is only for pH values less than 4 that the two curves collapse together, indicating that the organic acids do not enhance copper leaching at these low pH values.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This observation is consistent with the ionization state of the two organic acids (i.e., pKa values of 4.75 and 3.75 for acetate and formate, respectively), because H+ competition for COO– binding sites becomes stronger with decreasing pH.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast with the 18 h leaching tests, however, the SPLP and inorganic synthetic rainwater solutions gave relatively similar copper leaching results over the majority of the pH range tested.</text></s></P><P><s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>More copper leaching from the brake wear debris was observed with the SRFA versus SHA solutions over the pH range examined, although the differences were not always significant.</text></s> <s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This observation differs slightly from the 18 h leaching tests, which showed similar copper leaching values for the two HS.</text></s> <s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unlike the model rainwater solutions, appreciable amounts of copper were still being leached into solution by the two HS at pH values above 8.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In general, the degree of HS ionization increases with increasing pH, thus resulting in greater negative charges on the molecules and increased electrostatic potentials that attract cations present in solution.<REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit23"/></text></s> <s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Carboxyl and phenolic groups are considered to be the predominant HS functional groups responsible for complexing metals.</text></s></P><P><s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Static pH test results for iron revealed that it was leached only under relatively acidic conditions (pH &lt; 5.0), although the same general trend (i.e., increased metal leaching with decreasing pH) that was observed with copper also applied to iron (Fig. 2).</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Leached iron amounts only reached ∼15percent of the total iron present in the brake wear debris at the lowest pH value tested (pH 3).</text></s> <s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This observation suggests that although iron is the most abundant element present in the brake wear debris, it likely does not interfere with copper leaching under solution conditions similar to those examined here.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Copper leaching in kinetic studies</HEADER><P><s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Copper leaching was monitored as a function of time for the SPLP, synthetic rainwater, and SRFA solutions (Fig. 3).</text></s> <s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Measured pH values for all samples sharply increased from the initial pH by the first sampling time (20 min) and then slowly increased thereafter (Fig. 3a).</text></s> <s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Consistent with the results above, copper leaching at all observation times was highest with the synthetic rainwater solution (Fig. 3b).</text></s> <s sid="132"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For all three solutions, copper was released rapidly within the first few hours followed by slower leaching at longer contact times.</text></s> <s sid="133"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although 80 to 90percent of the copper in solution at 48 h was leached within the first 24 h, it was apparent that very slow copper leaching continued beyond the longest sampling time tested.</text></s> <s sid="134"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The environmental implications of our observed leaching rate results are not fully known, but one can reasonably speculate that such temporal effects likely contribute to “first flush” phenomena in watersheds<REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit4"/><REF ID="R-53" REFID="cit24"/> and also suggest that brake wear debris may be an ongoing low-level non-point source of copper in environments where it is exposed to long-term leaching processes.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="135"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An appreciable amount (40percent) of the copper present in our brake wear debris sample was released into a synthetic rainwater solution after 18 h.</text></s> <s sid="136"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This value was higher than the leaching observed with either DDW or an SPLP solution.</text></s> <s sid="137"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our results demonstrate that organic ligands and chelating agents present in rainwater, urban storm water runoff, and/or surface waters enhance the leaching of copper from brake wear debris.</text></s> <s sid="138"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Irrespective of the particular leaching solution used, copper mobilization from the brake wear debris showed a very high dependence on pH, with the highest leaching occurring under more acidic conditions.</text></s> <s sid="139"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Despite its high abundance in the brake wear debris, iron was not leached to a great extent in most of the solutions tested.</text></s> <s sid="140"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The overall results of this study suggest that monitoring important solution chemistry parameters such as pH and the presence of potential metal binding organic ligands in natural waters and storm water runoff will allow for a better understanding of the environmental fate of copper resulting from brake wear debris loadings to watersheds.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>