<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310806f" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Synthesis of nanostructured materials in supercritical ammonia: nitrides, metals and oxides</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In this study, the synthesis of nanostructured particles of nitrides (Cr2N, Co2N, Fe4N, Cu3N, Ni3N), metal (Cu) and oxides (Al2O3, TiO2, Ga2O3) by using supercritical ammonia in the reaction medium is described.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The elaboration process is based on the thermal decomposition of metal precursors in a supercritical ammonia–methanol mixture at a range of temperatures between 170 and 290 °C at about 16 MPa.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Nitrides are obtained at relatively low temperatures in comparison with classical processes.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is shown that the chemical composition of the produced materials can be controlled by the adjustment of process operating conditions (pressure, temperature, metal precursor concentration and residence time in the elaboration reactor) and by the knowledge of the Gibbs free energy of oxide formation of the studied metal.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Today one of the main challenges in materials science concerns the synthesis of nanomaterials since they exhibit interesting properties which can be different of those of bulk materials.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For instance, optical, magnetic and electrical properties are sensitive to size effects.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore nanosized particles are equally very efficient in the field of catalysis due to high ratio of surface to volume.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Consequently, numerous processes of nanomaterial synthesis have been investigated aiming to control their size, morphology, structure and chemical composition.</text></s></P><P><s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this context, supercritical processes are an interesting alternative to elaborate nanomaterials.</text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A large number of studies concerning the production of nanoparticles have been published.</text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There exist two main routes of material elaboration in supercritical media: processes using a physical transformation (rapid expansion of supercritical solution, gas antisolvent, …)<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/> and less commonly processes using a chemical transformation.<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This work refers to the chemical transformation of metal precursors in a supercritical fluid.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>More precisely the metal precursor is thermally decomposed to metal atoms which give access to the nucleation and growth of particles.</text></s></P><P><s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous works devoted to copper particle synthesis in a supercritical mixture CO2–ethanol demonstrated that this process allows control of the size, the size distribution and the morphology of particles as a function of the operating conditions.<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper, our objective is to demonstrate the potential of this process to also control the chemical composition of materials.</text></s></P><P><s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Many studies have concerned oxide synthesis in supercritical media such as oxide elaboration by hydrothermal synthesis (CeO2 and LiCoO2)<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit11"/> or the synthesis of MgAl2O4 in supercritical ethanol.<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, synthesis of metal particles by supercritical fluid processing has been equally studied: (i) preparation of nickel, cobalt and iron nanoparticles by chemical reduction of NiCl2, CoCl2 and FeBr3, respectively;<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit13"/> (ii) copper and silver nanoparticle synthesis in reverse micelles in compressed propane and supercritical ethane solutions;<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit14"/><REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit15"/> (iii) synthesis of silver and copper nanoparticles in a water-in-supercritical carbon dioxide microemulsion by chemical reduction of Ag+ and Cu2+;<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit16"/> (iv) the reactive supercritical fluid spray fluid processing method for silver nanoparticles elaboration;<REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit17"/> (v) radiolytically induced synthesis of silver nanoparticles in supercritical ethane;<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit18"/>….</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, nitride synthesis has been investigated to a lesser extent: (i) the synthesis of TiN in supercritical cryogenic nitrogen by self-propagating-high-temperature synthesis (6.21 MPa, −141 °C);<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit19"/> (ii) GaN synthesis by an ammonothermal process (100–500 MPa, 550 °C);<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit20"/> (iii) solvothermal synthesis of GaN in supercritical ammonia (100–250 MPa, 400–800 °C);<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit21"/> (iv) elaboration of Ni3N in supercritical ammonia from Ni(NH3)6Cl2 (NaNH2, 250 °C and 200 MPa).<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit22"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper we propose to study the influence of process operating conditions on the control of material nature, and more precisely, on nanostructured nitride elaboration in supercritical ammonia.</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After a brief description of the experimental set-up and operating conditions, the different types of obtained nanostructured materials as a function of process operating conditions are described.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Experimental set-up</HEADER><P><s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The experimental set-up is a continuous process (Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is composed of two pumps: one for pumping a solvent (NH3 or CO2), the other for pumping a cosolvent (methanol or ethanol) to dissolve the metal precursor.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The decomposition reaction occurs inside the reactor which is maintained at constant pressure and temperature.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The particles elaborated in the reactor are dragged by the flowing fluid to a second vessel (the collector) placed at the outlet of the reactor.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the collector, the particles are stopped by a metal filter placed perpendicularly to the fluid flow.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the end of the experiment, the powder is collected.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The powders were dry and free of solvent.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Experiments</HEADER><P><s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The experimental conditions are summarized in Table 1.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Ammonia was chosen as the reaction medium, except for experiment 1, since it exhibits a high reducing power and its critical temperature (TC = 132.4 °C and PC = 11.29 MPa) is lower than that of precursor decomposition (most of the metal precursors are thermally decomposed at temperatures above 200 °C).</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Methanol is used as cosolvent (molar ratio: 70percent NH3–30percent methanol) in order to solubilize the metal precursor and to decrease its decomposition temperature (reducing agent).</text></s></P><P><s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the reaction media, there are always traces of oxygen.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>More precisely, the potential sources of oxygen are: the cosolvent (methanol) and metal precursors (of the acetylacetonate family).</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The total flow rate was of 1.02 l h−1.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Experiment 1 was performed in a supercritical mixture of CO2–ethanol.</text></s></P><P><s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Three types of metal precursors were tested: metal acetylacetonates (acac), metal hexafluoroacetylacetonates (hfac) and a metal diisopropoxide bis(acetylacetonate) (OPri)2(acac)2.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All these precursors were provided by Sigma-Aldrich or Strem and used without any further purification.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Experimental pressures were about 16 MPa and temperatures between 180 and 290 °C as a function of decomposition temperatures of studied metal precursors.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Characterization</HEADER><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The chemical nature of materials was identified by conventional X-ray powder diffraction (XRPD: Cu-Kα radiation).</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When crystallized domains were too small to be detected by XRD, electron diffraction was used (JEOL 2000FX microscope); samples were prepared by deposition of a drop of powder dispersed in ethanol on a copper carbon grid.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The particle size and morphology were investigated by scanning electron microscopy, SEM (JEOL 840 microscope) and by transmission electron microscopy using the dark field method.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The particle size was determined by manual counting.</text></s></P><P><s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In a few cases, the materials were amorphous and a thermal treatment was performed from 20 to 1000 °C under argon in a tubular furnace.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The thermal treatment led to the crystallization of amorphous materials.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The obtained crystalline powder can be characterized by the above methods.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Results</HEADER><P><s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The results, structure, chemical composition, morphology and size of crystallized domains of the obtained materials are given in Table 2.</text></s></P><P><s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the case of copper hexafluoroacetylacetonate, the chemical composition of recovered materials depends on the fluid nature.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>CO2–ethanol (200 °C–20 MPa) leads to spherical metal copper particles of few micrometers diameter constituted of crystalline nanodomains of about 10 nm (Fig. 2(a)) whilst in NH3–methanol (200 °C–16 MPa), cubic copper nitride monocrystals (10 µm) were obtained (Fig. 2(b)).</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The difference of morphology between the metal and nitride has already been discussed<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit9"/> and is due to the initial concentration of copper precursor as explained elsewhere.</text></s></P><P><s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The synthesis of materials in supercritical NH3–methanol from nickel and cobalt precursors leads to the pure metal nitrides: nickel nitride and cobalt nitride.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As far as Ni3N and Co2N particles were concerned, they are organized in shapeless aggregates of a few micrometers constituted of crystalline nanodomains of 20–100 and 60–120 nm, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These materials were identified by XRD and electron diffraction (Fig. 3).</text></s></P><P><s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The decomposition of iron and chromium precursors in supercritical NH3–methanol induces the formation of oxide/nitride mixtures, more precisely, Fe2O3/Fe4N and Cr2O3/Cr2N, as shown in Fig. 4.</text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mixture Fe2O3/Fe4N is composed of crystalline nanodomains of 10 nm aggregated in spherical particles of 50 nm, so the chemical composition was identified by electron diffraction (Fig. 4).</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Concerning the second mixture, Cr2O3/Cr2N, it was amorphous after the synthesis thus a thermal treatment was performed.</text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The obtained material was crystallized and characterized by XRD (Fig. 4(b)).</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A mixture of Cr2O3 and Cr2N, was synthesized with two different chromium precursors: chromium(iii) acetylacetonate and chromium(iii) hexafluoroacetylacetonate.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Oxides were obtained by decomposition of gallium, titanium and aluminium precursors under the same experimental conditions (supercritical NH3–methanol).</text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These decompositions were performed at 225–230 °C, 16 MPa (Table 1) and led to the growth of Ga2O3, TiO2 and Al2O3, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Ga2O3 and TiO2 powders are formed by aggregated crystalline nanodomains of 1–10 and 4–50 nm, respectively, as shown in Fig. 5.</text></s></P><P><s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast to the above oxides, aluminium oxide was amorphous.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Al2O3 particles were spherical particles of about 2 µm (Fig. 6(a)).</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A thermal treatment was applied to the amorphous material and led to well crystallized aluminium oxide particles as shown in Fig. 6(b).</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The choice of the solvent has a great influence on the chemical composition of materials as demonstrated above between syntheses in CO2 (metallic copper) and NH3 (copper nitride).</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>CO2 is an inert solvent whereas NH3 reacts with the metal atoms to give nitrides.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This process of material elaboration in supercritical ammonia allows nitrides to be obtained, in a controlled manner, at relatively low temperature and pressure in comparison with other published methods.<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit23"/><REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit24"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Beyond the case of copper, metal nitride formation does not depend only on the solvent choice but also on the nature of the metal.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In fact three different behaviours have been observed: nitride formation (Cu3N, Ni3N and Co2N), mixture oxide/nitride formation (Fe2O3/Fe4N and Cr2O3/Cr2N) and oxide formation (Ga2O3, TiO2 and Al2O3).</text></s></P><P><s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To better understand these results, the affinity of the different studied metals with oxygen was quantified from an Ellingham diagram of oxide formation (Fig. 7).</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This diagram was obtained from the literature<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit25"/> and was completed by the calculation of the curve relative to the formation of Ga2O3.<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit26"/></text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This diagram is established at atmospheric pressure but it can be used under our pressure conditions.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The pressure dependence of the Gibbs free energy is given by eqn. (1):<EQN ID="eqn1"><EQ-S ID="s73">ΔG(P) = ΔG(P0) + ΔVP</EQ-S></EQN>with ΔG(P), the Gibbs free energy at pressure P, ΔG(P0), the Gibbs free energy at pressure P0 and ΔV, the molar volume.</text></s></P><P><s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, ΔV is inversely proportional to the Young modulus of the concerned oxide and so can be neglected; in these conditions, we can assume ΔG(P) ≅ ΔG(P0).</text></s></P><P><s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>On the one hand, metals for which the Gibbs free energy of oxide formation is weak (Cu, Ni and Co) tend to only give metal nitrides because the ammonolysis reaction is favoured relative to the metal oxidation reaction by the oxygen atoms dissolved in the reaction media.</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>On the other hand, metals for which the Gibbs free energy of oxide formation is high (Ti and Al) lead to metal oxides.</text></s></P><P><s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As far as iron and chromium were concerned, these are located in an intermediate range of affinity with oxygen and there is a competition between ammonolysis and oxidation which involves the formation of mixtures Cr2O3/Cr2N and Fe2O3/Fe4N.</text></s></P><P><s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The affinity of gallium with oxygen is in the same range as that of iron and chromium, but only the oxide was obtained.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The kinetics of the gallium oxidation reaction seems to be favoured in regard to the thermodynamics.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Beyond the control of size, size distribution and morphology, the process of material preparation in supercritical media, developed at ICMCB, allows to control the chemical composition of the synthesized nanostructured materials.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This process is based on the thermal decomposition of metal precursors in supercritical media, more precisely, in a supercritical ammonia–methanol mixture used in this study.</text></s></P><P><s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The thermal decomposition in supercritical ammonia–methanol mixtures of different metal precursors (precursors of Cu, Ni, Co, Fe, Cr, Ga, Al and Ti) was studied at a range of temperatures between 170 and 290 °C at about 16 MPa.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Three different mechanisms were observed with the formation of nitrides (Cr2N, Co2N, Cu3N, Ni3N, Fe4N), metal (Cu) and oxides (Al2O3, TiO2, Ga2O3).</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In most of the experiments, the synthesized powders were composed of crystalline nanodomains (&lt;100 nm) aggregated in spherical or shapeless particles (except for the Cr and Al compounds which were amorphous).</text></s></P><P><s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, the use of supercritical ammonia in the reaction media allows the elaboration of nitrides at relatively low temperatures if the Gibbs free energy of oxide formation of the metal is not too high (Cr, Co, Cu, Ni and Fe).</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>By contrast, only oxides are obtained with metals for which the Gibbs free energy of oxide formation is high (Al and Ti).</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>