<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310495h" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Reactions of hydroxyl radicals with trichloroethene and tetrachloroethene in argon matrices at 12 K</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Irradiation of argon matrices at 12 K containing hydrogen peroxide and tetrachloroethene using the output from a medium-pressure mercury lamp gives rise to the carbonyl compound trichloroacetyl chloride (CCl3CClO).</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Similarly trichloroethene gives dichloroacetyl chloride (CCl2HCClO) – predominantly in the gauche form – under the same conditions.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It appears that the reaction is initiated by homolysis of the O–O bond of H2O2 to give OH radicals, one of which adds to the double bond of an alkene molecule.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reaction then proceeds by abstraction of the H atom of the hydroxyl group and Cl-atom migration.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This mechanism has been explored by the use of DFT calculations to back up the experimental findings.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mechanism is analogous to that shown by the simple hydrocarbon alkenes.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The chemistry of the troposphere is dominated by the oxidation of hydrocarbons and during daytime the hydroxyl radical is the most important oxidant.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is formed by photolysis of ozone to yield O(1D) atoms which then react with water to give hydroxyl radicals:-<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/><EQN><EQ-S ID="s9">O3 + hν → O(1D) + O2</EQ-S><EQ-S ID="s10">O(1D) + H2O → 2OH.</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For most hydrocarbons in the troposphere oxidation is initiated by the hydroxyl radical and indeed this radical acts as a cleaning agent since many of the products of oxidation are water-soluble and can be rained out of the atmosphere.<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit4"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reactions of hydroxyl radicals with alkenes have been studied in some detail both in the gas phase and in low-temperature matrices.<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is clear that the first stage of reaction is addition of the OH radical to the double bond to form hydroxyalkyl radicals.</text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These may be further oxidised to carbonyl products.<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit8"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compared to the information available for simple alkenes much less is known about the chloroalkenes.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, these man-made pollutants have been identified in urban areas and have several industrial and non-industrial sources.</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>They have been found in samples taken from points adjacent to a municipal incinerator, a waste collection centre and a sewage treatment plant.<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Gas-phase measurements show that the initial step of the reaction is analogous to that of the hydrocarbon alkenes i.e. addition of the OH radical to give an energy-rich OH-haloalkene complex,<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit3"/> which may either decompose back to reactants, or be collisionally stabilised to give the hydroxyalkyl radical:- <EQN><EQ-S ID="s19">OH + CH2CHCl = HOC2H3Cl*</EQ-S><EQ-S ID="s20">HOC2H3Cl* + M → HOC2H3Cl + M.</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is possible also that a halogen atom may be eliminated from the activated complex to give a vinyl alcohol – for the activated complex of chloroethene and OH the elimination of a Cl atom is exothermic by about 45 kJ mol−1:- <EQN><EQ-S ID="s22">HOC2H3Cl* → H2CCH(OH) + Cl.</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, it appears that Cl-atom elimination is, in fact, a relatively minor pathway under these conditions.<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit10"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Decomposition of the hydroxychloroalkyl radicals certainly occurs in the troposphere but the mechanisms are uncertain.</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reactions probably proceed by further oxidation.<REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Product analysis has shown that HC(O)Cl is formed in the reaction of vinyl chloride or trichloroethene and OH radicals, and that phosgene (COCl2) is formed in the reaction of trichloroethene or tetrachloroethene and OH radicals.<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These C1 products are unlikely to be primary products, however.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Accordingly, we have carried out a study of the reactions of trichloroethene and tetrachloroethene with hydroxyl radicals in argon matrices at 12 K. In this way we hoped to identify products of these reactions and hence to learn something of the reaction mechanisms.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In particular we wished to search for and identify chlorine-containing carbonyl products and to obtain evidence that, like the hydrocarbon alkenes, the reaction within the matrix is initiated by addition of the OH radical to the double bond of the alkene.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental section</HEADER><P><s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The matrix-isolation apparatus used at Reading has been described in detail elsewhere.<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit11"/><REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The experiments were carried out in a very similar manner to previous experiments on hydrocarbon alkenes.<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Samples of trichloroethene (Aldrich, 99.5percent pure), tetrachloroethene (Aldrich, &gt;99percent pure), dichloroacetyl chloride (Aldrich, 99percent pure) and trichloroacetyl chloride (Aldrich, 99percent pure) were used as supplied after freeze–pump–thaw purification.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Gas phase mixtures of the alkene under investigation with argon were made up on a vacuum line using standard manometric techniques.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hydrogen peroxide vapour was obtained from the H2O2–urea adduct<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit13"/> and was co-condensed with the alkene/argon mixture.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Matrices were photolysed using the broad-band ultraviolet output from a medium-pressure mercury lamp.</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>It has been shown elsewhere that this method is an efficient route to generate OH radicals.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit8"/><REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit14"/></text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Spectra were recorded on a Perkin-Elmer 983 dispersive spectrophotometer with a typical resolution of 2 cm−1 or better.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Data were saved onto a Perkin-Elmer data station, transferred to a computer and manipulated using GRAMS software.</text></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>DFT calculations were carried out using the Gaussian 98 computational package<REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit15"/> with the 6-31G(d) basis sets and the B3-LYP functional.</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>There were no imaginary frequencies generated by any of the calculations.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When a hydrogen peroxide-doped argon matrix (at 12 K) initially containing ca.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>1percent of tetrachloroethene was subjected to broad-band UV-visible photolysis for a period of 2 h the infrared bands of tetrachloroethene<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit16"/><REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit17"/> (916 (vs) 781 (vs) cm−1 with weaker features at 898 (m), 811 (m) and 760 (m) cm−1) and of hydrogen peroxide<REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit13"/> (3582 (s) and 1291 (s) cm−1) were seen to decay.</text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the same time new features appeared which may be assigned to H2O<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit18"/><REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit19"/><REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit20"/><REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit21"/> (3590 and 1624 cm−1), CO2<REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit22"><REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit23"/><REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit24"/></REF> (2342 and 665 cm−1) and CO<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit25"/><REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit26"/> (2143 cm−1).</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Bands were also observed at 1809, 870 and 852 cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These are assigned to the product trichloroacetyl chloride CCl3CClO.<REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit8"/><REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit16"/><REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit27"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to confirm that the product of this reaction is indeed tricholoroacetyl chloride an authentic sample of this compound was isolated at 1percent concentration in an argon matrix at 12 K and the infrared spectrum was recorded.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In Table 1 are compared the infrared spectra of the matrix-isolated and liquid<REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit27"/> compound.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unfortunately only three absorptions were observed for the product of the matrix reaction of C2Cl4 with OH radicals.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, these correspond well to the two strongest bands of matrix-isolated CCl3ClO (see Table 1).</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The band at 1809 is assigned to the ν(CO) vibration and those at 870 and 852 to a matrix-split band (see Fig. 1) arising from the antisymmetric stretch of the CCl3 moiety.<REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit27"/></text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The match between these spectra, although not entirely unambiguous, does suggest that CCl3ClO is produced by the reaction of C2Cl4 with OH radicals in an argon matrix.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When photolysis was continued for further periods of 2 h and 17 h, the spectral changes reported above continue in that bands of the reactants decayed while those of the product trichloroacetyl chloride and of H2O, CO2 and CO increased.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Following photolysis the matrix was annealed to 40 K and re-cooled to 12 K for 5 cycles.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This had the effect of sharpening the bands but did not have any noticeable effect on their intensities.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The behaviour of the spectral features upon photolysis and annealing is detailed in Table 2 and the spectra are illustrated in Fig. 1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>We have previously carried out similar experiments where hydrogen peroxide is photolysed in matrices containing ethene or other simple alkenes.<REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>It was shown that under the conditions of these experiments photolysis of H2O2 proceeds via O–O bond rupture to yield OH radicals.<REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-53" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-54" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Reaction of the OH radical with the alkene substrate yields a hydroxyalkyl radical which may suffer one of two fates.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Upon annealing, reaction with a second OH radical in the matrix cage gives the diol, whereas prolonged photolysis causes decomposition of the radical to form a carbonyl product.</text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It seems reasonable to suppose that a similar mechanism (Scheme 1) operates in the case of tetrachloroethene.</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this case, however, there is no sign of any bands belonging to a radical intermediate, nor were any major changes detected upon annealing the matrix.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is pertinent, therefore, to discuss briefly why the two systems may behave rather differently.</text></s></P><P><s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>First is the possibility that it is the absorption properties of the radicals that determines their lifetime within the matrix.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Addition of chlorine atoms to a saturated organic compound typically red-shifts the absorbance maximum by some 5–10 nm,<REF ID="R-55" REFID="cit16"/> making photolysis, under the conditions of our experiments, more efficient.</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We found it impossible to verify this point by specifically excluding certain irradiation wavelengths by using filters.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This was because of the long photolysis times required, which become impossibly long when filters are employed and the light intensity is substantially reduced.</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A second important point concerns the stability of the radical intermediates.</text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Chloroalkenes with one or more vinylic chlorine atoms are stabilised by a mesomeric interaction between the chlorine atom and the CC double bond.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When hydroxyl radicals react with the chloroalkene this mesomeric interaction is lost.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This destabilisation is reflected in the lower rate constants for the reaction of OH radicals with steadily more chlorinated alkenes as shown in Table 3.<REF ID="R-56" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-57" REFID="cit28"/><REF ID="R-58" REFID="cit29"/></text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Once a carbonyl product is formed, provided an acyl chlorine atom is present, a mesomeric effect with the carbonyl double bond is possible.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus the radical intermediate is destabilised with respect to both reactant alkene and product carbonyl.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Finally it is known that chlorine atom migration in a system like this is more efficient than hydrogen atom migration because a chlorine atom readily forms a cyclical transition state between the two carbon atoms.<REF ID="R-59" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These factors probably all contribute to the destabilisation of the hydroxychloroalkyl radical with respect to the carbonyl product and suggest why the radical was not seen in the matrix in this case.</text></s></P><P><s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>One important feature to emerge from our experiments with tetrachloroethene is that no product containing a C–H bond was formed.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This counts against an alternative mechanism in which the carbonyl product is formed by Cl-atom elimination or abstraction from the hydroxychloroalkyl radical intermediate.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This would yield an enol which could rearrange, upon photolysis, to give a keto product, but in this case the keto product would contain a C–H group:- <EQN><EQ-S ID="s78">HOCCl2CCl2 → HOClCCCl2 + Cl</EQ-S><EQ-S ID="s79">HOClCCCl2 → OCClCHCl2.</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The observation that no C–H-containing product was seen provides strong support for the mechanism shown in Scheme 1, where H-atom abstraction is followed by Cl-atom migration to give the carbonyl product.</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This observation is in keeping with the findings from gas-phase studies where Cl-atom elimination from similar hydroxy radicals was found to be only a minor pathway.<REF ID="R-60" REFID="cit10"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is of interest to note that CCl3CClO has previously been detected on oxidation of C2Cl4 in gaseous mixtures containing O2 and NO.<REF ID="R-61" REFID="cit30"/></text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Under these conditions it was suggested that this reaction proceeds by addition of a Cl atom to C2Cl4 to yield the C2Cl5 radical which adds to O2.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Subsequent loss of an O (by oxidation of NO to NO2) and a Cl atom yields CCl3CClO:- <EQN><EQ-S ID="s85">Cl + CCl2CC2 → CCl3CCl2</EQ-S><EQ-S ID="s86">CCl3CCl2 + O2 + M → CCl3CCl2O2 + M</EQ-S><EQ-S ID="s87">CCl3CCl2O2 + NO → CCl3CClO + NO2 + Cl.</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although a similar mechanism cannot operate in our system where neither O2 nor NO is present it is nonetheless pertinent to note the production of CCl3CClO as a product of oxidation of C2Cl4.</text></s></P><P><s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We next turned our attention to the reaction of tricholorethene with hydroxyl radicals.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Here the reaction is potentially more complicated because there are two possible radical intermediates and two possible carbonyl products.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The possible reaction pathways are shown in Scheme 2.</text></s></P><P><s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Two hours' irradiation of a hydrogen peroxide-doped argon matrix at 12 K containing ca.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>1percent of trichloroethene led to a reduction in the intensity of the bands of hydrogen peroxide<REF ID="R-62" REFID="cit13"/> (3583 and 1291 cm−1) and of tricholoroethene<REF ID="R-63" REFID="cit16"/><REF ID="R-64" REFID="cit17"/> (3094, 1593, 936, 846, 784 and 632 cm−1).</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the same time new bands appeared (alongside those of H2O, CO2 and CO) at 2792, 1804, 993, 766 and 587 cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Prolonged photolysis for a total period of 4 or 21 h caused product bands to increase further in intensity.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Annealing to 40 K and recooling to 12 K had little effect other than to sharpen the bands slightly.</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The spectral changes are illustrated in Figs. 2 and 3 and the behaviour of the bands upon photolysis is listed in Table 4.</text></s></P><P><s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The new bands seen upon photolysis clearly belong to a carbonyl product.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Assuming that the reaction mechanism is analogous to that of the hydrocarbon alkenes or of tetrachloroethene, the question is, is this product chloral or dicholoroacetyl chloride?</text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to attempt to answer this question an authentic sample of dichloroacetyl chloride was isolated at 1percent concentration in an argon matrix.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Bands were observed for this matrix-isolated compound at 2801 (s), 1815 (vs), 1784 (vs), 1083 (s), 993 (s), 800 (s), 786 (s), 756 (vs) and 583 (s) cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Comparison with literature data for the gaseous and liquid compound show that both syn and gauche forms of this molecule have been isolated.</text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The bands at 2801, 1815, 993, 800, 756 and 583 cm−1 may be assigned to the gauche form, while those at 2801, 1784, 1083 and 786 cm−1 arise from the syn conformer.<REF ID="R-65" REFID="cit31"/></text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When these spectra are compared with the spectrum obtained by photolysing C2Cl3H and H2O2 in an argon matrix it is suggested that the gauche form of dichloroacetyl chloride is formed predominantly under these conditions.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All of the product bands match well with observed bands of gauche-CCl2HCClO (see Table 5).</text></s></P><P><s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There is no obvious match between our product spectrum and the reported spectrum of chloral (CCl3CHO).<REF ID="R-66" REFID="cit32"/><REF ID="R-67" REFID="cit33"/></text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In particular the reported position of ν(CO) for chloral vapour (1778 cm−1) or CCl4 solution (1768 cm−1) does not match well with our observed product band at 1804 cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Other strong bands of chloral vapour are seen at 1030, 987, 857 and 739 cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The band at 987 cm−1 matches one of our product bands quite well but the others do not have any obvious counterparts.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It therefore appears that the product of reaction of trichloroethene with OH radicals in an argon matrix is dichloroacetyl chloride, predominantly in the gauche form.</text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We have no detailed mechanistic explanation as to why the gauche form should be favoured but we note that this is the lower-energy form by some 3.5 kJ mol−1.<REF ID="R-68" REFID="cit31"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>DFT calculations were carried out in order to identify the most energetically favourable species with the lowest value of ΔE.</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Table 6 gives the energy (enthalpy) values obtained for reactants and possible products.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Zero point energies were added to all values.</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The energy values for the various possible reaction steps are illustrated by the diagram in Scheme 3.</text></s></P><P><s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These calculations serve to back up the experimental findings in that dichloroacetyl chloride and water are calculated to be the most stable reaction products.</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The overall energy value of this pathway is −303.8 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The first step of the reaction, the formation of a hydroxyalkyl radical, is strongly exothermic.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The energy to overcome this step is provided by photolysis of the reaction mixture.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is calculated that the 1,2,2-trichloro-2-hydroxyethyl radical is favoured over the isomeric 1,1,2-trichloro-2-hydroxyethyl radical.</text></s> <s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is perhaps somewhat surprising in that it might be expected that the radical with the unpaired electron on the CCl2 moiety would be the more stable.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The 1,2,2-trichloro-2-hydroxyethyl radical proceeds to the product dichloroacetyl chloride by H-atom abstraction and migration of a Cl atom.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The alternative 1,1,2-trichloro-2-hydroxyethyl radical would need to undergo H-atom migration to form dichloroacetyl chloride.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As mentioned previously Cl-atom migration is expected to be favoured over H-atom migration.</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The conversion of radical intermediate to carbonyl product is calculated to be strongly exothermic (−428.0 kJ mol−1) in line with the failure to observe the radical intermediates in our experiments.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our experiments have identified the products of reaction of tetrachloroethene and of trichloroethene with hydroxyl radicals as being the carbonyl compounds trichloroacetyl chloride and dicloroacetyl chloride respectively.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is likely that the reactions proceed via addition of an OH radical to the double bond of the alkene in a reaction entirely analogous to that of the simple hydrocarbon alkenes.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This addition reaction forms a hydroxychloroalkyl radical which reacts further by abstraction of the hydroxyl hydrogen atom.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In keeping with the findings from gas phase studies<REF ID="R-69" REFID="cit10"/> chlorine-atom loss from this radical is, at best, a very minor pathway.</text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For trichloroethene, where two carbonyl products are possible, the observed product – dichloroacetyl chloride – has an acyl chlorine atom which gives a mesomeric stabilisation.</text></s> <s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This product is probably formed by Cl-atom rather than H-atom migration.</text></s> <s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is found that this product is formed predominantly in the low-energy gauche form.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our experiments suggest that carbonyl products of the type observed may be important in the atmospheric oxidation of chloroalkenes, just as acetaldehyde is important in ethene oxidation.<REF ID="R-70" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-71" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-72" REFID="cit34"/></text></s> <s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The use of DFT calculations in support of the experimental results from matrix isolation is shown to be important in exploring these reaction mechanisms.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>