<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b310767a" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Probing the stereochemistry of the active site of gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase using sulfur derivatives of l-glutamic acid</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Gamma-glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT) catalyses the transfer of a γ-glutamyl moiety from a donor substrate to different acceptors, such as amino acids and water.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>GGT is known to display relatively low stereospecificity with respect to the α-stereocentre of its donor substrates.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In this study we have studied its stereospecificity with respect to the stereocentre at the δ-position of different analogues of l-glutamic acid.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Notably, l-methionine sulfoxide is well-recognised whereas l-methionine sulfone and l-methionine sulfoximine are not.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, when the synthetic γ-diastereoisomers of l-methionine sulfoxide were separated and tested, it was discovered that GGT shows remarkable stereospecificity at the γ-position, binding the SCSS diastereoisomer with a Ki of 3.5 mM, whereas the SCRS diastereoisomer is not recognised.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, using a sulfoxide as a new pharmacophore for GGT, we have synthesized and tested an analogue of glutathione to obtain a very promising competitive inhibitor with a Ki of (53 ± 3) µM.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>γ-Glutamyl transpeptidase (GGT; E.C.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>2.3.2.2) is a highly glycosylated heterodimeric enzyme found mainly in the kidney, but also in the brain and pancreas.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It catalyses the formation of leukotriene D4, is implicated in the inflammatory response,<REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/> and is involved in cellular detoxification<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/> owing to the critical role that glutathione (γ-glutamylcysteinylglycine), its in vivo substrate, plays in this process.</text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It also plays numerous roles in physiological disorders, namely inhibition of apoptosis,<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/><REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/> Parkinson's disease,<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit6"/> diabetes<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit7"/> and asthma.<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit8"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit9"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, its precise pathological function is not well known, due to lack of information about its mechanism and its structure.</text></s></P><P><s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>GGT catalyses the transfer of the γ-glutamyl moiety of glutathione (donor substrate) to acceptor substrates, usually amino acids or dipeptides, or to a water molecule, forming either a γ-glutamyl–acceptor compound containing an isopeptide bond or glutamate, respectively, through a modified ping-pong mechanism.<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The enzyme binds glutathione and releases cysteinylglycine as its first product to form an acyl–enzyme intermediate in the acylation step.<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit11"/></text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This transient intermediate then binds the acceptor substrate and transfers its acyl moiety to form the second product (γ-glutamyl–acceptor) and regenerate the free enzyme in the deacylation step.</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>α-Amino acids serve as good acceptor substrates, and the resulting transamidation reaction has been suggested to represent the principal physiological function of the enzyme, particularly in the γ-glutamyl cycle.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, a water molecule can also act as an acceptor ‘substrate’, leading to hydrolysis of the acyl–enzyme and formation of glutamate.</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The nature of the amino acids implicated in substrate binding and the catalysis of these transamidation and hydrolysis reactions are not well known.</text></s></P><P><s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The active-site nucleophile has not been identified for all types of GGT.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>E. coli GGT has been inhibited with a fluorophosphonate analogue of glutamic acid and subsequent mass spectrometric sequencing revealed the N-terminal Thr-391 of the light subunit, conserved at that position in all mammalian GGTs, to be covalently modified, leading the authors to classify this enzyme as an N-terminal nucleophile (Ntn) hydrolase.<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit13"/></text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, other work based on site-directed mutagenesis of human GGT has suggested Ser-405 or Ser-406 may be the active site nucleophile.<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the widely studied rat GGT, no nucleophile has been unambiguously identified.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We have previously proposed that the nucleophile (probably a Thr hydroxyl group) attacks the carbonyl group of the γ-glutamyl amide bond to form a tetrahedral intermediate (Scheme 1).</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The rate-limiting step of the acylation process is the decomposition of this intermediate, namely the cleavage of the C–N bond with concomitant protonation of the departing amine, probably by a nearby His residue.<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit14"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The binding site for the donor substrate has been studied in detail, showing that GGT is intolerant of certain modifications of the γ-glutamyl moiety.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, the free ammonium group and the carbonyl at the α-position are necessary for good recognition of the substrate.<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit15"/></text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, donor substrates of either l- or d-configuration are recognised without significant selectivity.<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit10"/></text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The side chain cannot bear any alkyl substituents, except at the α-position.<REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit16"/></text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Upon substitution of a methylene unit by heteroatoms such as oxygen or nitrogen, the resulting compounds no longer act as donor substrates.<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit17"/></text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, due to the lack of a crystal structure suitable for analysis of any type of GGT, it is difficult to specify the precise nature of the amino acids involved in the mechanism or affecting the stereochemistry of the active site near the nucleophile.</text></s></P><P><s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to gain insight into the steric environment near the catalytic nucleophile, active site mapping was carried out with various l-glutamic acid analogues bearing different functionalities at the γ-position on the lateral chain.</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>As shown in Fig. 1, the carbonyl group of the glutamyl moiety was replaced by various functional groups, thereby altering the geometry of the donor substrate near the nucleophile.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Analysis of the relative affinities of these compounds as competitive inhibitors at the donor substrate binding site has permitted an examination of the stereospecificity of the active site and the design and synthesis of a glutathione analogue that is one of the most potent inhibitors of GGT.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>These results are discussed herein.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous studies from our laboratories<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit15"/> and others<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit18"/> have shown that an inhibitor must incorporate certain features to display good affinity for the active site of GGT.</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, it appears that a free α-ammonium group and an α-carbonyl group are essential for recognition.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>A series of compounds were designed to contain these functional groups while varying the geometry of the atom at the δ-position of the corresponding glutamine model compound.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Compounds 1–9, as shown in Fig. 1, were tested for their ability to act as inhibitors of the GGT-mediated transpeptidation reaction between l-γ-glutamic acid p-nitroanilide as the donor substrate and glycylglycine as the acceptor substrate.</text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="None" advantage="Yes"/><text>Glycylglycine was chosen as an acceptor substrate both for its efficiency and its known inability to act as an inhibitor at the donor substrate binding site,<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit19"/> such that our inhibition results are relevant to the compounds tested and not contaminated by background inhibition inherent in the test reaction.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For each compound tested, a Ki (or an IC50) value was determined and is reported in Table 1.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Almost all of the compounds were found to be competitive inhibitors, as was obvious from the Lineweaver–Burk plots of the inhibition data (not shown).</text></s></P><P><s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compound 1, l-glutamic acid, is a reasonable analogue of l-glutamine, which serves as a simple donor substrate for GGT,<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit19"/> and functions as a modest competitive inhibitor (Table 1).</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compound 2, the nitrile of l-glutamine, was shown to be a weaker inhibitor of GGT, perhaps due to its linear geometry at the δ-position, even though inhibitors of this type have been effective for other enzymes such as chymotrypsin.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit20"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Certain compounds have been reported that are excellent inhibitors of GGT, purportedly due to their similarity to the transition state of GGT acylation.<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, a complex of l-serine and borate has been used to inhibit GGT with a Ki of 20 µM.<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The l-glutamic acid boronate analogue (ABBA) has an in vitro Ki of 17 nM and is one of the best competitive inhibitors for GGT, although it also inhibits several other glutamate-dependant enzymes, such as glutamic pyruvic transaminase.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Its efficacy as an inhibitor of cell growth has been demonstrated, although in vivo concentrations of 1 mM are required.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Hoping to capitalise on the general efficiency of transition-state analogues and to improve upon the specificity of known GGT inhibitors, a series of compounds were tested that bear functional groups that resemble the geometric and/or electrostatic character of the transition state of the acylation step of GGT catalytic cycle.</text></s></P><P><s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>5-hydroxy-dl-lysine (3) has also been tested with other enzymes with some success<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit23"/> due to its resemblance to glutamine.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, when we tested 3 with GGT, no inhibition was observed. l-Methionine, thioether 4, has previously been tested as an inhibitor of the donor substrate and found to have low affinity for the enzyme.<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit19"/></text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The absence of the double bonded oxygen may explain the lack of recognition of this compound.</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to test for the necessity of this double bond, we tested the sulfoximine 5, which is known to be a good inhibitor for enzymes recognizing a γ-glutamyl moiety such as glutamine synthetase.<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit25"/></text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, in light of the high IC50 obtained for GGT, compound 5 is not well recognised by GGT.</text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thinking that the NH group could affect its recognition by the enzyme, we prepared and tested sulfone 6.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This compound also proved incapable of inhibiting the enzyme, even though compound 6 has been used as a l-glutamic acid analogue for inhibition of enzymes such as glutamate synthase<REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit24"/> and glutamine synthetase.<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit25"/></text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To probe the effect of replacing the methyl group with a heteroatom, sulfonic acid 7, dl-homocysteic acid, was tested.</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For this compound, weak inhibition was observed (Ki = 11.1 mM) that appeared to be uncompetitive with respect to the donor substrate.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This signifies that while this substitution did not improve affinity for the donor substrate binding site, it apparently led to a modest increase in affinity for a second site on the enzyme.</text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further tests showed that it is not a good competitive inhibitor of glycyclycine, however, so it does not appear to be bound in the acceptor substrate binding site.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In partial summary of these results, from comparison of the inhibition results obtained for compounds 4–7, it would appear that the presence of two double bonds at the δ-position adversely affects the affinity of the compound for the donor substrate binding site, the simple thioether 4 being the best of this subset and a weak inhibitor at that.</text></s></P><P><s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Conversely, when the commercial sulfoxide analogue 8 was tested it was found to act as a surprisingly efficient competitive inhibitor of the donor substrate of the transpeptidation reaction.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Its Ki value was found to be less than half of that of compound 1, l-glutamic acid.</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sulfoxide functionality has interesting geometric and electrostatic properties and has been widely used as l-glutamic acid analogue inhibitors with different enzymes.<REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit26"/><REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit27"/></text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sulfoxide group can be represented as a sulfur atom double bonded with an oxygen, or forming a dative bond with an oxygen, or bearing a partial positive charge bonded to an oxygen atom with a partial negative charge.<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit28"/></text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In all cases, the sulfur atom at the δ-position of compound 8 represents a stereocentre, the fourth corner of the asymmetric tetrahedron occupied by a lone pair of electrons.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the Ki value reported in Table 1, a mixture of the two δ-diastereoisomers of 8 was used.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Stereoselectivity for chiral sulfoxide derivatives has been observed in the inhibition of peptidyl transferase by the antibiotic sparsomycin,<REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit29"/> so we were intrigued to see if GGT would display greater affinity for one diastereomer of 8 compared to the other.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>In order to measure the stereoselectivity of GGT for the δ-position of the molecule, we synthesised and separated the two diastereoisomers according to a literature procedure<REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit30"/><REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit31"/><REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit32"/> as described in the Experimental section.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The diastereomers 8a (SCSS) and 8b (SCRS) were thus obtained, but only 8a was obtained as a relatively pure stereoisomer, having a diastereoisomeric excess (de) of &gt; 95percent, as determined by 13C NMR.<REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit30"/></text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The SCSS molecule gave a Ki value of 3.4 mM, nearly half the value of the diastereoisomeric mixture.</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This suggested the enzyme has a lower affinity for the SCRS diastereomer, compound 8b.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although purification of 8b to a de of 95percent has been reported elsewhere,<REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit31"/> in our hands it was always obtained as a mixture of the two δ-diastereomers.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our highest enrichment gave a mixture of 76percent 8b and 24percent 8a.</text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Since it was impossible for us to obtain diastereoisomer 8b in pure form, we used an indirect kinetic method to determine its Ki.</text></s></P><P><s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Scheme 2 signifies the inhibition of an enzyme by two different competitive inhibitors (I and I′), each having different affinities for the same donor substrate binding site, represented by the inhibition constants (Ki and Ki′).</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>As is shown in detail in the Experimental section, one may derive from this competitive inhibition scheme an equation for the variation of the apparent inhibition constant as a function of the mole fraction of inhibitor, namely .</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This equation provides the basis for the graphical analysis of the inhibition data obtained for a series of mixtures of diastereomers 8a (SCSS) and 8b (SCRS), displaying satisfactory linear correlation (r2 = 0.987) as shown in Fig. 2.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Extrapolation of the data indicated clearly that the value of Ki′ (for 8b) is very high, giving an intercept of around zero in Fig. 2.</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this way, the inhibition constant of diastereomer 8b was determined indirectly, since the compound could not be isolated as a pure diastereomer.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From the slope of Fig. 2 the inhibition constant of 8a was determined to be Ki = 3.4 mM.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This lack of recognition by GGT of the SCRS isomer 8b, in contrast to its relatively high affinity for the SCSS diastereoisomer 8a clearly illustrates the stereospecificity of its interactions with the δ-position of γ-glutamyl analogues.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These interactions may include an electrostatic interaction of some positively charged amino acid residue with the (partially) anionic oxygen of the sulfoxide, and/or a dipole–dipole interaction between the active site nucleophile (possibly a threonine hydroxyl group) and the partially positively charged sulfur, as represented in Fig. 3.</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The stereospecificity of these interactions presents an interesting feature for the design of future high-affinity inhibitors of GGT.</text></s></P><P><s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The affinity displayed for the sulfoxides tested herein suggested to us that the distribution of partial charges in this functional group may also be important for favourable interaction with the donor substrate binding site.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Phosphorus-containing compounds have been used widely as transition-state analogues of enzymatic reactions.<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit33"/></text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, with GGT, a fluorophosphoric acid derivative of glutamic acid has been used as an (irreversible) inhibitor to identify the nucleophile for bacterial GGT.<REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit13"/></text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When we tested the commercially available compound 9, dl-2-amino-4-phosphonobutyric acid, a relatively high Ki of 35.8 mM was determined at pH 8.0.</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This weak affinity for the donor substrate binding site may be due to charges on the side chain phosphonate present at this pH.</text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The pKa of the α-ammonium and α-carboxylate groups do not vary greatly according to the nature of the side chain, such that the compounds tested all exist predominantly as α-ammonium carboxylates around neutrality.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Likewise, one of the two hydroxyl groups bound to the phosphorus atom would have a pKa value around 2.4 and would always be ionised at the pH range of the kinetic analyses.</text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the pKa of the second hydroxyl group varies with the length of the side chain and the nature of adjacent substituents.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compound 9 was therefore titrated to determine that the second pKa value of the phosphonic acid group is 7.022 ± 0.002.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, during the inhibition tests at pH 8.0, both oxygens were negatively charged.</text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>One could hypothesize that the low affinity of compound 9 for the donor substrate binding site may be due to electrostatic repulsion.</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>On repeating the same competitive inhibition experiment at successively lower pHs of 7.0 and 6.0, we found increasingly lower Ki values of 5.91 mM and 0.6 mM, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is noteworthy that the Ki determined for compound 9 at pH 6.0, where the second oxygen would be predominantly protonated, is 60 times lower than at pH 8.0, where the oxygen would be predominantly ionised.</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Of course, these results may also be due to the ionisation of an amino acid residue in or near the substrate binding site of GGT.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We<REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit11"/><REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit14"/> and others<REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit35"/> have shown that GGT-mediated transpeptidation shows a bell-shaped pH-rate profile, with a kinetic pKa on the acidic limb of around 7.8.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although this pKa has been attributed to the α-amino group of the acceptor substrate, it may overlap with an ionisation of a residue on the enzyme itself.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In any case, it is clear that at lower pH the affinity between compound 9 and the donor substrate binding site is dramatically improved.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This suggests that electrostatic interactions at this position of the γ-glutamyl sub-site probably play an important role in inhibitor affinity.</text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This may provide another reason, in addition to its geometry, why sulfoxide 8, bearing one (partial) negative charge, shows relatively better affinity for GGT.</text></s></P><P><s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Methyl sulfoxide 8 is a new type of competitive inhibitor for GGT, but does not contain any recognition element on the sulfoxide moiety.</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The natural substrate of GGT is glutathione and the presence of the Cys–Gly moiety on the other side of the scissile γ-glutamyl bond is also important in the recognition of this donor substrate by the enzyme.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, l-glutamine functions as a donor substrate of GGT, but with a KM value around 10 times greater than that of glutathione.</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to extend the potential binding interactions and consequent inhibitory ability of the parent sulfoxide 8, an analogue of glutathione was designed, namely sulfoxide derivative 16.</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The pendant propionylglycine moiety of 16 was added with the notion that it could be bound in the sub-site usually occupied by the cysteinylglycine moiety of glutathione.</text></s></P><P><s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The general procedure used to synthesize compound 16 was based on a published protocol<REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit36"/> and is shown in Scheme 3.</text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Initially, the α-carboxylate group of l-homocystine was protected as a methyl ester (10).</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Ester 10 was then efficiently converted to the Boc-protected compound 11.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This derivative was reduced by tri-n-butylphosphine in the presence of CH2Cl2 saturated with water to obtain 12.</text></s> <s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The key step of this synthesis is the subsequent condensation of l-homocysteine derivative 12 with bromide 17.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This bromomethylene analogue of glycylglycine was synthesized in one step through the simple condensation of glycine tert-butyl ester with 3-bromopropionyl chloride (Scheme 4).</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Bromide 17 and thiol 12 were then condensed to provide a sulfide 13 which was oxidized directly with NaIO4 to give sulfoxide 14 in good yield.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The remaining steps represent the straightforward deprotection of the molecule.</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The cleavage of the α-methyl ester group was carried out successfully with NaOH to give 15 and the Boc group and tert-butyl ester were finally removed with TFA to give compound 16 in good yield.</text></s></P><P><s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compound 16 was then tested in the same way as the other compounds shown in Table 1.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It gave a surprisingly low Ki value of (53 ± 3) µM, well below all the other inhibitors tested in this work, and 100-fold lower than the other sulfoxide, compound 8.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Obviously, the presence of some recognition element N-terminal to the analogous γ-glutamyl group contributed greatly to the overall binding affinity of this compound, giving an inhibitor that compares well with other known GGT inhibitors.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is important to note that the Ki value for 16 was measured on a 50 : 50 mixture of the two S-diastereoisomers, since we were unable to separate them by the same techniques used for compound 8.</text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although one may speculate that the stereospecificity that GGT manifested for compound 8 would suggest that the SS diastereomer of 16 would give a Ki value even lower than 53 µM, we were unable to test this hypothesis.</text></s></P><P><s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Other analogues of glutathione have been synthesized containing heteroatoms in the γ-position on the lateral chain of the γ-glutamyl moiety,<REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit37"/><REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit38"/> or modifications on the sulfur of the cysteinyl moiety.</text></s> <s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These compounds are good inhibitors, probably due to their affinity for the binding site of the cysteinyl moiety.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The synthesis of a γ-sulfonamide analogue of glutathione has been reported, but no kinetic data is available yet to indicate if this (possibly irreversible) inhibitor shows good affinity for GGT.<REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit39"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In conclusion, we have shown that γ-glutamyl derivatives containing a sulfoxide moiety at the δ-position are a promising new class of GGT inhibitors.</text></s> <s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>GGT displays stereospecific affinity for one diastereoisomer (SCSS) of methionine sulfoxide, as determined by an indirect kinetic analysis method that should prove useful for the analysis of other known mixtures of competitive inhibitors.</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We have also synthesized a sulfoxide analogue of glutathione which is a potent inhibitor of GGT and demonstrates the importance of interactions with the putative cysteinylglycine sub-site of the glutathione binding site to the overall affinity with the inhibitor.</text></s> <s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Studies are currently in progress in our laboratory to design and prepare better glutathione analogue inhibitors and to glean more structural information regarding the active site of GGT.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Material</HEADER><P><s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All compounds (except 2) were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich and were used without further purification.</text></s> <s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compound 2 is a generous gift from Dr B. Badet<REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit40"/> (CRNS, Gif–sur–Yvette, France).</text></s> <s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compounds 8a and 8b were synthesized as described below.</text></s> <s sid="132"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The buffers MES, MOPS and Tris and glycylglycine were purchased at Sigma.</text></s> <s sid="133"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The donor substrate l-γ-glutamic acid p-nitroanilide was synthesized as described previously.<REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit41"/></text></s> <s sid="134"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rat kidney GGT was purified as previously described in an established protocol.<REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit14"/></text></s> <s sid="135"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the kinetic studies, absorbance values at 410 nm were recorded on a Cary 100 Bio spectrophotometer or on a Pharmacia Biotech Ultrospec 2000 spectrophotometer.</text></s> <s sid="136"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The pKa of compound 9 was determined by using a Mettler Toledo DL53 Titrator.</text></s></P><P><s sid="137"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All chemical products used in synthesis were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich.</text></s> <s sid="138"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>1H and 13C spectra were recorded on Brukers AMX300 or ARX300 (300 MHz) or Brukers AMX400 or ARX400 (400 MHz).</text></s> <s sid="139"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All solvents were dried using a drying column on a GlassContour system (Irvine, CA).</text></s> <s sid="140"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Low- and high-resolution mass spectra were obtained from the Regional Centre of Mass Spectrometry at the Université de Montréal.</text></s> <s sid="141"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Melting points were determined with a capillary tube with an Uni-melt Thomas-Hoover melting point apparatus and are reported as corrected values.</text></s> <s sid="142"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>IR spectra were recorded on a FT-IR Paragon 1000 spectrophotometer (Perkin Elmer).</text></s> <s sid="143"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Specific optical rotations were measured at 20 °C in units of 10−1 deg cm2 g−1.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Synthesis</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Synthesis of sulfoxides 8a and 8b</HEADER><P><s sid="144"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Sulfoxides 8a and 8b were prepared according to a previously described procedure,<REF ID="R-53" REFID="cit30"/><REF ID="R-54" REFID="cit31"/> with some slight modifications.</text></s> <s sid="145"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The hydrogen peroxide oxidation of N-phthaloyl l-methionine was done at room temperature over 2 days and not at −20 °C.</text></s> <s sid="146"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The SCRS and SCSS stereoisomers were initially isolated as a 50 : 50 mixture, as determined by comparison of the S–CH3 and the Cα peaks of the 13C NMR.<REF ID="R-55" REFID="cit31"/></text></s> <s sid="147"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The SCSS diastereoisomer was crystallised in MeOH several times to obtain a purity &gt; 95percent by 1H NMR.</text></s> <s sid="148"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Different attempts to obtain the other diastereoisomer SCRS were unsuccessful.</text></s> <s sid="149"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In our hands, separation by simple chromatography (gradient 100percent AcOEt to 20percent MeOH in AcOEt) gave a maximum ratio of 76 : 24 (SCRS : SCSS).</text></s> <s sid="150"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To obtain mixtures containing different proportions of both diastereoisomers, we varied the number of subsequent recrystallisations in MeOH and determined the diastereomeric ratio of the recrystallised product by NMR 13C according to the published procedure.<REF ID="R-56" REFID="cit30"/></text></s> In this way we generated and tested diastereomeric mixtures of which the mole fraction of diastereomer 8a, f was 0.24, 0.31, 0.5, 0.65, and 1.0.</P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>l-Homocystine methyl ester hydrochloride (10)</HEADER><P>To a solution of l-homocystine (2.262 mmol, 0.607 g) in methanol (15 mL) at 0 °C, was added thionyl chloride (13.6 mmol, 0.988 mL). <s sid="151"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solution was kept overnight at room temperature and then removed under reduced pressure.</text></s> <s sid="152"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To remove the traces of SOCl2, the resulting oil was diluted in CHCl3 and concentrated again to give a hygroscopic gummy solid (0.833 g, 100percent).</text></s> <s sid="153"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This compound 10 was used without further purification.</text></s> <s sid="154"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>[α]D +52.6 (c 0.63, MeOH); IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3410, 2956, 1746, 1620, 1516, 1442, 1234; 1H NMR (MeOD, 400 MHz) 2.32 (2H, m), 2.85 (2H, m), 3.82 (3H, s), 4.18 (1H, t, J = 5.4 Hz); 13C NMR (MeOD, 100 MHz) 30.6, 33.4, 52.4, 53.7, 170.2.</text></s> <s sid="155"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>HRMS (MAB, M+) 296.0876.</text></s> C10H20N2O4S2 calculated 296.0865.</P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>tert-Butoxycarbonyl l-homocystine methyl ester (11)</HEADER><P>To a solution of 10 (0.815 mmol, 0.300 g) in MeOH (10 mL) at 0 °C, was added Boc2O (2.445 mmol, 0.534 g) and triethylamine (3.261 mmol, 0.454 mL). <s sid="156"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solution was stirred overnight at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="157"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The MeOH was removed under reduced pressure and the residue was diluted in CHCl3 and washed with aqueous HCl (0.1 M).</text></s> <s sid="158"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The organic layer was dried over MgSO4 and removed under reduced pressure, giving a white solid which was purified by flash chromatography (30percent EtOAc in hexane) (0.396 g, 98percent).</text></s> <s sid="159"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rf 0.5 (50percent EtOAc in hexane).</text></s> <s sid="160"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>[α]D +30.4 (c 0.53, CHCl3); IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3363, 2978, 1714, 1515, 1439, 1367, 1250, 1219, 1165, 1051, 1025; 1H NMR (CDCl3, 300 MHz) 1.38 (18H, s), 1.95 (2H, m), 2.25 (2H, m), 2.66 (4H, t, J = 7.4 Hz), 3.74 (6H, s), 4.34 (2H, m), 5.22 (2H, m); 13C NMR (CDCl3, 75 MHz) 28.4, 32.6, 34.6, 52.6, 80.2, 155.5, 172.8; HRMS (MAB, M+) 496.1910.</text></s> C20H36N2O8S2 calculated 496.1913.</P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>tert-Butoxy-l-homocysteine methyl ester (12)</HEADER><P>To a solution of 11 (0.786 mmol, 0.390 g) in wet CH2Cl2 (6 mL), was slowly added tri-(n-butyl)phosphine (0.786 mmol, 0.197 mL) under a nitrogen atmosphere. <s sid="161"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mixture was stirred for 30 minutes and the solvent removed under reduced pressure.</text></s> <s sid="162"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The residue was purified by flash chromatography (75percent hexane in EtOAc) to give 12 (0.392 g, 100percent) as an oil.</text></s> <s sid="163"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rf 0.5 (33percent EtOAc in hexane).</text></s> <s sid="164"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>[α]D +13 (c 0.60, CHCl3); IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3352, 2978, 2580, 1710, 1513, 1436, 1366, 1164, 1050; (CDCl3, 300 MHz) 1.42 (9H, s), 1.56 (1H, t, J = 8.1 Hz), 1.87–2.09 (2H, m), 2.55 (2H, m), 3.73 (3H, s), 4.43 (1H, m), 5.09 (1H, m); 13C NMR (CDCl3, 75 MHz) 20.8, 28.4, 37.3, 52.3, 52.6, 80.2, 155.5, 172.9; HRMS (MAB, M+) 249.1035.</text></s> <s sid="165"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>C10H19NO4S calculated 249.1035.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>2-tert-Butoxycarbonylamino-4-[2-(tert-butoxycarbonylmethylcarbamoyl)ethylsulfanyl]-butyric acid methyl ester (13)</HEADER><P><s sid="166"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To a solution of 12 (1.570 mmol, 0.390 g) in DMF (7 mL) at 0 °C, was added 17 (1.883 mmol, 0.5 g) and then K2CO3 (1.727 mmol, 0.239 g) under a nitrogen atmosphere.</text></s> <s sid="167"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solution was warmed to room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="168"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After stirring overnight, the solution was diluted with water and the desired product was extracted 5 times with EtOAc.</text></s> <s sid="169"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The organic layer was concentrated under reduced pressure and the residue was purified by flash chromatography (35percent EtOAc in hexane) to obtain a colourless oil (0.489 g, 72percent).</text></s> <s sid="170"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rf 0.27 (35percent EtOAc in hexane).</text></s> <s sid="171"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>[α]D +6.6 (c 0.43, CHCl3); IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3330, 2979, 1744, 1708, 1663, 1529, 1439, 1368, 1225, 1161; 1H NMR (CDCl3, 300 MHz) 1.42 (9H, s), 1.45 (9H, s), 1.87–2.09 (2H, m), 2.50 (4H, m), 2.75 (2H, t, J = 7.1 Hz), 3.72 (3H, s), 3.93 (2H, d, J = 5.1 Hz), 4.38 (1H, m), 5.28 (1H, d, J = 8.1 Hz), 6.55 (1H, t, J = 4.7 Hz); 13C NMR (CDCl3, 75 MHz); 27.4, 28.1, 28.4, 32.5, 36.5, 42.1, 52.5, 52.7, 80.1, 82.4, 155.5, 169.1, 171.2, 172.8; HRMS (FAB, MH+) 435.2161.</text></s> <s sid="172"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>C19H35N2O7S calculated 435.2165.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>2-tert-Butoxycarbonylamino-4-[2-(tert-butoxycarbonylmethylcarbamoyl)ethylsulfinyl]-butyric acid methyl ester (14)</HEADER><P><s sid="173"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To a solution of 13 (0.375 mmol, 0.163 g) in THF : H2O (7 : 2) (6 mL) at 0 °C, was added 2 mL H2O containing 0.073 g of NaIO4 (0.342 mmol).</text></s> <s sid="174"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After 1 day of reaction, the THF was evaporated under reduced pressure.</text></s> <s sid="175"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The remaining aqueous solution was diluted with water and the desired product was extracted with CHCl3 (3 × 10 mL).</text></s> <s sid="176"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The organic layer was dried over MgSO4 and the resulting oil was purified by flash chromatography (gradient 100percent EtOAc to 80percent EtOAc in MeOH) to give the desired product as an oil (0.154 g, 91percent); Rf 0.2 (100percent EtOAc); [α]D +12.7 (c 0.29, CHCl3); IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3294, 2979, 2928, 1741, 1716, 1656, 1530, 1448, 1368, 1226, 1159, 1021; 1H NMR (CDCl3, 300 MHz) 1.40 (9H, s), 1.42 (9H, s), 2.01–2.37 (2H, m), 2.75 (4H, m), 2.84–3.12 (2H, m), 3.71 (3H, s), 3.88 (2H, dd, J = 5.1 Hz, J = 2.3 Hz), 4.36 (1H, m), 5.58 (1H, m), 7.00 (1H, m); 13C NMR (CDCl3, 75 MHz) 26.0 (d, 50 : 50 mixture of diastereoisomers), 28.1, 28.3, 28.5, 42.2, 47.0 (d), 48.4 (d), 52.6, 52.7, 80.2, 82.2, 155.6, 169.0, 170.3, 172.2.</text></s> <s sid="177"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>HRMS (FAB, MH+) 451.2127.</text></s> <s sid="178"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>C19H35N2O8 calculated 451.2114.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>2-tert-Butoxycarbonylamino-4-[2-(tert-butoxycarbonylmethylcarbamoyl)ethylsulfinyl]-butyric acid (15)</HEADER><P><s sid="179"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A solution of 14 (0.361 mmol, 0.163 g) with NaOH (0.543 mmol, 0.022 g) in THF–H2O (7 : 2) (5 mL) at 0 °C was stirred for 2 h.</text></s> <s sid="180"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reaction was concentrated under reduced pressure, diluted in CHCl3 and extracted with H2O.</text></s> <s sid="181"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The aqueous layer was acidified to pH 2–3 and EtOAc (3 × 20 mL) was added to extract compound 15.</text></s> <s sid="182"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The organic layer was dried with MgSO4 and concentrated to obtain an oil (0.112 g, 71percent).</text></s> <s sid="183"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rf 0.13 (75percent EtOAc in MeOH); [α]D +21.0 (c 0.56, CHCl3); IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3320, 2979, 2930, 1710 (br), 1531, 1368, 1230, 1160, 1023; 1H NMR (CDCl3, 400 MHz) 1.42 (9H, s), 1.44 (9H, s), 2.26 (m, 2H), 2.78–2.90 (4H, m), 3.00–3.18 (2H, m),3.92 (2H, br s ), 4.38 (1H, m), 5.80 (1H, dd, J = 6.4 Hz, J = 30 Hz), 7.19 (1H, m); 13C NMR (CDCl3, 100 MHz) 25.9 (d, 50 : 50 mixture of diastereoisomers), 28.2, 28.5, 30.4, 42.3 (d), 47.2, 52.5, 77.2, 80.3, 82.5, 155.9, 169.2 (d), 170.8, 174.5 (d).</text></s> <s sid="184"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>HRMS (FAB, MH+) 437.1953.</text></s> <s sid="185"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>C18H33N2O8S calculated 437.1958.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>2-Amino-4-[2-(carboxymethylcarbamoyl)ethylsulfinyl]-butyric acid (16)</HEADER><P><s sid="186"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To a solution of 15 (0.248 mmol, 0.108 g) in CH2Cl2 (5 mL) at 0 °C, was added anisole (0.248 mmol, 0.027 mL) and TFA (7.428 mmol, 0.572 mL).</text></s> <s sid="187"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solution was stirred overnight at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="188"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A supplementary volume of 0.191 mL (2.476 mmol) of TFA was added and the mixture was stirred again for 5 h.</text></s> <s sid="189"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solvent was removed under reduced pressure.</text></s> <s sid="190"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Cyclohexane was added to the residue and the solution was concentrated under reduced pressure 3 times.</text></s> <s sid="191"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The resulting oil was dissolved in CHCl3 and the desired product was extracted with aqueous HCl (0.1 M).</text></s> <s sid="192"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The aqueous layer was concentrated under reduced pressure to obtain a pale yellow very hygroscopic gum (0.074 g, 95percent).</text></s> <s sid="193"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>[α]D +13.1 (c 0.300, MeOH); IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3372, 2933, 1735, 1654, 1550, 1414, 1230, 1002; 1H NMR (D2O, 300 MHz) 2.32 (2H, m), 2.73 (2H, t, J = 7.2 Hz), 2.80–3.22 (4H, m), 3.90 (2H, s), 4.07 (1H, td, J = 3.0 Hz, J = 6.6 Hz); 13C NMR (D2O, 75 MHz); 23.6 (d, 50 : 50 mixture of diastereoisomers), 28.3, 41.4, 46.5 (d), 46.6 (d), 51.8 (d), 171.0, 173.6; HRMS (FAB, MH+) 281.0817.</text></s> <s sid="194"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>C9H17N2O6S calculated 281.0807.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>(3-Bromopropionylamino)acetic acid tert-butyl ester (17)</HEADER><P><s sid="195"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To a solution of glycine tert-butyl ester hydrochloride (0.978 g, 5.833 mmol) and Et3N (1.626 mL, 1.167 mmol) in CH2Cl2 (10 mL) at 0 °C, was added a solution of 3-bromo-propionyl chloride (0.588 mL, 5.833 mmol) in CH2Cl2 (5 mL) under a nitrogen atmosphere.</text></s> <s sid="196"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mixture was allowed to stir overnight.</text></s> <s sid="197"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The residue was purified by flash chromatography (20percent EtOAc in hexane) to give 17 (1.026 g, 66percent) as a white solid.</text></s> <s sid="198"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rf 0.20 (35percent EtOAc in hexane). mp 104–106 °C; IR (NaCl, cm−1) 3288, 3091, 2977, 1741, 1651, 1567, 1413, 1367, 1227, 1154, 1H NMR (CDCl3, 400 MHz) 1.43 (9H, s), 2.81 (2H, t, J = 6.7 Hz), 3.60 (2H, t, J = 6.7 Hz), 3.92 (2H, d, J = 5.0 Hz), 6.49 (1H, br s); 13C NMR (CDCl3, 100 MHz) 27.2, 28.1, 39.3, 42.2, 82.5, 169.1, 170.0; HRMS (MAB, MH+) 266.0404.</text></s> C9H17NO3Br calculated 266.0392.</P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>pKa determination</HEADER><P>A solution of 9 (final concentration 1.5 mM) in 55 mM KCl plus 4 mM HCl was titrated with a solution of 0.1 M NaOH from pH 2.0 to pH 12.0 in triplicate. <s sid="199"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The pKa was calculated using an internal routine.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Enzyme inhibition studies</HEADER><P><s sid="200"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Stock solutions for each compound tested were prepared as follows: l-γ-glutamic acid p-nitroanilide (5 mM), glycylglycine (0.1 M), l-glutamine nitrile 2 (50 mM), 5-hydroxy-dl-lysine 3 (200 mM), l-methionine sulfoximine 5 (200 mM), l-methionine sulfone 6 (200 mM), dl-homocysteic acid 7 (200 mM), l-methionine sulfoxide 8 (200 mM), dl-2-amino-4-phosphonobutyric acid 9 (200 mM), and sulfone 16 (10 mM) were all prepared in 0.1 M Tris-HCl at pH 8.0.</text></s> <s sid="201"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp37" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Compound 9 was also prepared in 0.1 M MOPS at pH 7.0 and in 0.1 M MES at pH 6.0.</text></s></P><P><s sid="202"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp38" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Calibration curves for the extinction coefficient of p-nitroaniline were constructed at pH 6.0 and pH 7.0; the exctinction coefficient at pH 8.0 was previously determined<REF ID="R-57" REFID="cit14"/> to be 8800 M−1 cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="203"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp39" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A stock solution of 5 mM p-nitroaniline was made in 0.1 M MES pH 6.0 buffer.</text></s> <s sid="204"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Concentrations in the range 0–100 µM were used and their absorbance at 410 nm was measured to make a standard absorbance vs. concentration curve in duplicate, giving 8440 M−1 cm−1 as the molar extinction coefficient.</text></s> <s sid="205"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When the same experiment was done at pH 7.0 with 0.1 M MOPS buffer, an extinction coefficient of 8110 M−1 cm−1 was obtained.</text></s></P><P><s sid="206"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp40" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All inhibition kinetic experiments were performed using a reaction mixture consisting of l-γ-glutamic acid p-nitroanilide (67.2 µM to 1400 µM), glycylglycine (20 mM) and fixed concentrations of inhibitors (0 mM to 20 mM, except for compound 16, 0 mM to 1 mM) and completed to 1 mL by 0.1 M Tris–HCl pH 8.0.</text></s> <s sid="207"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp41" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Reactions were initiated by the addition of approximately 7.8 mU of GGT.</text></s> <s sid="208"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp42" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After 15 min, the slope of the graph of absorbance versus time was measured and converted to velocity by dividing by the extinction coefficient (ε = 8800 M−1 cm−1<REF ID="R-58" REFID="cit10"/> at pH 8.0, 8110 M−1 cm−1 at pH 7.0 and 8440 M−1 cm−1 at pH 6.0 (vide supra)).</text></s> <s sid="209"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp43" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A Lineweaver–Burk plot was prepared for each inhibitor concentration, using a broad range of substrate concentrations (0.1 × KM – 2 × KM) judiciously chosen so as to be evenly distributed over the reciprocal x-axis.</text></s> <s sid="210"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp44" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The linear slopes (KM app/Vmax) of these plots, determined using the curve-fitting software Axum 5.0, were re-plotted against the inhibitor concentration to obtain Ki as the intercept on the abscissa of these secondary plots.</text></s> <s sid="211"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All plots displayed excellent linearity (r2 &gt; 0.99).</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Kinetic analysis of diastereomeric mixture</HEADER><P><s sid="212"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Eqn. (1) represents a typical double reciprocal equation (cf. Lineweaver–Burk plot) of an enzyme-catalysed reaction in the presence of a competitive inhibitor, where v is the reaction rate, KM is the Michaelis constant of the donor substrate, [S] is the concentration of the substrate, Vmax is the maximal rate of the enzymatic reaction, [I] is the concentration of the competitive inhibitor and Ki is the inhibition constant.</text></s> <s sid="213"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The observed apparent Michaelis constant KM app varies according to the inhibitor concentration and the inhibition constant as shown in eqn. (2). </text></s></P><P><s sid="214"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When a second competitive inhibitor is added to the inhibition scheme as shown in Scheme 2, the double reciprocal equation can be shown to include an additional term, as indicated in eqn. (3), after application of the steady state approximation (k1[E][S] = (k−1 + k2)[E·S]) and the mass balance equation ([E]0 = [E] + [E·S] + [E·I] + [E·I′]) and defining and : </text></s></P><P><s sid="215"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In eqn. (3), Ki and Ki′ represent the inhibition constants for inhibitor I (compound 8a (SCSS) in this case) and I′ (compound 8b (SCRS) in this case), respectively.</text></s> <s sid="216"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>With this model, we can modify eqn. (2) to give eqn. (4). </text></s></P><P><s sid="217"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From eqn. (4) we note that the combined effect of both competitive inhibitors to increase KM app can be roughly defined as a function of total inhibitor concentration [I]tot as follows: where Ki app is the apparent inhibition constant.</text></s> <s sid="218"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The fraction of the total inhibitor concentration corresponding to one diastereoisomer 8a can be written as follows: and eqn. (6) can be used to re-write eqn. (5) in the following linear equation: </text></s></P><P><s sid="219"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>From eqn. (7) it can be seen that a plot of the reciprocal of the (observed) apparent competitive inhibition constant as a function of the fraction of 8a in the mixture of diastereomer inhibitors will give a slope of and an intercept of , allowing the apparent inhibition constants for both diastereomers to be determined.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>