<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b311656e" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Gas phase ion chemistry of charged silver(i) adenine ions via multistage mass spectrometry experiments and DFT calculations</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Electrospray ionization (ESI) of solutions containing adenine and AgNO3 yields polymeric [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+ species.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Density functional theory (DFT) calculations have been used to examine potential structures for several of the smaller ions while multistage mass spectrometry experiments have been used to probe their unimolecular reactivity (via collision-induced dissociation (CID)) and bimolecular reactivity (via ion–molecule reactions with the neutral reagents acetonitrile, methanol, butylamine and pyridine).</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>DFT calculations of neutral adenine tautomers and their silver ion adducts provide insights into the binding modes of adenine.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We find that the most stable [Ad + Ag]+ ion does not correspond to the most stable neutral adenine tautomer, consistent with previous studies that have shown that transition metal ions can stabilize rare tautomeric forms of nucleobases.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Both the charge and the stoichiometry of the [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+ complexes play pivotal roles in directing the types of fragmentation and ion–molecule reactions observed.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ is observed to dissociate to [Ad + Ag]+ and to react with butylamine via proton transfer, while [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ fragments via loss of neutral adenine to form the [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ ion and does not undergo proton transfer to butylamine.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>DFT calculations on several isomeric [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ions suggest that planar centrosymmetric cations, in which two adjacent silver atoms are bridged by two N7H adenine tautomers via N(3),N(9)-bidentate interactions, are the most stable.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The [Ad + Ag2 −H]+ ion adds two neutral reagents in ion–molecule reactions, consistent with the presence of two vacant coordination sites.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It undergoes a silver atom loss to form the [Ad + Ag − H]+. radical cation, which in turn fragments quite differently to the even electron [Ad + Ag]+ ion.</text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Several other pairs of radical cation/even electron adenine–silver complexes were also found to undergo different fragmentation reactions.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The gas phase chemistry of copper and silver complexes is enjoying a renaissance largely due to the advent of electrospray ionization mass spectrometry (ESI-MS) as well as advances in computational chemistry which allow these species to be examined by density functional theory (DFT) calculations.</text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Examples include the use of ligand exchange reactions to determine thermochemical binding energies and the gas phase “synthesis” of exotic species such as the simple organometallic ion Ag(CH3)2− and the Fischer carbene complexes XC(COCH3)2+ (where X = Cu or Ag) via collision induced dissociation (CID) of suitable precursors.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The gas phase bioinorganic chemistry of copper and silver has also been the subject of numerous studies ranging from the fragmentation chemistry of complexes of amino acids and peptides through to the use of ESI-MS to examine the formation of polymeric species.</text></s></P><P><s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>One of the interesting aspects of the gas phase bioinorganic chemistry of copper and silver is that CID of their complexes with biological molecules, M, can proceed via redox processes to form radical cations (M+˙).</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This provides an opportunity to compare the gas phase chemistry of odd electron biomolecules with their even electron (EE) counterparts under similar experimental conditions.</text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unfortunately such comparisons are rare, being limited to: (i) the decomposition of odd- and even-electron anions derived from deoxy-polyadenylates; and (ii) the fragmentation of [M + H]+ and M+˙ ions of simple peptides including the isomeric tripeptides Gly–Leu–Arg and Gly–IIe–Arg.</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The later study illustrates the potential analytical value of probing the gas phase fragmentation reactions of M+˙ ions, since these ions allowed distinction between isomeric leucine and isoleucine residue, which was not possible for their protonated counterparts.</text></s></P><P><s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In a recent study, we showed that solutions of silver(i) and the nucleobase adenine A (note the numbering scheme for the various ring positions as well as the favoured sites of metallation as indicated by arrows) resulted in the formation of polymeric silver adenine clusters of the type [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We proposed that these complexes were built up from structures of the type B. Our premise was based on a number of observations coupled with the known condensed phase structure C, consisting of planar centrosymmetric [(adeninium)2Ag2]4+ cations, in which two adjacent silver atoms are bridged by two N(3),N(9)-bidentate adeninium cations, N(1) is protonated and the acidic proton originally attached to N(9) is displaced to N(7).</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In conjunction with CID, ion–molecule reactions were used to provide further evidence for our “dimeric” cluster model by “titrating” the number of vacant coordination sites around the silver cation(s).</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We also noted that some of the [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+ complexes fragmented via loss of a silver atom to yield radical cations.</text></s></P><P><s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In this study, we use a combination of multistage mass spectrometry experiments in a quadrupole ion trap and DFT calculations to: (i) examine the structures and stabilities some of the smaller [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+ ions and (ii) compare the gas-phase reactivity of the novel radical cations formed via loss of a silver atom with their even-electron counterparts.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Mass spectrometry</HEADER><P><s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All experiments were performed using a commercially available quadrupole ion trap mass spectrometer (Finnigan-MAT model LCQ, San Jose, CA) equipped with electrospray ionization (ESI) and recently modified to allow the introduction of neutral reagents via the helium background gas inlet line.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Kinetic and thermodynamic studies by Gronert and Flores have demonstrated that ions within the LCQ ion trap are essentially at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All compounds and reagents used were commercially available and used without further purification.</text></s></P><P><s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A 1 ∶ 2 mixture of adenine and AgNO3 was dissolved in a 50 ∶ 50 mixture of H2O and CH3OH (1percent acetic acid) to a final concentration of 0.1 mg mL−1 and was introduced into the mass spectrometer via electrospray ionization.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Typical ESI conditions used were: syringe pump flowrate of 3.0 µL min−1; spray voltage of 4.5–5.5 kV; capillary temperature of 200 °C; nitrogen sheath pressure of 30 psi and capillary and tube lens offset voltage in the range of 0–10 V.</text></s></P><P><s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The two major isotope ions from the Ag isotopic clusters were mass selected (with a 5 Thomson (Th) window) and subjected to CID to investigate their fragmentation reactions.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Typically CID conditions were: activation amplitude, 0.35–0.60 V; activation (Q), 0.25 V, and activation time 100 ms.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Independent experiments showed that background ion–molecule reactions resulted in the addition of water and methanol to various precursor and product ions.</text></s></P><P><s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Other ion–molecule reactions were carried out by mass selecting the ions of interest and allowing them to react for a fixed period of time with the neutral reagent (methanol, acetonitrile, butylamine and pyridine) introduced into the trap as a part of the helium background gas flow.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A constant flow of the reagent (5–15 µL h−1) was established using a syringe pump with the syringe needle being directed into a measured flow of helium (850–2050 mL min−1).</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The majority of the gas exits through a flowmeter, whereas a small amount (∼1 mL min−1) is drawn into the trap.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The LCQ uses a constriction capillary to control the helium flow and is designed to maintain 0.2 Pa in the trap when 20.7 kPa of He pressure is applied to the capillary.</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the stock system, the 20.7 kPa is maintained by an internal regulator that steps down the 275.8 kPa of He that is delivered at the external port.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To avoid the dead volume in the internal regulator, we bypass it and deliver the He mixture (20.7 kPa) directly to the capillary.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This greatly decreases the lag time after changes in reagent concentration.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Density functional theory and ab initio calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Structures of ions and neutrals were optimised using density functional theory at the B3LYP level using the Gaussian 98 suite of programs.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We employed the 6-31G(d) basis set for H, C and N, and the LANL2DZ effective core potential (ECP) set of Hay and Wadt for Ag, using the Gaussian 98 package.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to find a combination of theory and basis set which would allow us to economically model the geometry and binding energy of a silver(i) ion complexed to nitrogen, we studied the Ag+–NH3 complex at various levels of theory to check for consistency of the Ag–N bond length in each of the optimised structures and the accuracy of the total binding energy (results are given in Table S1 of the electronic supplementary information).</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Binding energies were calculated by scaling the zero point energies (ZPEs) using the scaling factors recommended by Scott and Radom (e.g. 0.9806 for ZPEs calculated at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level of theory).</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We note that the same system has been theoretically modelled earlier and also during the course of our studies.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Hartree–Fock, HF/6-31G(d) level of theory performs poorly, giving a longer and weaker Ag–N bond.</text></s></P><P><s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The B3LYP/6-31G(d) method results in an Ag–N bond length which is within 0.02 Å of the length calculated using the most expensive method (MP2/Aug-cc-pVDZ), while a single-point MP2/6-31G(d) energy calculation on the B3LYP/6-31G(d) optimised geometry is much less expensive than an MP2/6-31G(d) geometry optimisation, but yields a dissociation energy of 169.0 kJ mol−1 that is in excellent agreement of the most recent experimentally measured dissociation energy of 169.9 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This combination of MP2/6-31G(d) single-point energy with B3LYP/6-31G(d) geometry optimisation is denoted MP2/6-31G(d)//B3LYP/6-31G(d) in the standard notation and this method was used in calculations involving all other species described in this work.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The most stable geometries for the molecular species were found by evaluating the MP2 energies of all reasonable structures, with particular reference to geometrical isomers generated by the rearrangement of hydrogen atoms (tautomers) and of silver atoms (‘argentomers’).</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>To verify that the structure obtained was indeed at a local energy minimum, the FREQ keyword was used after the B3LYP geometry optimisation to compute the force constants and the resulting vibrational frequencies for the fully optimised geometry.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In all cases, the structure had no large imaginary frequencies that would indicate a transition state rather than a mininum.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All of the results (structures and energies) from the DFT calculations are available as electronic supplementary information.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In an earlier study, we suggested that polymeric adenine–silver species conformed to a “dimer-cluster” model [cf. structure B] based upon: (i) maps of their stoichiometry (i.e. the number of adenine vs. silver units); (ii) their dissociation pathways; and (iii) ion–molecule reactions (which titrated the number of vacant coordination sites around the silver cation).</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Following on from this work, we have used electrospray ionization coupled to a quadrupole ion trap mass spectrometer and DFT calculations to examine the gas-phase chemistry of the smaller isomeric [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+ ions (where x and y = 1, 2; and z = 0, 1).</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The results of these studies are discussed in the following sections: (A) DFT calculations of the tautomeric forms of adenine and previous studies on cation binding to adenine; (B) DFT calculations of the interaction of various tautomers of adenine with silver(i); (C) gas-phase chemistry of the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ and [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ions; (D) ion–molecule reactions, CID and DFT calculations of the fragmentation reactions of the [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ ion; (E) comparison of CID, ion–molecule reactions and DFT structures of the [Ad + Ag]+ and [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ ions; (F) synthesis and chemistry of other novel silver–adenine ions formed via CID reactions.</text></s></P><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(A)">DFT calculations of the tautomeric forms of adenine and previous studies on cation binding to adenine</HEADER><P><s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In attempting to rationalize the formation and structure of the adenine–silver complexes, it is worth reviewing the stability of each of the tautomeric forms of neutral adenine and how they bind to simple cations.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Numerous experimental and theoretical studies have examined the influence of the reaction medium on the tautomeric forms of nucleobases and some of this work has been recently reviewed.</text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the condensed phase, the amine forms of adenine A and D dominate (Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the gas phase, photoelectron spectroscopy, microwave spectroscopy, IR spectroscopy, and double resonance spectroscopy all point to the N(9)H tautomer A as being the predominant species present.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Matrix isolation experiments also reveal that the N(9)H tautomer A predominates.</text></s></P><P><s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to evaluate Ag+ binding to a range of tautomers, we first calculated all 12 possible tautomeric forms (i.e. 4 amine, 4 cis-imine and 4 trans-imine) of adenine at the MP2/6-31G(d)//B3LYP/6-31G(d) level of theory (Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The lowest-energy adenine tautomer at this level of theory was the N(9)H amine form (refer to Fig. 1 and the electronic supplementary information for optimised structures (Fig. S2) and their energies (Table S2)).</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The results of this study correlate well with previous theoretical work on adenine tautomers.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Literature calculations on the tautomeric forms of adenine using AM1, STO-3G and 3-21G levels of theory, HF/6-31G(d,p), pointwise MP2//HF/6-31G(d, p) and MP2/6-31G(d, p) levels of theory, AM1 and multi-configurational wave functions indicate that the N(9)H amine structure is most stable.</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>More recent solvation studies examining water-assisted intramolecular proton transfer and electronic spectra of adenine tautomers are also in agreement that the N(9)H amine form of adenine is the most stable.</text></s></P><P><s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The issue of how cations bind to the various tautomeric forms of nucleobases has only recently been addressed in the gas phase by examining the intrinsic gas phase binding energies of cations, Cat+, to nucleobases (as defined for adenine, Ad, in reaction 1) through a combination of experimental and theoretical studies.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Consider the simplest cation, H+.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous calculations on the sites of protonation of the N9H form A have shown a proton affinity order of N1 (highest proton affinity) &gt; N3 &gt; N7.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We decided to examine these sites of protonation as well as those of the other available N atom sites (e.g. N1, N3, N7 and N9) in D–F (Table 1, and the electronic supplementary information for optimised structures (Fig. S2) and their energies (Table S2)).</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our results for the proton affinity of A correlate with those of previous studies.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, the most stable protonated form of adenine H directly correlates to the most stable tautomeric form of adenine A via protonation at N1.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Interestingly, the next most stable protonated form of adenine is not due to protonation at N3 of A, but rather due to protonation at N3 of D. The largest proton affinity corresponds to removing the proton at N9 from H to yield F. Of course the large energy difference between deprotonating H from N9 versus N1 simply reflects the energy difference between the tautomers A and F. <EQN ID="eqn1"><EQ-S ID="s69">[Ad + Cat]+ → Cat+ + Ad</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P><P><s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Attachment of a metal ion can yield quite a different outcome to that for protonation since metal ions can not only coordinate to adenine at more than one site (i.e. adenine acts as a bidentate ligand), but they can also stabilize the rare forms of nucleobases.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus the most stable form of a metallated adenine system may not correlate with the most stable neutral tautomer of adenine A.</text></s></P><P><s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This has an important consequence for the experimental measurement of metal ion affinities of nucleobases such as adenine as the value measured will depend not only on the method of measurement, but also on the genesis of the [Ad + Cat]+ species.</text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, two different experimental methods have been used to study the alkali metal ion affinities of adenine.</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, Cerda and Wesdemiotis have used the kinetic method to indirectly determine the alkali metal ion affinities of adenine by measuring the competition between ligand losses of alkali metal ion bound heterodimers between adenine and a ligand L of known alkali metal ion affinity.</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>More recently, Rodgers and Armentrout have used threshold collision induced dissociation to measure alkali metal ion affinities of adenine directly from the [Ad + Cat]+ species.</text></s></P><P><s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Apart from the differences in the methods of thermochemical measurement, the way the [Ad + Cat]+ species are formed may play a role on the value of the alkali metal ion affinity determined.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Cerda and Wesdemiotis form their [Ad + Cat + L]+ species in solution (under fast atom bombardment conditions) and then transfer them to the gas phase, while Rodgers and Armentrout form their [Ad + Cat]+ species in the gas phase directly by interacting the metal ion with neutral adenine.</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Thus the [Ad + Cat]+ species formed in the gas phase must arise from the most stable gas phase tautomer A, while the [Ad + Cat + L]+ species formed in the condensed phase may arise from a rare tautomer.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This issue is easier to address using theoretical calculations since the structures and relative energies of a range of tautomers and their metal adducts can be calculated, leading to “site specific” metal ion affinities for each tautomer.</text></s></P><P><s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Rodgers and Armentrout used ab initio calculations to examine the structures and relative stabilities of the [Ad + Cat]+ species I1–I3 where Cat = Li, Na and K for cation attachment at the N1, N3 and N7 sites of A. They found that unlike the case of Cat = H, the alkali ions prefer to bind at the N7 site since bidentate 5 membered ring structures involving the N6 exocyclic amino group are formed (I3).</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>They found that the next favoured site of attachment is N1, which also form bidentate structures involving the N6 exocyclic amino group I1, but in this case the ring size is four membered.</text></s></P><P><s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Russo et al. also considered binding of Li+ in a bidentate fashion to N3 and N9 of D to yield J1 and to N6 and N7 of the imino tautomer G3 to yield K. Both of these [Ad + Li]+ species involving the tautomers D and G3 were less stable than I3.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The situation changes for [Ad + Na]+ and [Ad + K]+ species, with J1 being more stable than I3.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An even more dramatic effect is observed for the transition metal ion Cu(i)+, whereby the imino tautomer yields the most stable [Ad + Cu]+ species K. Interestingly, the tautomer D does not give a bidentate structure J1, rather forming a monodentate structure (J3) where Cu binds to N3.</text></s></P><P><s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Experimental studies involving metal-stabilization of rare adenine tautomers have also been discussed by Muller and co-workers.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>They suggest that when a metal replaces a proton in a tautomeric structure, it forces the proton to take another site, resulting in formation of a rare tautomeric form.</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A number of examples are given involving formation of the imino tautomer species K. In these instances (where Cat = Mo(ii), Hg(ii) and Pt(ii)), the metal undergoes exchange of one of the protons from the exocyclic amino group and the resultant metal–nucleobase complex reprotonates at the N1 site.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(B)">DFT calculations of the interaction of various tautomers of adenine with silver(i)</HEADER><P><s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast to previous experimental and theoretical studies which only examined alkali and first row transition metal ion affinities for selected adenine tautomers, in this study, we consider the “site specific” silver ion affinities of all possible amino adenine tautomers.</text></s> <s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Of the imino complexes, we chose only to calculate (and compare with the amino adenine complexes) the silver ion affinity of tautomer G3 as the literature suggests that it gives rise to the most stable rare adenine complexes (K) for heavy metal ions.</text></s></P><P><s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous ab initio studies on the coordination of silver to adenine have been limited to coordination at the N7 atom of the most stable tautomer of adenine (N(9)H).</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A silver ion affinity (defined as the energy required to dissociate [Ad + Ag]+ into Ad and Ag+, cf. reaction 1) of 158.2 kJ mol−1 was calculated.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast, our calculations yield a silver ion affinity of 165.6 kJ mol−1 at the same position.</text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Apart from differences in level of theory, another reason for this discrepancy is that in Burda et al.'s work, the NH2 group (from [Ad + Ag]+) was constrained to be in the Cs plane, thereby avoiding pyramidalization of the N atom to give structure I4.</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This resulted in a monodentate interaction between the N7 atom of adenine and the silver ion.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast, no such constraint was imposed in our work and a different structure was optimised in which a bidentate interaction gives structure I3.</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This confirms the results of other studies which show that bidentate interactions with adenine can help stabilize metal complex formation.</text></s></P><P><s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The silver ion affinities at the N(1), N(3), N(7) and N(9) sites of A, D, E and F and the N(7) site of G3 (Fig. 1) were all considered and a range of bidentate structures were examined.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All structures are shown in Fig. S2 and their energies are listed in Table S4 of the electronic supplementary information, while Table 1 summarizes the silver ion affinities.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Starting from a total of 13 structures, 11 unique [Ad + Ag]+ structures were found.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reasons that a smaller set of unique [Ad + Ag]+ structures was found are discussed in more detail below.</text></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Ag+ binding to tautomer A</HEADER><P><s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The silver ion affinities for the various positions of the N9H tautomer A are: N1 = 153.5 kJ mol−1, N3 = 137.2 kJ mol−1 and N7 = 165.6 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reason that binding at the N1 and N7 position is more favorable is that the N6 amino group provides an additional binding site to yield structures of the type I1 and I3, while binding at N3 remains monodentate to give I2.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Ag+ binding to tautomer D</HEADER><P><s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For D only two unique structures were found: a bidentate J2-like structure for N1 binding with a silver ion affinity of 143.4 kJ mol−1, and a J1 type structure in which the Ag+ ion bridges between the N3 and N9 positions.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus initial guesses for geometries in which the Ag+ ion was bound to either the N3 or N9 positions always resulted in structure J1.</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Interestingly this species yields the second highest silver ion affinity (205.8 kJ mol−1) of all the tautomers.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Ag+ binding to tautomer E</HEADER><P><s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The silver ion affinities for the various positions of the N3H tautomer E are: N1 = 117.2 kJ mol−1, N7 = 164.9 kJ mol−1 and N9 = 167.3 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The binding in each of theses species are represented by structures L1–L3.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Ag+ binding to tautomer F</HEADER><P><s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Two unique structures were found for binding of Ag+ to tautomer F: the bidentate structure M1 for N7 binding with a silver ion affinity of 159.5 kJ mol−1, and the unidentate N9 structure M2.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Initial guesses for geometries in which the Ag+ ion was bound to the N3 position always resulted in migration of the Ag+ ion onto the N9 position to give structure M2.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Interestingly this species yields the highest silver ion affinity (227.5 kJ mol−1) of all the amine tautomers.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Ag+ binding to tautomer G3</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A very stable structure, K, arising from bidentate binding of Ag+ to the N6 and N7 positions of the G3 tautomer of adenine was found.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This yields the highest silver ion affinity (263.1 kJ mol−1) of all the tautomers.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(C)">Gas-phase chemistry of the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ and [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ions</HEADER><P><s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>ESI/MS of the adenine–silver nitrate (1 ∶ 2) solution yielded the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ion (m/z 485.0) as the most abundant complex.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>While singly charged ions were generally observed, several doubly charged species were also detected, most notably [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ (m/z 243.1).</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>As the species at m/z 242.1/243.1/244.1 appeared to be a combination of both the [Ad + Ag]+ and [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ions, a 1 ∶ 1 ∶ 2 solution of adenine ∶ 6-N,N-dimethyladenine (DMAP) ∶ silver nitrate was examined under identical ESI conditions to verify the existence of the multiply charged species (see the electronic supplementary information, Fig. S1a).</text></s> <s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>While overlap occurs between the singly and doubly charged homo-polymers (i.e. [Ad + Ag]+ and [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ at m/z 242.1/243.1/244.1 and [DMAP + Ag]+ and [DMAP2 + Ag2]2+ at 270.1/271.1/272.1), the formation of the doubly charged hetero-polymer [Ad + DMAP + Ag2]2+, at m/z 256.0/257.0/258.0, is a clear indication that multiply charged species are, indeed, being generated.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To determine if the complex at m/z 485.0 in the ESI/MS consisted of both singly and doubly charged ions (i.e. [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ and [Ad4 + Ag4 − 2H]2+), the 1 ∶ 1 ∶ 2 solution of adenine ∶ DMAP ∶ silver nitrate was once more utilized, and showed the presence of multiply charged ions (see the electronic supplementary information, Fig. S1b).</text></s></P><P><s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The presence of both the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ and [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ions in the ESI mass spectrum suggests that these ions have special stability.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Given that the related [Ad2 + Ag2 + 2H]4+ ion C has been structurally characterized by X-ray crystallography, it is tempting to speculate that all three ions are related to the same structural framework.</text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj9" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>To gain further insights into the gas phase chemistry and structures of the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ and [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ions, we have carried out CID, ion–molecule reactions and DFT calculations on them.</text></s></P><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>CID reactions</HEADER><P><s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ion at m/z 242.9 (corresponding to the 107Ag109Ag isotope) was mass selected with a 0.5 Th window and observed to solely fragment via formation of two [Ad + Ag]+ ions (m/z 241.9/243.9) (reaction 2) (Fig. 2a).</text></s> <s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The [Ad + Ag]+ ions underwent subsequent ion–molecule reactions with the background ESI solvent molecules, S, to form [Ad + Ag + S]+ ions.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reaction shown in reaction 3 was not observed.</text></s> <s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj10" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>To further probe and verify the fragmentation reactions of the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ion, the analogous species from the 1 ∶ 1 ∶ 2 DMAP ∶ Ad ∶ Ag mixture (i.e. [DMAP + Ad + Ag2]2+ (m/z 257.1)), was isolated and subjected to CID (Fig. 2b).</text></s> <s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The primary dissociation pathway for [DMAP + Ad + Ag2]2+ involved formation of the complementary [Ad + Ag]+ (m/z 242.1/244.1) and [DMAP + Ag]+ (m/z 270.1/272.1) ions (reaction 4), which also readily added background ESI solvent molecules.</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, a minor channel (reaction 5) involving the formation of the complementary [DMAP + H]+ (m/z 164.2) and [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ (m/z 349.9) ions was observed (Fig. 2b).<EQN ID="eqn2"><EQ-S ID="s127">[Ad2 + Ag2]2+ → 2[Ad + Ag]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn3"><EQ-S ID="s128">[Ad2 + Ag2]2+ → [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ + [Ad + H]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn4"><EQ-S ID="s129">[DMAP + Ad + Ag2]2+ → [Ad + Ag]+ + [DMAP + Ag]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn5"><EQ-S ID="s130">[DMAP + Ad + Ag2]2+ → [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ + [DMAP + H]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P><P><s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Under CID conditions, the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ion (m/z 484.9) fragments via loss of a neutral adenine molecule to form [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ (m/z 349.9) (reaction 6).</text></s> <s sid="132"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The observation of the [Ad + Ag]+ (m/z 242.0/244.0) suggests that splitting the dimer into both neutral and charged monomers may operate (reaction 7).</text></s> <s sid="133"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the formation of a complementary ion, [Ad3 + Ag3 − 2H]+ (m/z 727.7) in minor amounts (Fig. 3a), suggests that the [Ad + Ag]+ ion must mainly arise from a minor “contamination” of the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ signal by the doubly charged “tetramer” [Ad4 + Ag4 − 2H]2+ (as shown in reaction 8).</text></s> <s sid="134"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj11" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>To confirm this, the non-symmetrical “tetramer” [DMAP + Ad3 + Ag4 − 2H]2+ (m/z 499.2) ion was subjected to CID (Fig. 3b).</text></s> <s sid="135"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Indeed, the major fragments of this ion are [DMAP + Ag]+ (m/z 270.1/272.1) and [Ad3 + Ag3 − 2H]+ (m/z 727.8) (Fig. 3b, reaction 9).</text></s> <s sid="136"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Interestingly, this non-symmetrical “tetramer” also fragments to give the singly charged dimers (reaction 10) as minor products.<EQN ID="eqn6"><EQ-S ID="s137">[Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ → [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ + Ad</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="137"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn7"><EQ-S ID="s138">[Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ → [Ad + Ag]+ + [Ad + Ag − H]</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="138"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn8"><EQ-S ID="s139">[Ad4 + Ag4 − 2H]2+ → [Ad + Ag]+ + [Ad3 + Ag3 − 2H]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="139"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn9"><EQ-S ID="s140">[DMAP + Ad3 + Ag4 − 2H]2+ → [DMAP + Ag]+ + [Ad3 + Ag3 − 2H]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="140"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn10"><EQ-S ID="s141">[DMAP + Ad3 + Ag4 − 2H]2+ → [DMAP + Ad + Ag2 − H]+ + [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P><P><s sid="141"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus the complex at m/z 484.9 (Fig. 3a) predominately consisted of the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ species.</text></s> <s sid="142"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The fragmentation behaviour of the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ species was further confirmed by MSn experiments in which the singly charged species was “synthesized” from larger adenine–silver complexes and subjected to CID, e.g. [Ad3 + Ag4 − 3H]+ → [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+.</text></s> <s sid="143"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Adenine loss resulting in the formation of [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ was once again found to be the major product ion (data not shown).</text></s></P><P><s sid="144"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is clear from these results that the charge on a metal complex can play a significant role in the fragmentation reactions observed.</text></s> <s sid="145"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus while monomer formation dominates for [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ (reaction 2), this only represents a minor process for [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ (reaction 7).</text></s> <s sid="146"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Similarly adenine loss, which is the major fragmentation channel for [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ (reaction 6), does not occur for [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ (reaction 3).</text></s></P><DIV DEPTH="4"><HEADER>Ion–molecule reactions</HEADER><P><s sid="147"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Butylamine (proton affinity (PA) = 921.5 kJ mol−1) reacts with the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ion via two pathways (Fig. 4a): (i) a proton transfer reaction to yield [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ (m/z 484.9) and BuNH3+ (m/z 74.1) (reaction 11); (ii) formation of an adduct containing two butylamine molecules (reaction 12).</text></s> <s sid="148"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Chemical dissociation (e.g. via reaction 13) of the dimer is not observed.</text></s> <s sid="149"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Product ions similar to reaction 11 and 12 were observed when [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ was allowed to react with pyridine (PA = 930 kJ mol−1), while in the cases of acetonitrile (PA = 779.2 kJ mol−1) and methanol (PA = 754.3 kJ mol−1), only adduct formation involving the addition of two neutral molecules was observed (cf. reaction 12).</text></s> <s sid="150"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since proton transfer is not observed for acetonitrile but is observed for butylamine, the apparent proton affinity of [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ can be bracketed between acetonitrile PA = 779.2 kJ mol−1 and butylamine PA = 921.5 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="151"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We have not tried to experimentally determine a more precise PA since these reactions have problems associated with determining the reverse activation barrier.<EQN ID="eqn11"><EQ-S ID="s153">[Ad2 + Ag2]2+ + BuNH2 → [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ + BuNH3+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="152"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn12"><EQ-S ID="s154">[Ad2 + Ag2]2+ + 2BuNH2 → [Ad2 + Ag2 + 2BuNH2]2+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="153"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn13"><EQ-S ID="s155">[Ad2 + Ag2]2+ + 2BuNH2 → 2 [Ad + Ag + BuNH2]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P><P><s sid="154"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to find support that the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ions formed via reaction 11 have the same structure as those formed in the ESI processes, these ions were mass selected in a MS3 experiment and subjected to CID (data not shown).</text></s> <s sid="155"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The major fragmentation channel corresponded to loss of adenine (reaction 6).</text></s> <s sid="156"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results suggest that the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ and [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ions observed in the ESI mass spectrum have the same structural framework and that the [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ions may be formed during the ESI process via gas phase deprotonation reactions in the desolvation region.</text></s></P><P><s sid="157"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Butylamine reacts differently with [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ (Fig. 4b), not undergoing proton transfer (reaction 14), but rather forming an adduct in which one neutral molecule was able to complex to the parent ion (reaction 15).</text></s> <s sid="158"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same type of reaction is observed for pyridine and acetonitrile (data not shown).<EQN ID="eqn14"><EQ-S ID="s161">[Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ + BuNH2 → [Ad2 + Ag2 − 2H] + BuNH3+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="159"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn15"><EQ-S ID="s162">[Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ + BuNH2 → [Ad2 + Ag2 − H + BuNH2]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P><P><s sid="160"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The “overcoordination” reactions observed in reactions 12 and 15 are quite interesting.</text></s> <s sid="161"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Based on studies which showed that Ag(i) prefers to coordinate two ligands in the gas phase, we previously suggested that ligands such as butylamine act as a hydrogen bond acceptors, forming hydrogen-bonded complexes N and O with the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ and [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ ions.</text></s> <s sid="162"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our speculation was also consistent with early investigations into the clustering of water and ammonia to Ag+ in the gas phase, which suggest that more than 2 ligands can cluster to form ions of the type AgLn+ (where L = H2O or NH3 and n &gt; 2) but that the binding energies for n &gt; 2 are less than the first and second binding energies.</text></s> <s sid="163"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>More recent studies suggest that although the rate of the third addition of ammonia is slower than the second, isomeric structures of Ag(NH3)n+ ions are likely to exist in the gas phase.</text></s> <s sid="164"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Shoeib et al. suggest that the Ag(NH3)3+ trigonal pyramidal structure is slightly more stable than the hydrogen bonded isomer [H3NAgNH3…NH3]+, while Fox et al. found a reverse order.</text></s> <s sid="165"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although these two recent theoretical studies seem in conflict, they both agree that there is very little energetic difference between directly coordinating a third ammonia versus placing it in a second solvation shell.</text></s> <s sid="166"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In light of these new theoretical results it is possible that the species formed in reactions 12 and 15 may have alternative structures to N and O involving the direct binding of ligands L to the silver centres.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="3"><HEADER>Insights into the reactivity of [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ and [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ species via DFT calculations</HEADER><P><s sid="167"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Various isomeric structures are possible for the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ species, ranging from structures in which two silver ions bridge two adenines to give a dimer which is stabilized via four silver–adenine bonds (cf. structure C) to structures which have fewer silver–adenine bonds.</text></s> <s sid="168"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>While many of these isomers might fragment to form monomeric species (reaction 3), isomeric [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ structures with fewer silver–adenine bonds may be more prone to chemical dissociation in ion–molecule reactions (reaction 13).</text></s> <s sid="169"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Given the large numbers of possible isomers and the computationally challenging size of these systems, we limited our search to isomers of structures P1–P7 shown in Fig. 5.</text></s> <s sid="170"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="No"/><text>Thus, we cannot guarantee that this limited search has located the global minimum for the [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ structure.</text></s> <s sid="171"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Structures P1–P3 share the same trans motif of C but differ in the adenine tautomer(s) present in the structure, with P1 being composed of two D tautomers.</text></s> <s sid="172"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast P2 is composed of one D and one F tautomer, while P3 is composed of two F tautomers.</text></s> <s sid="173"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our initial structure search at the B3LYP/6-31G(d) level gave a stability order of P1 (most stable) &gt; P2 &gt; P3 (least stable), which nicely tracks the relative stabilities of the adenine tautomers (D is more stable than F).</text></s> <s sid="174"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Given that bridged dimers containing two F tautomers are the least stable, we limited our search of the alternative cis motif to structures P4 and P5.</text></s> <s sid="175"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Not only do these isomers exhibit the same relative stability order (P4 more stable than P5), but their stabilities relative to their trans isomers are similar, with P1 being the most stable species.</text></s> <s sid="176"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Isomers which had fewer silver–adenine bonds but which were compensated by hydrogen bonding proved to be much less stable than isomers P1–P5.</text></s> <s sid="177"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example P6 (which has three silver–adenine bonds and one hydrogen bond) and P7 (which has two silver–adenine bonds and two hydrogen bonds) were 106 and 217 kJ mol−1 less stable than P1, respectively.</text></s></P><P><s sid="178"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since isomer P1 is the most stable, we focussed the rest of our DFT calculations on the reactions of this isomer.</text></s> <s sid="179"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The first reaction we considered was deprotonation (reaction 3), which can occur from either the N7 or the N6 amino group of P1.</text></s> <s sid="180"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Deprotonation at N7 yields the most stable isomer: Q1 (by nearly 100 kJ mol−1).</text></s> <s sid="181"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Recalling the difficulties in precisely measuring the proton affinity of [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ experimentally, the energies of the DFT calculated structures P1 and Q1 can be used to yield a theoretical estimate of the proton affinity of [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ of 772.7 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="182"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This value is entirely consistent with the experimental results if one considers that the base acetonitrile (PA = 779.2 kJ mol−1) is likely to experience a reverse activation energy barrier for deprotonation.</text></s></P><P><s sid="183"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We can also use the DFT calculated energies of P1 and Q1 and various other adenine species to calculate the competing fragmentation reactions of [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ (reaction 2 versus reaction 3) and [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ (reaction 6 versus reaction 7).</text></s> <s sid="184"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>If we disregard complex rearrangement or tautomerization reactions, then reaction 2 represents the symmetrical dissociation of P1 to give two singly charged [Ad + Ag]+ ions with structure J1, while reaction 3 represents the formation of a [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ species and the N9 protonated tautomer D. A number of isomeric [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ structures are possible including R1 and R2, which were fully optimised using DFT theory (see Fig. S2 and Table S5 of the electronic supplementary information).</text></s> <s sid="185"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although R2 is more stable than R1, its formation requires a translocation of a silver ion and thus we use R1 in our calculation for the energy of reaction 3.</text></s> <s sid="186"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Using these structures, we calculate that reaction 2 is endothermic by 25.5 kJ mol−1 while reaction 3 is endothermic by 137.4 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="187"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results are consistent with the experimental observation that reaction 2 is the major process (Fig. 2a).</text></s> <s sid="188"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In a similar fashion, reaction 6 represents dissociation of Q1 to give R1 and neutral tautomer D, while reaction 7 represents the formation of J1 and a [Ad + Ag − H] neutral species.</text></s> <s sid="189"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Once again, a range of a [Ad + Ag − H] neutral species are possible and we calculated the structures of 9 isomers (see Fig. S2 and Table S6 of the electronic supplementary information).</text></s> <s sid="190"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Deprotonation of J1 at the N7 position yields S1.</text></s> <s sid="191"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Not only is S1 the most likely isomer to form since it does not require a rearrangement reaction, but it is the most stable [Ad + Ag − H] neutral isomer calculated.</text></s> <s sid="192"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Using these species, we calculate that reaction 6 is endothermic by 282.0 kJ mol−1 while reaction 7 is endothermic by 268.7 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="193"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These predictions contrast with the experimental observation that reaction 6 is the major process (Fig. 3a).</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(D)">Ion–molecule reactions, CID and DFT calculations of the fragmentation reactions of the [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ ion</HEADER><P><s sid="194"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ ion (m/z 350.1) reacts with butylamine (Fig. 6a), pyridine, acetonitrile and methanol, respectively, via the addition of two equivalents of the neutral species (reaction 16), which is consistent with the presence of two vacant coordination sites on the silver atoms in structure R1.</text></s> <s sid="195"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ ion underwent a unique fragmentation reaction under CID to yield the radical cation [Ad + Ag–H]+˙ (m/z 240.9/242.9) via loss of a silver atom (reaction 17) (Fig. 6b).</text></s> <s sid="196"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>No significant formation of a charged silver ion (reaction 18) was observed.</text></s> <s sid="197"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Once again, DFT calculations were used to examine the two fragmentation processes shown in reactions 17 and 18.</text></s> <s sid="198"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj12" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Reaction 17 represents the dissociation of R1 to give a radical cation species [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ and silver atom, while reaction 18 represents the [Ad + Ag − H] neutral species and a silver cation.</text></s> <s sid="199"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Once again, a range of isomers are possible for the [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ and [Ad + Ag − H] species.</text></s> <s sid="200"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs37" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Repeated attempts to optimise structures of the radical cation of tautomer D with the N7H atom removed and with the Ag ion bound to either N3, N9 or bridging N3 and N9 always resulted in the formation of structure T1 in which the silver binds to the N9 position (see Fig. S2 and Table S6 of the electronic supplementary information).</text></s> <s sid="201"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Using S1 and T1, we calculate that reaction 17 is endothermic by 242.1 kJ mol−1 while reaction 18 is endothermic by 192.5 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="202"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These predictions contrast with the experimental observation that reaction 17 is the major process (Fig. 6b).</text></s> <s sid="203"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn16"><EQ-S ID="s206">[Ad + Ag2 − H]+ + 2L → [Ad + Ag2 − H + 2L]+ (L = MeOH, MeCN, BuNH2 and pyridine)</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="204"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn17"><EQ-S ID="s207">[Ad + Ag2 − H]+ → [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ + Ag</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="205"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn18"><EQ-S ID="s208">[Ad + Ag2 − H]+ → Ag+ + [Ad + Ag − H]</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(E)">Comparison of CID, ion–molecule reactions and DFT structures of the [Ad + Ag]+ and [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ ions</HEADER><P><s sid="206"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj13" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The multistage mass spectrometry capabilities of the ion trap allow the [Ad + Ag]+ (m/z 242.1/244.1) (i.e. the product of reaction 2) and [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ (m/z 241.1/243.1) (i.e. the product of reaction 17) ions to be isolated and studied under similar reaction conditions.</text></s> <s sid="207"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Ion–molecule reactions with butylamine (and the other neutral reagents) do not distinguish between the even (reaction 19) (Fig. 7a) and odd electron ions (reaction 20) (Fig. 7b) since both undergo addition of only one butylamine molecule to their vacant coordination site.</text></s> <s sid="208"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast, their behaviour under CID conditions is quite different.</text></s> <s sid="209"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, the even electron ion solely fragmented via neutral adenine loss (reaction 21) (Fig. 8a), while the odd electron ions underwent three fragmentation pathways (Fig. 8b): (a) loss of the neutral adeninyl radical U1 (reaction 22), (b) loss of a silver atom to yield the even electron ion corresponding to abstraction of a hydride ion from neutral adenine V1 (reaction 23) and (c) fragmentation of the adenine ring (resulting in HCN loss) with retention of the silver ion (reaction 24).</text></s> <s sid="210"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Reaction 23 is noteworthy since it results in the formation of the nitrenium ion of adenine V1 and it proceeds via redox reactions of [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ involving two consecutive losses of silver atoms.</text></s> <s sid="211"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Nitrenium ions, which are of considerable interest as the nitrogen analogues of carbenes, exhibit unusual singlet–triplet splitting and are also involved in damage of DNA.</text></s> <s sid="212"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Several nitrenium ions have been synthesized and characterized in the gas phase including: NH2+, NF2+, CH3NH+, CH3CH2NH+, (CH3)2N+, PhNH+.</text></s> <s sid="213"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>While aromatic nitrenium ions in which the N is attached to the aromatic ring have been extensively studied in the condensed phase, nitrenium ions such as V1 in which the N atom is part of a ring have received less attention.</text></s></P><P><s sid="214"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj14" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The fragmentation pathways of the radical cation species [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ (reactions 22 and 23) were theoretically investigated as well.</text></s> <s sid="215"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Loss of a silver ion from [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ to yield the neutral adeninyl radical U1 (reaction 22) was calculated to be thermodynamically favoured ( + 217.9 kJ mol−1) over loss of a silver atom to yield the ion V1 (reaction 23) ( + 276.6 kJ mol−1), consistent with a higher combined yield of 107Ag+ and 109Ag+ over the [Ad − H]+ ion (Fig. 8b).</text></s> <s sid="216"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since the nitrenium ion V1 may exist in either the singlet or triplet state, we used DFT calculations to show that the singlet state is more stable by +160.5 kJ mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="217"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This finding is consistent with calculations on the singlet-to-triplet transition energy in other nitrogen-rich heteroaromatic systems and may be attributed to π stabilization in the singlet state.</text></s> <s sid="218"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn19"><EQ-S ID="s221">[Ad + Ag]+ + BuNH2 → [Ad + Ag + BuNH2]+</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="219"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn20"><EQ-S ID="s222">[Ad + Ag − H]+˙ + BuNH2 → [Ad + Ag − H + BuNH2]+˙</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="220"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn21"><EQ-S ID="s223">[Ad + Ag]+ → Ag+ + Ad</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="221"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn22"><EQ-S ID="s224">[Ad + Ag − H]+˙ → Ag+ + [Ad − H]˙</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="222"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn23"><EQ-S ID="s225">[Ad + Ag − H]+˙ → [Ad − H]+ + Ag</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="223"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn24"><EQ-S ID="s226">[Ad + Ag − H]+˙ → [Ad + Ag − H − HCN]+˙ + HCN</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P><P><s sid="224"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj15" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>How do these CID reactions compare with other studies on adenine actions and related systems?</text></s> <s sid="225"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rodgers and Armentrout recently studied the threshold CID reactions of a range of metal ions complexed to adenine, [M + Ad]+, using xenon as the collision gas.</text></s> <s sid="226"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the majority of these complexes, the primary dissociation pathway was loss of neutral adenine (reaction 25), which is similar to the Ag+ forming reactions we observed (reactions 21, 22).</text></s> <s sid="227"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For M = Zn+, a redox reaction occurs (reaction 26), which is similar to that shown in reaction 23.</text></s> <s sid="228"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Redox processes involving losses of metal atoms have also been observed in: (i) the high energy CID spectra of the [M + Li]+, [M + 2Li − H]+ and [M + 3Li − 2H]+ ions of adenine, and (ii) the photodissociation of the [pyridine + Ag]+ ion.</text></s> <s sid="229"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, [M + Ad]+ ions also fragment via small molecule losses from the adenine moiety, including loss of HCN (reaction 27) when M = Sc+, Ti+ and V+.</text></s> <s sid="230"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>HCN loss has also been observed in the CID spectra of various adenine ions, including protonated adenine.</text></s> <s sid="231"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn25"><EQ-S ID="s234">[M + Ad]+ + Xe → M+ + Ad + Xe</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="232"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn26"><EQ-S ID="s235">[M + Ad]+ + Xe → M + Ad+˙ + Xe</EQ-S></EQN></text></s><s sid="233"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text><EQN ID="eqn27"><EQ-S ID="s236">[M + Ad]+ + Xe → M+(C4H4N4)+ HCN + Xe</EQ-S></EQN></text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="(F)">Synthesis and chemistry of other novel silver–adenine ions formed via CID reactions</HEADER><P><s sid="234"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In order to evaluate whether redox processes occur in larger adenine–silver clusters to yield other novel radical cations, we examined their MSn behaviour.</text></s> <s sid="235"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj16" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In those cases where radical cations were formed, their fragmentation behaviour was compared to their even electron counterparts.</text></s> <s sid="236"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our results are summarized in Scheme 1 and key spectra are shown in Fig. S3–S5.</text></s> <s sid="237"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Consistent with the observations for the [Ad + Ag]+ and [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ ions, all of the corresponding even and odd electron species fragmented via different pathways.</text></s> <s sid="238"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, CID of [Ad2 + Ag3 − 2H]+ resulted in two distinct dissociation pathways, i.e. formation of the [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ (reaction 28) and [Ad + Ag3 − 2H]+ (reaction 29) ions, while the [Ad2 + Ag3 − 3H]+˙ ion (which was observed to form upon CID of the [Ad2 + Ag4 − 3H]+ ion (reaction 32)) fragmented via multiple HCN losses (reaction 36), in addition to forming the [Ad + Ag3 − 3H]+˙ (reaction 33), [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ (reaction 34) and [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ ions (reaction 35).</text></s> <s sid="239"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A comparison of the dissociation pathways for the [Ad + Ag3 − 2H]+ and [Ad + Ag3 − 3H]+˙ ions revealed a striking difference.</text></s> <s sid="240"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>While loss of a silver atom was observed for the [Ad + Ag3 − 2H]+ ion (reaction 30), multiple losses of HCN and CN occurred for [Ad + Ag3 − 3H]+˙ to yield the silver trimer cluster ion, Ag3+ (reaction 37), a species whose gas phase chemistry has been examined previously.</text></s> <s sid="241"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This fragmentation pattern was also observed for the [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ and [Ad + Ag2 − 2H]+˙ ions, which resulted in the formation of [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ (reaction 17) and loss of HCN, respectively (reaction 31).</text></s> <s sid="242"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results clearly show that multistage CID experiments can be effectively used to distinguish between even and odd electron ions of silver–adenine complexes.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="243"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This study confirms that complexes between adenine and silver exhibit a rich range of binding modes.</text></s> <s sid="244"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Electrospray ionization on a mixture of adenine and AgNO3 provides access to [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+ species whose reactivity can be examined in the gas phase using a combination of multistage mass spectrometry experiments as well as DFT calculations.</text></s> <s sid="245"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The structures of 11 isomeric [Ad + Ag]+ ions, examined via DFT calculations, show different binding modes of Ag+ which depend on both the site of binding and the tautomeric form of adenine.</text></s> <s sid="246"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For silver cation coordination at the N3 position, only the N7H tautomer results in bidentate bridging of the silver.</text></s> <s sid="247"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the case of the N1H species, the silver actually migrates from N3 to N9, while for the N9H tautomer the silver ion remains at the N3 position.</text></s> <s sid="248"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the case of silver coordination at the N9 position, both the N1H and N3H tautomers result in unidentate structures, while the N7H species yields bidentate silver coordination at the N3 and N9 positions.</text></s> <s sid="249"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These calculations also reveal that the most stable [Ad + Ag]+ ion does not correspond to the most stable neutral adenine tautomer (which was found to be is the N9H tautomer), consistent with previous studies that have shown that transition metal ions can stabilize rare tautomeric forms of nucleobases.</text></s></P><P><s sid="250"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Both the charge and the stoichiometry of the [Adx + Agy − zH](y − z)+ complexes plays a pivotal role in directing the types of fragmentation and ion–molecule reactions observed.</text></s> <s sid="251"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ is observed to dissociate to [Ad + Ag]+ and to react with butylamine via proton transfer, while [Ad2 + Ag2 − H]+ fragments via loss of neutral adenine to form the [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ ion and does not undergo proton transfer to butylamine.</text></s> <s sid="252"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>DFT calculations on several isomeric [Ad2 + Ag2]2+ ions suggest that planar centrosymmetric cations, in which two adjacent silver atoms are bridged by two N7H adenine tautomers via N(3),N(9)-bidentate interactions are the most stable.</text></s> <s sid="253"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is consistent with the known condensed phase planar centrosymmetric [(adeninium)2Ag2]4+ cations of structure C.</text></s></P><P><s sid="254"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The [Ad + Ag2 − H]+ ion adds two neutral reagents in ion–molecule reactions, consistent with the presence of two vacant coordination sites.</text></s> <s sid="255"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It undergoes a silver atom loss to form the [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ radical cation, which in turn fragments quite differently to the even electron [Ad + Ag]+ ion.</text></s> <s sid="256"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus while the [Ad + Ag]+ ion fragments solely via Ag+ loss, the [Ad + Ag − H]+˙ ion also fragments via loss of a silver atom as well as fragmentation of the adenine ring (via HCN loss).</text></s> <s sid="257"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The fragmentation reactions of other pairs radical cation/even electron adenine–silver complexes were examined and in each case they fragmented differently.</text></s> <s sid="258"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since amino acid–silver complexes are known to form polymeric structures in the condensed phase, we are currently examining their gas phase chemistry to see if we can generate novel radical cations of amino acids.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>