<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b311934c" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Polyferrocenes: metallopolymers with tunable and high refractive indices</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The refractive index, molar refraction and Abbé number of polyferrocene derivatives are reported and the values indicate that these materials are very promising for a range of photonics applications.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER/><P><s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Progress in developing and fabricating new photonic devices depends on the availability of materials with appropriate optical properties.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Polymers offer ease of functionalization and low processing cost.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Additionally, due to their inherent flexibility, polymers can be used in devices with a complicated design.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unfortunately, in contrast to traditionally used inorganic glasses, organic polymers possess a narrow range of refractive indices.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since many present and proposed photonic devices are based on microcomponents with a high refractive index contrast, the applicability of polymers in such devices is limited.<REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In response to this shortcoming, molecular tailoring of macromolecules with functional groups varying in electronic polarization is used to expand the refractive index (RI) range of polymers.<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For instance, highly polarizable π-conjugated functionalities incorporated into organic polymers increase their RI.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Unfortunately, π-conjugation brings drawbacks such as high optical dispersion, light absorption, and birefringence.<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, as a general approach, molecular tailoring is constrained by the availability of functional groups, maintaining the upper limit of the refractive index of organic polymers near 1.6.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Alternatively, the incorporation of inorganic clusters into a polymer matrix can be used as a means of increasing the refractive index of polymers; however the weaknesses of heterogeneous structures include higher optical loss and poor processability.</text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A more promising strategy involves the incorporation of high molar refraction elements such as S, P, and Pb, into macromolecules which increases the RI without significantly increasing the optical dispersion of the material.<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit6"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit7"/><REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit8"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous studies on polyferrocenylsilanes<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit9"/> demonstrated their potential as materials for optical-fiber sensing and tunable photonic devices.<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit10"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit11"/></text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To date, however, the optical properties of these and other polyferrocenes remain virtually unexplored.</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this communication, we demonstrate that the class of polyferrocene polymers possesses unusually high RI values which can be further increased by tailoring the backbone with high molar refraction substituent groups.</text></s></P><P><s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The structures of polyferrocene derivatives synthesized by ring-opening methodologies,<REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit12"/><REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit14"/><REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit16"/> are given in Fig. 1, along with the corresponding RI values measured at λ = 589 nm (Sopra GES-5 ellipsometer).</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For polyferrocenylsilanes (series 1), we show the possibility of tuning the refractive index by varying the substituent groups: from lower values via fluorination (n = 1.60 for 1a) to higher values via arylation (n = 1.68 for 1d).</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Additional tuning of the refractive index was accomplished by changing the spacer element (E), as exemplified with 1c and 2 for the same substituent groups, and for 3–5 for different substituent groups.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Polyferrocenylphosphines and polyferrocenylphosphine sulfides (4 and 5) showed unusually high RI values (n = 1.74 and n = 1.72, respectively).</text></s></P><P><s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Further characterization of the optical properties of polyferrocenes was performed by extracting their molar refraction.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We used the Lorentz and Lorenz equation [eqn.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(1)]<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit17"/> which expresses the molar refraction (RM) of the repeating unit in terms of n and the molar volume (VM) of a polymer repeating unit.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since the molar refraction is an additive term (ΣRi), where Ri is the molar refraction of the functional group, for each repeating unit we subtracted from RM the molar refraction of the substituent groups.<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit17"/></text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this fashion, we obtained the molar refraction of the backbone unit, RfcE, where fc is the ferrocene unit and E is the spacer element.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We found RfcE to be 57.2, 58.9, 63.2, and 62.5 cm3 mol−1 for fcSi, fcGe, fcSn and fcP, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We note that these values are significantly higher than those of other inorganic polymers.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For instance, the molar refraction of the [NP] repeating unit of polyphosphazenes is 14.36 cm3 mol−1. <REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit8"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The values of RfcE allowed us to predict refractive indices for polyferrocenes with different substituent groups (for which the values of Ri are known).<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit17"/></text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For instance, the large RM value of 63.2 cm3 mol−1 for the fcSn repeating unit showed the potential of further increasing the RI to 1.82 for a hypothetical polyferrocenylstannane 3c tailored with naphthyl substituent groups.</text></s></P><P><s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Since at optical frequencies the extent of light-induced polarization of electrons from their equilibrium position relative to the nuclei is directly related to the molar refraction of a medium [eqn.</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(2)],<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit17"/> we plotted RfcE vs. the atomic polarizability of the spacer element (αE).</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In Fig. 2 the slope of 2.72 × 1024 mol−1 obtained from the regression for group 14 elements is comparable to the slope of 2.52 × 1024 mol−1 expected from eqn. (2).</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A small discrepancy between the experimental and theoretical values resulted from the assumption that the spacer elements are in an unbound state.<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit18"/></text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This discrepancy was more significant for the molar refraction of the fcP group which did not follow the trend of fcE for group 14 elements (Fig. 2).</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast with group 14 elements, the P-center in polyferrocene 4 is trivalent with a nonbonding pair of electrons.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, for P a higher molar value of refraction per polarizability presumably expressed the stronger propensity of nonbonding electrons to be polarized by an applied electric field.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Previous studies of phosphorus compounds showed that their molar refractivity strongly depends on P valency.<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit19"/><REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit20"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We also used the y-intercept of the group 14 regression to calculate the molar refraction of ferrocene in polyferrocenes.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We found an extrapolated Rfc of 43.6 cm3 mol−1.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This value is comparable to a previous value of 50.4 cm3 mol−1 found for molecular ferrocene by Aroney et al.<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit21"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Optical dispersion of polyferrocenes 1–5 (Fig. 1) was expressed as the Abbé number, νD:<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit1"/> where nD, nF, and nC are the refractive indices at 589, 486 and 656 nm, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To demonstrate the optical merits of polyferrocenes, we adapted the data of Dislich<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit1"/> showing the relationship between the Abbé number (optical dispersion) and the refractive indices for inorganic glasses and organic polymers.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In Fig. 3, the dotted and the hatched areas show the range of Abbé numbers and the associated refractive indices for purely organic polymers and for inorganic glasses, respectively.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Polyferrocenes have a substantially higher Abbé number (lower dispersion) than organic polymers with the same refractive indices.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 3 also shows that for the same dispersion polyferrocenes possess significantly higher values of RI than organic polymers (e.g. see dotted line for ν = 23).</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus the main group spacer elements prove to be efficient in increasing the refractive index of a polymer without increasing its optical dispersion.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Overall, polyferrocenes have an intermediate position between organic polymers and inorganic glasses.</text></s></P><P><s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In summary, we showed that polyferrocenes have exceptionally high refractive indices at relatively low optical dispersion.</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We also found that polyferrocenes have inherently high molar refraction, in comparison with other inorganic polymers.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This feature provides great promise for achieving higher values of refractive index by attaching deliberately chosen side groups with high molar refraction.</text></s></P><P><s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>E.K. and I.M. thank the Canadian Government for Canada Research Chairs.</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>C.P. thanks NSERC and is grateful to Sara Bourke for providing polyferrocenylgermane.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>