<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b311304c" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Immunoquantitative analysis for berberine and its related compounds using monoclonal antibodies in herbal medicines</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The monoclonal antibody (MAb) against berberine, a bioactive constituent of Coptis japonica M., Phellodendron amurense R. and Hydrastis canadensis L., was produced and characterized.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As immunogen, the derivative of berberine, 9-O-carboxymethyl berberrubine was synthesized and conjugated to carrier protein, bovine serum albumin (BSA).</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In order to confirm its immunogenicity, the ratio of hapten in berberine–BSA conjugate was determined by matrix-assisted laser desorption/ionization time of flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF MS).</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After immunization, hybridomas secreting MAbs against berberine were produced by fusing splenocytes with mouse myeloma cell line, P3-X63-Ag8-653.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After the screening, anti-berberine MAb 1D5-3B-7 was obtained.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Subsequently, a quantitative ELISA system for berberine and its related compounds using the MAb was established and evaluated comparing with HPLC method.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The ELISA method described in this study can be available as an analytical tool for quality control and standardization of medicinal plants and its prescriptions containing berberine and its related compounds.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Berberine, a quarternary protoberberine-type alkaloid, is one of the well-known bioactive compounds distributed widely in a number of clinically important medicinal plants such as Coptis japonica M., Phellodendron amurense R. and Hydrastis canadensis L. Berberine containing plants have been used in traditional and folk medicine around the world for centuries.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It has been used for a bitter tonic, diaphoretic, anti-pyretic, eye infections and diarrhoea.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the past three decades, berberine has been studied intensively in over 1000 cases because of its physiological and pharmacological effects such as anti-inflammatory,<REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/> anti-fungicidal,<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/> anti-secretory,<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/> anti-mycotic,<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/> anti-leishmanial<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit6"/> and cardiovascular effect.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit7"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, berberine has been applied orally as a tea or capsule, externally as a skin lotion, as an eyewash, or as a virginal douche.</text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition to its medicinal uses, berberine is also used as a fluorescent staining of cells,<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit8"/> DNA,<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit9"/> and energized mitochondria<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit10"/> in biochemical researches.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Currently, a number of methods including colorimetric determinations,<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit11"/> thin layer chromatography (TLC),<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit12"/> high performance liquid chromatography (HPLC)<REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit13"/><REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit14"/> and capillary electrophoresis (CE)<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit15"/> have been applied for the determination of berberine in its quality control.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="No"/><text>Although these chromatographic methodologies are accurate and sufficiently sensitive, there are some disadvantages such as the limited number of samples, pretreatment of sample, time and labour consuming besides interference by other compounds included in herbal medicines.</text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>In contrast, an enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay (ELISA) using monoclonal antibody (MAb) is more fast, convenient, and economic comparing with other methods.</text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Despite their high cost and the long process involved in their development and establishment, an ELISA has become an important methodology for the quantitative and/or qualitative analysis of pesticides,<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit16"/> preservatives,<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit17"/> environmental chemicals<REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit18"/> and phytochemical compounds<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit19"/> having small molecular weights.</text></s></P><P><s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We report herein an ELISA system using MAb against berberine and its related compounds.</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj4" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>It is applied to the analysis of berberine and its related compounds in individual plants and herbal medicines.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Chemicals and immunochemicals</HEADER><P><s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Berberine hydrochloride was purchased from Nacalai tesque, Inc. (Kyoto, Japan).</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Coptisine chloride, palmatine chloride, corydaline and papaverine hydrochloride were purchased from Wako Pure Chemical Ind., Ltd. (Osaka, Japan).</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Berberrubine, 9-acetylberberine and 8-oxyberberine were synthesized (data not shown).</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Prescription samples were purchased from Teikoku Seiyaku Co., Ltd. (Kagawa, Japan) and Tsumura Co. (Tokyo, Japan).</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Bovine serum albumin (BSA) and human serum albumin (HSA) were obtained from Sigma Chemical Co. (St. Louis, MO, USA).</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Enriched RPMI1640-Dulbecco's-Ham's F12 medium (eRDF) and RD-1 additives were obtained from Kyokuto Pharamceutical Ind., Ltd. (Tokyo, Japan).</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Peroxidase-labelled anti-mouse IgG was provided by Organon Teknika Cappel Products (West Chester, PA, USA).</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Fetal Calf Serum (FCS) was provided by Cambrex Co. (Wakersville, MA, USA).</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>All other chemicals were standard commercial products of analytical grade.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Synthesis of hapten for conjugates</HEADER><P><s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Berberine was derived to 9-O-carboxymethyl berberine as follows (Fig. 1):</text></s></P><P><s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Step A: Demethylation of berberine</text></s></P><P><s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Demethylation of berberine was performed following Iwasa's method<REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit20"/> with modification as indicated below.</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Berberine (3 g) was heated at 190 °C for 15 min.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The resulting mixture was dissolved in H2O, and extracted with chloroform 3 times.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Chloroform was evaporated, and the residue was purified by column chromatography using Sephadex LH20 and ODS gel to give berberrubine which was identified by the comparison of 1H NMR with that of an authentic sample.</text></s></P><P><s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Step B: Carboxymethylation of berberrubine</text></s></P><P><s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>9-O-Carboxymethyl berberrubine was synthesized following Sadykov's method with modification.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Chloroacetic acid (300 mg, 3.17 mol) was added to a stirred solution of berberrubine (100 mg, 0.31 mol) in chloroform at room temperature.<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reaction mixture was stirred for 3 h.</text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solvent was evaporated, the residue was chromatographed to give 9-O-carboxymethyl berberrubine.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>9-O-Carboxymethyl berberrubine was identified by comparing the data of 1H NMR with that of an authentic sample.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Conjugation to carrier proteins</HEADER><P><s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>1-Ethyl-3-(3′-dimethylaminopropyl)-carbodiimide hydrochloride (EDC, 8 mg, 0.042 mmol) and 9-O-carboxymethyl berberrubine (8 mg, 0.021 mmol) was added to a solution of pyridine (1 ml).</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reaction mixture was added dropwise to H2O solution (1 ml) containing BSA or HSA (8 mg), and then stirred for 3 h at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Subsequently, the mixture was dialyzed with 5 changes of H2O for 2 days at 4 °C, and lyophilized.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Determination of hapten number in hapten–carrier protein conjugate by MALDI-TOF MS</HEADER><P><s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met15" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The hapten number in the berberine–protein conjugates were determined by MALDI-TOF MS as previously described.<REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A small amount (1–10 pmol) of hapten–conjugate was mixed with a 103-fold molar excess of sinapinic acid in an aqueous solution containing 0.15percent trifluoroacetic acid.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mixture (0.5–1.0 µl) was deposited on sample plate and air-dried.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The mass spectra were acquired using a delayed extraction MALDI TOF MS (Voyager Elite, PerSeptive Biosystems, Inc., Framingham, MA, USA) operated in the linear model.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The instrument was generally operated at an accelerating voltage of 20 kV and a grid voltage of 90percent of the accelerating voltage.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Flight time was measured by a 500 MHz transient digitizer board in the computer, and the data were analyzed using GRAMS/386 software (Galactis Industries Corp., Salem, NH, USA).</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met16" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The molecular weight of each conjugate was calculated from the peak centroid of the [M + H]+ peak.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Immunization, hybridization and antibody production</HEADER><P><s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Two female, 6 weeks old BALB/c mice (Kyudo, Kumamoto, Japan) were immunized intraperitoneally with berberine–BSA solution three times biweekly.</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The first immunization (50 µg of immunogen) was injected as a 1:1 (v/v) emulsion in Freund's complete adjuvant (DIFCO Laboratories., MI, USA) to a total volume of 0.5 ml.</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The second immunization (50 µg of immunogen) was injected as a 1:1 emulsion in Freund's incomplete adjuvant.</text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The final immunization (100 µg of immunogen) was given without any adjuvant 3 days prior to cell fusion.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The immunized splenocytes were isolated and fused with a hypoxanthine-aminopterine-thymidine (HAT) sensitive mouse myeloma cell line, P3-X63-Ag8-653, by the polyethylene glycol (PEG) method.<REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit23"/></text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hybridoma producing MAb against berberine were cloned twice by the limited dilution method<REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit24"/> as follows: After centrifuging the cells from the wells of a 24 well plate that contains hybridomas, the cells were counted and suspensions with concentrations of 50, 10 and 5 cells ml−1 were prepared.</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then 100 µl of a suspension of each concentration was added to each well of a 96 well tray.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A week later, the plates were examined and screened for those wells containing only single colonies.</text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Subsequently, cells were picked from positive wells and expanded in 24 well plate.</text></s></P><P><s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The established hybridomas were scaled up and cultured in serum-free media (SFM), enriched RPMI1640-Dulbecco's-Ham's F12 medium (eRDF) supplemented with RD-1 additives containing 9 µg ml−1 of insulin, 20 µg ml−1 of transferrin, 20 µM of ethanolamine and 25 nM of sodium selenite.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Purification of MAb</HEADER><P><s sid="61">MAb 1D5-3B-7 was purified using a protein G FF column (0.46 × 11 cm, Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, Uppsala, Sweden).</s> <s sid="62">The media containing the IgG was adjusted to pH 7 with 1 M Tris solution and loaded onto the column.</s> <s sid="63">After binding, the column was washed with 20 mM phosphate buffer (pH 7) and the adsorbed IgG was eluted with 100 mM of citrate buffer (pH 3).</s> <s sid="64">The eluted IgG was neutralized with 1 M Tris solution, then dialyzed against 5 changes of H2O for 3 days in 4 °C, and finally lyophilized.</s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>ELISA procedures</HEADER><P><s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A 100 µl of berberine–HSA (1 µg ml−1 in 50 mM carbonate buffer, pH 9.6) was allowed to adsorb onto the wells of a 96 well flat-bottomed polystyrene immunoplate (NUNC, Roskilde, Denmark) for 1 h, and washed three times with washing buffer, PBS containing 0.05percent Tween-20 (TPBS).</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The plate was treated with 300 µl of PBS containing 5percent skimmed milk (SPBS) for 1 h to reduce nonspecific adsorption, and washed three times with TPBS and reacted with 100 µl of MAb for 1 h.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The plate was washed three times with TPBS, then the MAb was combined with 100 µl of 1:1000 dilution of peroxidase-labelled anti-mouse IgG as the secondary antibody for 1 h.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After washing the plate three times with TPBS, 100 µl of 100 mM citrate buffer (pH 4.0) containing 0.003percent H2O2, and 0.3 mg ml−1 of 2,2′-azino-bis(3-ethylbenzothiazoline-6-sulfonic acid) diammonium salt, ABTS (Wako Pure Chemical Ind.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Ltd., Osaka, Japan) was added to each well, and the plate was incubated for 20 min.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The absorbance at 405 nm was measured using an immunoplate reader (ImmunoMini NJ-2300, NUNC, Roskilde, Denmark).</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All reactions were carried out at 37 °C.</text></s></P><P><s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Competitive ELISA was performed with almost the same protocol as direct ELISA except for one step.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After blocking and washing, 50 µl of various concentrations of berberine or related compound solutions dissolved in 10percent methanol were introduced into the wells of plate fixed berberine–HSA.</text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An equal volume of MAb solution was added to the wells, and incubated for 1 h.</text></s></P><P><s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For data analysis, absorbance values from standards were mathematically fitted to a four-parameter logistic equation: <EQN><EQ-S ID="s74">y = {(A − D)/[1 + (x/C)B]} + D</EQ-S></EQN>where y is the absorbance value, A is the maximum absorbance with no analyte present, B is the curve slope at the inflexion point, C is the x value at the inflexion point (corresponding to the analyte concentration that reduces absorbance to 50percent of the maximum, IC50), and D is the minimum absorbance.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Quantitative analysis of berberine and its related compounds by HPLC</HEADER><P><s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The HPLC system (Shimadzu, LC-10ADvp, Kyoto, Japan) was composed with dual pump, a Rheodyne 7725 injector, DGU-14A degasser and SPD-10Avp UV detector coupled to chromatopac C-R8A intergrator.</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The analysis was performed on Cosmosil column (4.6 id × 150 mm, 5C18-AR-II, Nacalai tesque, Kyoto, Japan) using a mobile phase composed of 0.1percent HCOOH:CH3CN (85:15, v/v) at a flow rate 1.0 ml min−1.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A 10 µl of aliquot of each sample was injected and monitored at 345 nm.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Crude medicines, herbal medicines and sample preparation</HEADER><P><s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp37" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Each 100.0 mg of powdered samples were sonicated in 3 ml of methanol for 30 min.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp38" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sample was centrifuged at 380 g for 5 min, and the supernatant was collected.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp39" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same procedure was repeated 4 times and the combined extract was adjusted to volume of 12 ml with methanol.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp40" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The adjusted sample solution was filtered with 0.45 µm membrane and diluted serially with H2O for analysis.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Synthesis of hapten for conjugates</HEADER><P><s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The specificity and selectivity of immunoassays are mainly determined by the antibody.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, the design of hapten, target compound-like molecules containing a functional group suitable for protein conjugate, is the key step in the development of an immunoassay technique for small molecules.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the case of berberine (MW 366), it is too small to be immunogenic and must be conjugated to a large carrier protein that will function as the primary immunogen.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, berberine lacks a reactive group such as NH2, COOH, OH, SH, CO or CHO for linkage to a protein.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met17" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>To overcome this problem, 9-O-carboxymethyl berberrubine preserved the chemical structure of berberine was designed for the hapten and synthesized following Iwasa's method<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit20"/> and Sadykov's method<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit21"/> (see Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met18" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The designed hapten and carrier protein were conjugated with a zero-length cross-linking procedure mediated by the water-soluble carbodiimide EDC to prevent the production of antibodies against the cross-linker bridge.<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit25"/></text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The carbodiimide first reacts with carboxylic groups on 9-O-carboxymethyl berberrubine to form a highly active O-acylisourea intermediate and the activated carboxylic group then reacts with a primary amine to form an amide bond, with release of the EDC mediator as a soluble isourea derivative.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Direct determination of hapten number in hapten–carrier protein conjugate by MALDI TOF MS</HEADER><P><s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met19" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>In order to confirm its immunogenicity, the hapten number in the berberine–carrier protein conjugate was determined by MALDI-TOF MS.</text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Using experimental results and a molecular weight of 66433 for BSA, the calculated value of the berberine component (MW 366) was m/z 1022, indicating at least 3 molecules of berberine conjugated with BSA.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This hapten number was estimated to be applicable for immunization.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The number of berberine moieties contained in the berberine–HSA conjugate was determined, by its spectrum, to be approximately 4 molecules.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Preparation of monoclonal antibody</HEADER><P><s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met20" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Spleen cells (3.77 × 108) from the mouse immunized with berberine–BSA were hybridized with myeloma cells (7.74 × 107).</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The number of well-grown hybridomas was 109 strains.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The cell fusion efficiency was 6.68percent (109 wells/1632 wells).</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The titer of all supernatants was investigated by direct ELISA and 17 strains were selected.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After scaling up for a week, 7 strains had high titers to berberine–BSA, but low titers to BSA.</text></s> <s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met21" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>From the strains producing antibodies of high titer and grown more rapidly, three strains were cloned twice by the limited dilution method.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met22" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Among 3 cloned strains, 1D5-3B-7 was chosen due to its reactivity and specificity for berberine.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met23" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The clone 1D5-3B-7 was grown in eRDF media giving anti-berberine MAb.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Characteristics of MAb 1D5-3B-7 against berberine</HEADER><P><s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met24" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The reactivity of MAb 1D5-3B-7 against berberine was determined by a direct ELISA.</text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met25" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The isotype of the secreted antibody was determined by using a mouse monoclonal antibody isotyping kit.</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>MAb 1D5-3B-7 was classified as IgG1 that had k light chain.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The reactivity of MAb was tested by direct ELISA using various concentrations (Fig. 2).</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Specificity and sensitivity of assay</HEADER><P><s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met26" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Specificity of MAb 1D5-3B-7 was estimated by cross-reactivity measurement according to Weiler and Zenk's equation.<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit26"/></text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The ELISA was not specific for berberine as showed in the cross-reactivity with structurally related compounds, coptisine, palmatine, but it did not react with other alkaloids (Table 1).</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This wide cross-reactivity is the major advantage of the antibody reagent used in this ELISA since berberine and structurally related alkaloids have the almost same pharmacological activity.<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit27"/><REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit28"/></text></s> <s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results show that the presence of charged residue in the berberine skeleton may be necessary as the epitope for MAb 1D5-3B-7.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, the phenol alkyl ether group in a molecule is also needed.</text></s></P><P><s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met27" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Various concentrations of berberine were incubated with MAb 1D5-3B-7 (80 ng ml−1) in an immunoplate adsorbed with berberine-HSA (1 µg ml−1).</text></s> <s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met28" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The calibration curve was obtained by averaging 12 individual standard curves performed in the course of berberine determination in samples.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The linear range of the assay was extended from 1.56 to 50 µg ml−1 with the correlation coefficient (R2) of 0.9956.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met29" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The detection limit was also estimated by IC90, the concentration of standard at which the initial binding was decreased by 10percent.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For berberine, the detection limit in this ELISA method was determined to be 780 ng ml−1.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Accuracy and variation of assay</HEADER><P><s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met30" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>In the standard curve for the competitive ELISA of berberine, the variations of repeatability from triplicate wells for each concentration (intra-assay) and the reproducibility from plate-to-plate (inter-assay) for four consecutive days were calculated by taking values in all aliquots of sample.</text></s> <s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Among ELISA runs, the coefficients of variation were below 15percent inter-assay and below 4percent intra-assay in most cases (data not shown).</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It becomes evident that intra-assay variations are lower than those of inter-assay.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although there are many factors such as coating step, the position of sample in immunoplate, multi-channel pipetter, edge effects due to evaporation, uneven temperature during incubation, and day-to-day variation, the results of accuracy and variation was acceptable.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Recovery by competitive ELISA in spiked samples</HEADER><P><s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met31" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>6.25, 12.5 and 25 µg ml−1 of samples was spiked at the zero spiked level.</text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met32" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The recovery was calculated by dividing the mean of all the obtained results using different ratios of added analyte, then multiplying by 100.</text></s> <s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As a result, the data ranged from 93.03 to 99.69percent (data not shown).</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Comparison of ELISA and HPLC determination of berberine and its related compounds in medicinal plants</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The correlation between the total concentration of berberine, coptisine and palmatine in crude extracts of individual plants determined by HPLC and ELISA was investigated (Table 2).</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Linear regression analysis of the plot gave acceptable results of which the equation was y = 0.9802x with correlation coefficients (R2) of 0.9383 (n = 4).</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Determination of the total concentration of berberine and its related compounds in various herbal medicines</HEADER><P><s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>After setting up assay validation and optimization, we determined the total concentration of berberine and related compounds in various herbal medicine samples by competitive ELISA.</text></s> <s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We concluded that it could be applied to the determination of the total concentration of berberine and related compounds in various herbal medicines (Table 3).</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Especially, it is an efficient analytical method for large scale certification in herbal medicines.</text></s></P><P><s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In conclusion, the ELISA method described in this study can be applied as an analytical tool for determining the levels of berberine in commercial products, either as a single crude drug or in combination with other crude drugs, to establish one of the primary criteria for quality and conformity of herbal medicines.</text></s> <s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Although not perfectly suited for the analysis of crude drugs and traditional Chinese medicines, the sensitivity and selectivity of ELISA are sufficient to determine berberine and its related compounds which have similar pharmacological activities.</text></s> <s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To our knowledge, this is the first approach to immunoassay using MAb against berberine and its related compounds for the quantitative determination.</text></s> <s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We have been attempting to apply MAb for the eastern blotting procedure for identification of berberine type alkaloids in plant and animal tissue as previous reported<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit29"/> and these results will be reported elsewhere.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV></BODY></PAPER>