<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312769a" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Phosphonate ligands encourage a Platonic relationship between cobalt(ii) and alkali metal ions</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Two new cobalt(ii) cages are reported where the metal core has a high symmetry related to a Platonic solid; the choice of alkali metal used in the base used for deprotonation appears to influence the resulting structures.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER/><P><s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The number of new polymetallic paramagnetic cages structurally characterised continues to grow, seemingly exponentially.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/></text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>One feature is the comparatively irregular structures often found – which contrasts with the orderly behaviour of the metal carbonyl clusters, where the structures appear to obey rules and often the metal vertices form a fragment of a metallic lattice.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The seeming chaos of the paramagnetic cages is both intriguing and challenging.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Still more extraordinary are the very large polyoxometallate cages reported by Müller<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/> and Pope:<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit4"/> here it can be possible to identify fragments that repeat between structures, and form the “blocks” from which the cage is constructed, but where the overall structure remains incommensurate.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There are major exceptions, perhaps the most exciting being “Keplerate” reported by Müller and co-workers,<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit5"/> where the thirty Fe(iii) centres lie on the vertices of an Archimedean solid, the icosidodecahedron.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Here we report two smaller clusters where the metal vertices lie on the vertices of Platonic solids including the tetrahedron, octahedron and icosahedron.</text></s></P><P><s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Phosphonates are rarely used in making polymetallic cage complexes, largely due to the extreme insolubility of the metal phosphonates.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Zubieta has solved this problem for vanadates by use of solvathermal conditions,<REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit6"/> while Chandrasekhar has reported an interesting dodecanuclear copper(ii) cage by using a co-ligand (3,5-dimethylpyrazole) to increase solubility.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit7"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Recently we have shown phosphonates can be used to link trinuclear iron(iii) cages into larger arrays.<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit8"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Here we report cobalt(ii) chemistry, related to the Chandrasekhar approach, but using deprotonated 6-chloro-2-pyridone (Hchp) as the co-ligand.</text></s></P><P><s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hydrated cobalt chloride (2 mmol) was dissolved in MeOH (25 ml), and Hchp (3.2 mmol), PhPO3H2 (0.85 mmol) and a 0.5M NaOMe solution in methanol (10 ml) was added, giving a deep purple solution.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solution was stirred for 6 h, filtered and the solvent removed in vacuo to give a purple solid.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Recrystallization from MeCN/Et2O gave deep purple crystals of [Co6Na8(chp)12(O3PPh)4(MeCN)4] 1 in a yield of 50percent.</text></s></P><P><s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Structural characterisation shows formation of a regular structure (Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The four P atoms from phenylphosphonates are found at the alternate corners of a cube, with Na atoms at the other corners – the Na atoms therefore describe a tetrahedron.</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The six Co(ii) ions are found above each face of this central cube – hence forming an octahedron of cobalt centres.</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The final four Na atoms lie above four of the edges of the cube, lowering the symmetry of the assembly of P, Na and Co to D2d – which is non-crystallographic.</text></s></P><P><s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The four phosphonates in 1 show the 7.322 bridging mode (Harris notation<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit10"/>) – which is unusual.</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The µ3-O atom bridges two Na and one Co, while the two µ2-oxygens bridge between one Na and one Co site.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The chp ligands show the 3.21 or 3.31 bridging modes, chelating to a cobalt site and additionally binding to either one or two Na atoms.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The cobalt sites are either six- or five-coordinate, with irregular geometries, while the coordination of Na ions is still more irregular.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The four Na sites within the cube are six-coordinate, while the four “capping” Na sites are four-coordinate.</text></s></P><P><s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The involvement of sodium in 1 suggested that variation of the alkali metal cation might generate further new structures.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore in a similar reaction, hydrated cobalt chloride (2 mmol) was dissolved in MeOH (25 ml) and Hchp (4 mmol), PhPO3H2 (0.33 mmol) and 1M LiOMe solution in MeOH (4.7 ml) was added.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The solution was stirred for 6 h, filtered and the solvent removed in vacuo to give a purple solid.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Recrystallization from EtOAc/hexane gave deep purple crystals of [Co6Li9(chp)14(PO4)Cl4(Hchp)4) 2 in low, but reproducible yield, ca.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>5percent.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A fine purple powder is precipitated shortly after the crystals.</text></s></P><P><s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The structure, which has crystallographic three-fold symmetry, is entirely unexpected (Fig. 2).</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the centre is a bridging phosphate, which adopts the 12.3333 bridging mode: one O-atoms binds to three Co atoms, while the others each bind to three lithium centres.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The twelve metal centres bound to the PO43– lie on the vertices of an icosahedron (Fig. 3).</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The metal–metal contacts within this polyhedron vary with Li⋯Li contacts lying in the range 3.03 to 3.28 Å, the Co⋯Co contact 3.22 Å and the Co⋯Li contacts ranging from 3.33 and 3.77 Å.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The presence of the phosphate must be due to decomposition of the phenylphosphonic acid used in the reaction – and this is reproducible.</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Phosphate is rarely found bound to metals in molecular complexes of the 3d-metals due to the insolubility of metal phosphate phases.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In situ formation of phosphate by decomposition of a ligand is allowing its incorporation in 2, but unfortunately this also contributes to the low yield.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Formation of phosphate may account for the purple powder that is deposited almost immediately after the crystals are formed.</text></s></P><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The final three Co(ii) centres are found outside the icosahedron, lying on the points of an equilateral triangle.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Four µ3-chloride ions are also found; these lie on the points of a tetrahedron, with three bridging between one Co and two Li atoms, and the fourth (which lies on the three-fold axis) bridging three Li centres.</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Li centres are all four-coordinate with tetrahedral geometries while the Co centres are all six-coordinate with distorted octahedral geometries.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This distortion is chiefly due to the presence of chelating chp ligands, with a narrow “bite” angle; the pyridonates all show the 2.21 binding mode, while the four Hchp ligands present are 2.20 bridging.</text></s></P><P><s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results suggest two new paths to explore.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The extreme flexibility of the phosphonate ligands clearly supports formation of new clusters with surprisingly high symmetry: such high symmetry has led to new physics<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit11"/> for the Keplerate phases and therefore this path is worth exploring further.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The in situ formation of phosphate suggests a method of inclusion of phosphate as a “templating” agent for formation of new cages.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Clearly our synthetic approach for the latter chemistry needs to be improved, probably by using less stable phosphonate ligands in the reactions and by examining more forcing conditions.</text></s></P><P><s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This work was supported by the EPSRC (UK).</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>