<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b312329d" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The development of an environmentally benign synthesis of sildenafil citrate (Viagra™) and its assessment by Green Chemistry metrics</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The process development and scale-up of the sildenafil citrate process is reviewed.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Key environmental metrics are reported at several time points during the development process.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Significant achievements during the development of sildenafil citrate were (i) discovering a convergent, efficient synthetic route (ii) designing 7 process steps so that there was no extractive work-up in any step (iii) implementing efficient solvent recovery early in the product's commercial lifetime.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The result of this work is that the E-factor for the process is very low with just 6 Kg of waste per kilogram of product compared with an industry average of 25–100 Kg.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Pfizer received the 2003 UK Award for Green Chemical Technology (Best Process category) for the sildenafil citrate process.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Sildenafil citrate is a selective inhibitor of phosphodiesterase 5 (PDE5) and was the first agent with this mode of action for the treatment of male erectile dysfunction (a disease that was more commonly known as male impotence).</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This new drug was approved for prescription use within the United States, the European Union and Japan during 1998 and immediately became a major seller, achieving sales of more than $1 billion during its first year on the market.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>With such a rapid sales take off it was critical that the environmental performance of the synthesis was good from the outset.</text></s></P><P><s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A crude assessment of the environmental performance of a synthesis is provided by the E-factor<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1a"/><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit1b"/> and Sheldon<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit1a"/><REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit1b"/> has given broad levels of environmental performance for different categories of the Chemical Industry as shown in Table 1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There are many reasons why waste levels are generally higher for pharmaceutical compounds.</text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For example, typical syntheses involve complex molecules with demanding quality standards, often requiring batch processing; there are greater regulatory constraints and in general high value, low volume products are being made.</text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Some earlier publications by GlaxoSmithKline have looked at assessing general reaction types by Green Chemistry metrics.<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This paper assesses a specific process, the sildenafil citrate process, using various Green Chemistry metrics, including the E-factor proposed by Sheldon, and examines how the process compares with industry norms.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Data at various points in the chemical development process are also reported.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Medicinal chemistry route and “quick fixes” for early scale-up</HEADER><P><s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The medicinal chemistry route is shown in Scheme 1.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit4"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The first task of the process chemist was to prepare a few kilograms of material for early toxicology studies.</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The following four changes were made for early batches to improve the environmental performance of the synthesis.</text></s></P><P><s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• The removal of the tin chloride reduction.</text></s> <s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Tin is a heavy metal and a major environmental polluter.</text></s></P><P><s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• The use of stoichiometric quantities of thionyl chloride in a solvent, rather than thionyl chloride as solvent in the preparation of compound (2).</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is much safer and has a reduced environmental impact.</text></s></P><P><s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• The elimination of hydrogen peroxide from the synthesis.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hydrogen peroxide causes burns on contact with skin and is a fire and transportation hazard especially in contact with organic materials.</text></s></P><P><s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• The use of thionyl chloride rather than oxalyl chloride for the preparation of 2-ethoxybenzoyl chloride.</text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This change gave an improvement in worker safety by avoiding carbon monoxide emissions.</text></s></P><P><s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac18" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Medicinal chemists employed a tin chloride reduction because standard reduction by hydrogenation was not effective.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Investigation showed that the failure of the hydrogenation was due to trace levels of sulfur impurities, from the previous thionyl chloride reaction, poisoning the hydrogenation reaction.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Careful control of these sulfur impurities (for example, switching to stoichiometric thionyl chloride use) allowed tin to be removed from the process and replaced with a simple catalytic hydrogenation reaction.</text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac19" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Catalytic hydrogenations are among the cleanest environmental chemical steps.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac20" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For a reduction of a nitro group to an amine, the only by-product is water and there are recovery options for solvent and catalyst.</text></s></P><P><s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac21" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The medicinal chemistry method to cyclise compound (4) to the pyrazolopyrimidinone (5) used an aqueous alcoholic solution of sodium hydroxide and hydrogen peroxide in 72percent yield.</text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac22" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A literature review of alternative cyclisation methods revealed that such reactions had only previously been performed in moderate yield (30–70percent).<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac23" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It was found that by employing KOBut in tBuOH in the cyclisation reaction, a 100percent isolated yield was obtained with no impurities detected.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac24" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Finding this very clean and high yielding reaction impacted on the way the commercial route was designed.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Selection and development of the commercial route</HEADER><P><s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac25" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A summary of the two routes is outlined in Scheme 2.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The flow diagrams in Scheme 2 clearly show that the strategic advantages of the commercial route were as follows:</text></s></P><P><s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• Greater convergency</text></s></P><P><s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• The clean cyclisation reaction is now at the end of the synthesis in the final bond-forming step.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac27" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The potentially toxic materials now occur near the start of the synthesis.</text></s></P><P><s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac26" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• The environmental and scale-up issues associated with the chlorosulfonation step (i.e. large volumes of aqueous acidic waste that require neutralisation and increased levels of hydrolysis during increased quench time on a larger scale) are reduced by placing the chlorosulfonation reaction earlier in the synthesis.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac28" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A simple, low molecular weight starting material (2-ethoxybenzoic acid) is used, hence less chlorosulfonic acid is needed and the problem is much reduced.</text></s></P><P><s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac29" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Once selected, the commercial route was subjected to further, detailed development and the optimised synthesis is outlined in Scheme 3.<REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit6"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac30" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>2-Ethoxybenzoic acid is chlorosulfonated using chlorosulfonic acid along with 1 mol of thionyl chloride, to ensure that the intermediate sulfonic acid is converted to the sulfonyl chloride.</text></s> <s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>2-Ethoxybenzoic acid is a low melting solid (mp 19–20 °C) and hence could be used as a melt, allowing the use of relatively low volumes of chlorosulfonic acid and thionyl chloride as there were no solubilisation issues.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac31" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Following aqueous quench, the product is isolated as a water wet sulfonyl chloride.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For simplicity and efficiency, the sulfonyl chloride is then resuspended in water and reacted with N-methylpiperazine.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the end of the reaction, the pH is adjusted and the sulfonamide (6) is collected by filtration.</text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac32" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hence, no organic solvent is used for the preparation of the sulfonamide.</text></s></P><P><s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac33" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As mentioned earlier, the original procedure to convert pyrazole (1) into the amide (2) used a neat reaction in thionyl chloride.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The introduction of toluene as a heat sink/solvent both increased the safety of the process and allowed reduction of the levels of thionyl chloride to 1.2–1.6 equivalents.</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac34" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The toluene in this reaction is recovered and reused.</text></s></P><P><s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac35" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Heterogeneous hydrogenation in ethyl acetate was used to convert the nitropyrazole (2) to the amine (3).</text></s> <s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Activation of the acid (6) was examined with a number of reagents including thionyl chloride, oxalyl chloride and N,N′-carbonyldiimidazole (CDI).</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>CDI was selected, despite its higher cost because this reagent:</text></s></P><P><s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• Provided clean, robust chemistry and high quality product.</text></s></P><P><s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• Allowed all three reactions (hydrogenation, activation and acylation) to be combined.</text></s></P><P><s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• Enabled a single solvent to be employed (ethyl acetate), allowing simple solvent recovery with low energy use.</text></s></P><P><s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• Avoided VOC emissions (EtCl) from the interaction of either thionyl chloride or oxalyl chloride with ethyl acetate.</text></s></P><P><s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• Provided a simple process – mix streams, concentrate and filter.</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This simplicity led to low energy use.</text></s></P><P><s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac36" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>• High chemical yield, (90percent) over three chemical steps (subsequently optimised to 96percent).</text></s></P><P><s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac37" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The resulting coupled product (7) is then cyclised with t-BuOH and t-BuOK.</text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac38" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The process is run at high concentration (2.5–3.75 L Kg−1) in order to minimise environmental waste.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac39" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At the end of the reaction, water is added and the pH adjusted to the isoelectric point to precipitate pure sildenafil, which is collected by filtration.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For Viagra™, the citrate salt is required.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The process to covert sildenafil to sildenafil citrate has been carefully designed to give both a high yield and high quality.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac40" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A 98–100percent yield is routinely obtained for this step.</text></s> <s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac41" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>By 1997 the overall yield from the pyrazole (1) to sildenafil citrate had risen to 75percent, and the high yields late in the synthesis minimised the environmental impact of the earlier steps.</text></s></P><P><s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac42" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Once the steps were developed, diligent solvent recovery was required to fully optimise the environmental performance.</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac43" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Recovery of toluene and ethyl acetate was introduced in 1998, the year Viagra™ was launched, and production scale trials for the recovery of 2-butanone are now complete.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A summary of the solvent usage at various stages of development is given in Fig. 1.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac44" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Of particular note is the complete elimination of chlorinated solvents and the elimination of highly volatile solvents such as diethyl ether, methylene chloride, methanol and acetone.</text></s> <s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac45" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The elimination of these highly volatile solvents reduces the atmospheric emissions as will be seen later.</text></s></P><P><s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A further improvement in the synthesis (described in Scheme 3) was the replacement of t-butanol.</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This solvent is completely water soluble in all proportions and is difficult to recover for reuse.</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac46" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There is a continued drive for improved environmental performance and t-butanol will be switched to another reaction solvent that can be recovered.</text></s> <s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac47" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This new process was developed and optimised in Ringaskiddy and has been demonstrated in the production plant in Ireland.</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac48" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When fully implemented this will give the final optimised solvent usage of 4 L Kg−1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A more detailed environmental analysis of the optimised medicinal chemistry synthesis (1994), the 1997 commercial route and the future target follows, using such measures as atom economy, reaction mass efficiency, chemical yield, organic waste, aqueous waste, atmospheric emissions, energy usage and the E-factor.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac49" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The original medicinal chemistry process (1990) is not analysed here, since it was only ever intended for laboratory scale synthesis.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Atom economy, reaction mass efficiency and chemical yield</HEADER><P><s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac50" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The concept of atom economy was first introduced by Barry Trost<REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit7"/> as a prompt to synthetic chemists to pursue “greener chemistry”.</text></s> <s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The method of calculating atom economy was kept deliberately simple and is a percentage of how much of the reactants remain in the final product.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Hence, atom economy ignores reaction yield and reagent excess.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>It also does not account for solvent usage.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac51" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further information on how to calculate atom economy can be found in Green Chemistry.<REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit3"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Reaction Mass Efficiency (RME)<REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit2"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit3"/> is a more sophisticated measure of “greenness” which allows for the effect of yield and the excesses of reagent used.</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>RME does not account for solvent usage.</text></s></P><P><s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mod" conceptID="Mod1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For a generic reaction A + B = C</text></s></P><P><s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The atom economy, reaction mass efficiency and chemical yields for the sildenafil citrate processes in 1994 (optimised medicinal chemistry route), 1997 (commercial route) and the future target (commercial route) are shown in Tables 2 to 4.</text></s></P><P><s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As can be seen from the data, the atom economy of the process has remained essentially constant over time.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Improvements have been made in yield and through a greater degree of convergency in the synthesis, but these are not measured by atom economy.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In contrast, there was a substantial improvement in both RME and chemical yield between 1994 and 1997 when the new route was introduced.</text></s> <s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There has been a further significant incremental improvement since 1997.</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A summary of the data in Tables 2–4 is given in Fig. 2.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Organic waste, aqueous waste, atmospheric emissions and energy usage</HEADER><P><s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The levels of organic waste, aqueous waste and atmospheric emissions for the sildenafil citrate process at three time points are shown in Fig. 3.</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The three time points are 1994, when the optimised medicinal chemistry was being used, 1997, following the switch to the commercial process and the future target, which includes solvent recovery, and switching from t-butanol to a solvent that can be recovered.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac52" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Each time point is given as a percentage of the 1994 process.</text></s></P><P><s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The organic and aqueous wastes are actually measured; the atmospheric emissions are estimated from a modelling process using Batch Plus.</text></s> <s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It can be seen that for aqueous waste, there was a large reduction between 1994 and 1997 when the new route was introduced while subsequent improvements will be incremental.</text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This shows the importance of route selection in controlling and eliminating waste.</text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>For the organic waste there was again a large reduction between 1994 and 1997 upon introduction of the commercial route.</text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, there was a further large reduction post 1997 due to the impact of introducing solvent recovery operations and reuse in the process.</text></s> <s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Interestingly, vapour emissions have also been reduced over time but by a much smaller amount.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Energy use was also estimated by the “Batch Plus” software and it was found that there was a 35percent reduction between 1994 and 1997.</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac53" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There were two possible reasons why reductions in vapour emissions and energy usage were smaller:</text></s></P><P><s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>1.</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>There is a significant level of solvent stripping performed in the commercial process to maximise the yield.</text></s></P><P><s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>2.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Parameters such as yield, aqueous waste and organic waste were actively managed and followed by the chemistry team as the process was developed, whereas volatile emissions were calculated retrospectively.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac54" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is interesting to speculate whether volatile emissions and energy use would have been lower if the chemistry team had used Batch Plus in real time to monitor volatile emissions and energy use as the process was being developed.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>The E-factor</HEADER><P><s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac55" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The future target process generates 4 L Kg−1 of organic waste along with 2 Kg Kg−1 of salts (mainly from neutralising chlorosulfonation waste).</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hence the total kilos of waste per kilo active of sildenafil citrate is around 6 Kg Kg−1.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The performance of the sildenafil citrate process against industry norms is shown in Table 5.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sildenafil citrate process is more similar to a bulk chemical or an efficient fine chemical synthesis in terms of its waste generation.</text></s> <s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However the annual volumes produced are in the lower end of the range for a Pharmaceutical given in Table 5.</text></s></P><P><s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As total annual waste is the multiple of the E-factor and the annual product volume it can be seen that the sildenafil citrate process produces exceptionally low levels of waste per annum.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Green Chemistry metrics have been presented at different time points in the development of the sildenafil citrate process.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>With the exception of atom economy, there was an improvement in the environmental performance as the process was developed, and for the most important measures there was a major improvement.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The future target for the E-factor is 6 (for 7 process steps) which is significantly less than the industry standard (25–100).</text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When both E-factor and the relatively low volume (of this high value, relatively complicated chemical product) are taken into account, the amount of waste produced per year is extremely low.</text></s> <s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac56" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Pfizer received the UK Award for Green Chemical Technology for the sildenafil citrate process in 2003.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac57" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Details of the commercial route to sildenafil citrate can be found in reference .<REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit6"/></text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac58" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Details of the 1990 medicinal chemistry synthesis can be found in reference .<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit4"/></text></s> <s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Aqueous waste, organic waste, atom economy and reaction mass efficiency were determined by the Batch Plus program then reality checked by human calculation.</text></s> <s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Energy usage and atmospheric emissions were estimated using the Batch Plus software.</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Batch Plus is a recipe based modelling program designed for simulating pharmaceutical/chemical batch operations.</text></s> <s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac59" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Batch Plus has the capability of performing process mass balance calculations based on a specified amount of product, and estimating the corresponding aqueous and organic waste stream amounts and atmospheric emissions.</text></s> <s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Batch Plus was shown to be a quick and efficient tool for assigning green chemistry metrics as the process was developed from laboratory to production scale.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>