<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b313094k" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Immunoassay using probe-labelling immunogold nanoparticles with silver staining enhancement via surface-enhanced Raman scattering</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>This paper reports a novel immunoassay based on surface-enhanced Raman scattering (SERS) and immunogold labelling with silver staining enhancement.</text></s> <s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Immunoreactions between immunogold colloids modified by a Raman-active probe molecule (e.g., 4-mercaptobenzoic acid) and antigens, which were captured by antibody-assembled chips such as silicon or quartz, were detected via SERS signals of Raman-active probe molecule.</text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj3" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>All the self-assembled steps were subjected to the measurements of ultraviolet-visible (UV-vis) spectra to monitor the formation of a sandwich structure onto a substrate.</text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The immunoassay was performed by a sandwich structure consisting of three layers.</text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The first layer was composed of immobilized antibody molecules of mouse polyclonal antibody against Hepatitis B virus surface antigen (PAb) on a silicon or quartz substrate.</text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The second layer was the complementary Hepatitis B virus surface antigen (Antigen) molecules captured by PAb on the substrate.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The third layer was composed of the probe-labelling immunogold nanoparticles, which were modified by mouse monoclonal antibody against Hepatitis B virus surface antigen (MAb) and 4-mercaptobenzoic acid (MBA) as the Raman-active probe on the surface of gold colloids.</text></s> <s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>After silver staining enhancement, the antigen is identified by a SERS spectrum of MBA.</text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A working curve of the intensity of a SERS signal at 1585 cm−1 due to the ν8a aromatic ring vibration of MBA versus the concentration of analyte (Antigen) was obtained and the non-optimized detection limit for the Hepatitis B virus surface antigen was found to be as low as 0.5 µg mL−1.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Introduction</HEADER><P><s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Raman spectroscopy is one of the most useful methods to investigate biomolecules and biological materials because it can provide rich structural information as well as quantitative and qualitative information by sharp Raman bands in a nondestructive manner.</text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Raman spectroscopy can be almost freely applied to aqueous samples and samples under physiological conditions.</text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, the signals of conventional Raman spectra are too weak to be widely used for highly sensitive quantitative and qualitative analyses.</text></s> <s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Surface-enhanced Raman scattering (SERS) and surface-enhanced resonance Raman scattering (SERRS) can readily enhance Raman signals by a factor of 103–14,<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1a"/><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit1b"/><REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit2a"/><REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit2b"/> and many single molecule Raman spectra have recently been acquired from an adsorbate on a single nanoparticle.<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit3"/><REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit4"/></text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This remarkable progress in SERS has broadened the applications of Raman spectroscopy in biology and biomedicine.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit1a"/><REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit1b"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit5"/><REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit6a"/><REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit6b"/><REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit6c"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit6d"/><REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit6e"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Immunoassay, which is based on a specific interaction between an antigen and a complementary antibody, is a powerful analytical tool for biochemical analyses, clinical diagnosis, and environmental monitoring.</text></s> <s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Many analytical methods, such as surface plasmon resonance (SPR),<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit7a"/><REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit7b"/><REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit7c"/><REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit7d"/> atomic force microscopy (AFM)<REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit8a"/><REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit8b"/><REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit8c"/><REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit8d"/><REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit8e"/><REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit8f"/> and quartz crystal microbalance (QCM),<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit9a"/><REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit9b"/> have been used for a direct measurement of the antigens binding to antibody molecules immobilized on a substrate.</text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Rapid, sensitive, and accurate methods for immunoassays have always been the goals pursued by scientists.</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, many kinds of conventional labelling immunoassay techniques, such as enzyme immunoassay (EIA),<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit10a"/><REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit10b"/><REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit10c"/> fluorescence<REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit11"/><REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit12"/> and chemiluminescence,<REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit13a"/><REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit13b"/><REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit13c"/><REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit13d"/> have widely been applied to increase the detection sensitivity of analytes.</text></s></P><P><s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Recently, metallic colloid nanoparticles (e.g. gold and silver colloids) have also been successfully applied to the label technologies because of their easily controllable-size distribution, long-term stability and friendly biocompatibility with antibodies, antigen proteins, DNA and RNA.<REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit14a"/><REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit14b"/><REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit14c"/><REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit14d"/><REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit16"/><REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit17"/><REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit18a"/><REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit18b"/><REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit19"/><REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit20"/></text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Many novel methods using metallic colloid nanoparticles have been developed, such as colloidal gold labelling immunoassay systems detected with transmission electron microscopy (TEM),<REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit15"/><REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit16"/> scanning electron microscopy (SEM),<REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit17"/> or even by naked eye,<REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit18a"/><REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit18b"/><REF ID="R-51" REFID="cit19"/> imaging of gold colloidal particles by conjugating the immune complexes on conductive substrates with scanning tunneling microscope (STM),<REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit20"/> and so on.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Moreover, noble metallic colloid particles with proper size and roughness are very suitable for SERS substrates,<REF ID="R-53" REFID="cit21a"/><REF ID="R-54" REFID="cit21b"/><REF ID="R-55" REFID="cit21c"/><REF ID="R-56" REFID="cit21d"/><REF ID="R-57" REFID="cit21e"/><REF ID="R-58" REFID="cit21f"/> and there is great interest in the coupling of the nano-labelling techniques with the SERS technique.</text></s> <s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Dou et al<REF ID="R-59" REFID="cit22"/>. developed a new enzyme immunoassay based on SERRS.</text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>In their system, antibody immobilized on a solid substrate reacts with antigen, which binds with another antibody labelled with peroxidase.</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>If this immunocomplex is subjected to the reaction with o-phenylenediamine and hydrogen peroxide, azoaniline is generated.<REF ID="R-60" REFID="cit22"/></text></s> <s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="Yes"/><text>This azo compound is adsorbed on a silver colloid, giving strong SERRS signals.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Ni et al<REF ID="R-61" REFID="cit23"/>. proposed an immunoassay readout method based on SERS in a dual analyte sandwich assay.</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>This method exploits SERS-derived signals from three different extrinsic reporter molecules that are coimmobilized with biospecific species on gold colloids.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="No"/><text>However, it was found that the excitation coefficient of a surface plasmon band for gold particles is approximately 4 times lower than that for silver particles with the same size.<REF ID="R-62" REFID="cit24"/></text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As a SERS substrate, the Raman enhanced ability of gold nanoparticles is about 100 times lower than that of silver nanoparticles.<REF ID="R-63" REFID="cit25"/><REF ID="R-64" REFID="cit26"/></text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Recently, Kim et al<REF ID="R-65" REFID="cit27"/>. demonstrated that isocyanide and biotin-derivatized silver nanoparticles with the size from 150 nm to 3 µm can be used via SERS as very effective sensing units between avidin and biotin moieties.</text></s> <s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="Old" advantage="No"/><text>However, problems of how to enhance the solubility, physicochemical stability and quantum efficiency of silver colloid nanoparticles after the surface modification remained.<REF ID="R-66" REFID="cit27"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In the present study, we have combined the immunogold nano-labelling and silver staining enhancement method with the SERS technique to develop a new immunoassay method.</text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We have used this method for the quantitative detection of Hepatitis B virus surface antigen (Antigen) by means of a sort of self-assembled sandwich structure immobilized on a silicon or quartz substrate (see Scheme 1).</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Immunoreactions between immunogold colloids modified by 4-mercaptobenzoic acid (MBA) and Antigen, captured by the antibody-assembled chips, are detected via SERS signals of MBA after silver staining enhancement.</text></s> <s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>The advantages of gold colloid nanoparticles, such as their long-term stability, easily controllable-size distribution and friendly biocompatibility with antibody molecules, are utilized to make the nano-labels.</text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Raman-active molecules as the probes are also fixed onto the gold nanoparticles for the SERS detection.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>Thus, the problem of the stability of silver colloid described above has been solved and the reproducibility of the detection has been improved.</text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="New" advantage="Yes"/><text>The silver staining enhancement method used in the present system has markedly increased SERS signals, and removed the flaws of gold nanoparticles in the Raman enhanced ability.</text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met8" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>The ultraviolet-visible (UV-vis) spectra have been used to monitor the immobilization of the MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles and the step of silver staining (in Scheme 1).</text></s> <s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A series of SERS spectra for the immunoassay, measured for the MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles with the silver staining enhancement, have shown that the detection limit of Hepatitis B virus surface antigen is as low as 0.5 µg mL−1.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Experimental section</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Reagents</HEADER><P><s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Hepatitis B virus surface antigen (Antigen), mouse monoclonal antibody against Hepatitis B virus surface antigen (MAb) and mouse polyclonal antibody against Hepatitis B virus surface antigen (PAb) were obtained from Kunming Yuda Monoclonal Antibody Technology Center, Yunnan University, P. R. China.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>HAuCl4·4H2O, trisodium citrate, and glutaraldehyde (GA) were purchased from Shanghai Chemical Reagent Co. Ltd. Goat immunoglobulin (IgG), bovine serum albumin (BSA), l-lysine, (3-amino-propyl)trimethoxysilane (APTMS), 4-mercaptobenzoic acid (MBA) and tris(hydroxymethyl)aminomethane (Tris) were obtained from Aldrich.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The other chemicals were all purchased from Beijing Chemical Reagent Co. Ltd. All the chemicals used were of analytical grade.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Solutions</HEADER><P><s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A borate buffer solution (2 mM, pH = 9.0), a PBS buffer solution (KH2PO4/K2HPO4, 150 mM, pH = 7.6), a Tris/HCl buffer solution (0.1 M, pH = 7.0) and a MBA solution (1.0 × 10−3 mol L−1) were employed in the present study.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>MBA and APTMS were dissolved in methanol.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Preparation of the MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles (Scheme 1)</HEADER><P><s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The probe-labelling immunogold nanoparticles were prepared by a process consisting of four steps.<REF ID="R-67" REFID="cit28"/></text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>First, gold colloid was prepared following the procedure developed by Frens.<REF ID="R-68" REFID="cit29"/></text></s> <s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All the glassware used were cleaned with freshly prepared aqua regia (HCl:HNO3 3:1 v/v).</text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Immediately after 100 mL of a 10−3 mol L−1 HAuCl4 solution started boiling, 9.34 mL of a 1percent (m/m) trisodium citrate aqueous solution was added to it.</text></s> <s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After the mixture had boiled for 20 min, the heating was stopped.</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>An UV-vis spectrum of the gold colloids thus prepared was measured; a plasmon resonance peak appeared at 518 nm.</text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The average diameter of gold particles was estimated to be ∼13 nm according to their TEM images.</text></s></P><P><s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the second step, 2.5 µL of the MBA solution (1 × 10−3 mol L−1) was added as a Raman-active probe to 1.0 mL of the gold colloids, and then the mixture was reacted for 12 h under stirring.</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>MBA was adsorbed onto the surface of gold particles with thiol groups.<REF ID="R-69" REFID="cit30"/><REF ID="R-70" REFID="cit31"/><REF ID="R-71" REFID="cit23"/></text></s> <s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then, the MBA modified gold colloids were rinsed by centrifugation and resuspension with a borate buffer solution (2 mM, pH = 9.0) twice.</text></s></P><P><s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As the third step, 10 µL of a MAb solution (1.0 mg mL−1) was added to 1 mL of the MBA-labelling colloid, and the solution was well mixed.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>MAb was adsorbed on the exposed portions of the colloid surface by static and hydrophobic interactions.<REF ID="R-72" REFID="cit28"/></text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The amount of MAb added to the MBA-labelling colloid is 50percent more than the minimum amount for coating the unmodified portion of the colloid surface.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After MAb reacting with the MBA-labelling gold colloid for 1 h at room temperature, MAb was separated from the solution by centrifugation at 10000 rpm for 10 min, and then the modified colloid was resuspended in 1 mL of a borate buffer solution (2 mM, pH = 9.0).</text></s></P><P><s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the last step, to assure that no space was left around the surface of gold colloids, 10 µL of a BSA (2percent m/m) solution was added to the above mentioned MBA-labelling immunogold colloid, to occupy the uncoated places, for 40 min at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then, the mixture was centrifuged and resuspended in 1 mL of a borate buffer solution.</text></s> <s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The MBA-labelling immunogold colloid usually kept stable for three days when stored at 4 °C.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Immobilization of PAb on a silicon or quartz chip<REF ID="R-73" REFID="cit13d"/>.</HEADER><P><s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Scheme 1 illustrates the process during which antibodies are immobilized on a silicon or quartz chip.</text></s> <s sid="65"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All the silicon and quartz chips (0.8 cm × 1.0 cm) were sonicated in water, ethanol, acetone, chloroform, acetone, ethanol, and water, sequentially to clean before use.</text></s> <s sid="66"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The cleaned chips were treated with a freshly prepared piranha solution (98percent H2SO4:30percent H2O2 = 3:1 v/v) at 90 °C for 10 min, and rinsed with a large volume of ultrapure water.</text></s> <s sid="67"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Having been dried with nitrogen gas, the substrates were cured in a drying oven at 100 °C for 30 min.</text></s> <s sid="68"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In this way, a surface with hydroxyl groups emerged on the chips.</text></s></P><P><s sid="69"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The first step for the immobilization of PAb on the chips is to prepare silanized substrates.</text></s> <s sid="70"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The chips with the hydroxy surface were immersed in a dilute solution of APTMS in dried methanol (5percent in volume) for 24 h at room temperature in the dark.</text></s> <s sid="71"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then, the substrates were rinsed with a large amount of methanol and cleaned by sonication for 5 min to remove the physisorbed APTMS.</text></s> <s sid="72"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The chips were rinsed with ultrapure water, and then dried with nitrogen gas.</text></s> <s sid="73"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, the silanized substrates were kept in a drying oven at 120 °C for 30 min.</text></s></P><P><s sid="74"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The second step is to add GA onto the APTMS silanized substrates to form an APTMS–GA surface (Scheme 1).</text></s> <s sid="75"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The silanized substrates were washed with a borate buffer solution, and immersed into a borate buffer solution containing 2.5percent (v/v) GA for 1 h at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="76"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The amino groups on the APTMS silanized chips reacted with the aldehyde groups of GA, yielding the APTMS–GA surface.</text></s> <s sid="77"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Having been rinsed in a borate buffer solution, the chips with the APTMS–GA surface were dried with nitrogen gas.</text></s></P><P><s sid="78"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The third step is to immobilize PAb on the APTMS–GA surface, and then to form an APTMS–GA–PAb surface on the chips (Scheme 1).</text></s> <s sid="79"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>40 µL of a borate buffer solution containing PAb (0.05 mg mL−1) was dropped onto the 1.0 × 0.8 cm2 GA-active chip surface and extended uniformly.</text></s> <s sid="80"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>PAb reacted with the aldehyde groups for 12 h at 4 °C and then the surface was rinsed with ultrapure water to remove the residual PAb and dried.</text></s> <s sid="81"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The aldehyde groups remaining after PAb attachment were blocked with 10 mg mL−1 l-lysine for 2 h at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="82"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>At last, the silicon or quartz chips with the APTMS–GA–PAb surface were carefully washed, and then stored in a 0.1 M Tris/HCl buffer solution at 4 °C until use.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>Immunoassay protocol</HEADER><P><s sid="83"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The immunoassays were conducted by a sandwich structure illustrated as Steps 4 and 5 in Scheme 1.</text></s> <s sid="84"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Antigen solutions with different concentrations were obtained by diluting with PBS buffer solutions.</text></s> <s sid="85"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>40 µL of the Antigen solution was dropped onto the APTMS–GA–PAb substrate, and the substrate was left for 1 h at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="86"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then, an APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen surface was formed on the chips.</text></s> <s sid="87"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Having been carefully rinsed with a PBS buffer solution, the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen surface were exposed to 50 µL of the MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles borate buffer solution for 3 h at room temperature.</text></s> <s sid="88"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All the chips were then rinsed with ultrapure water and dried under nitrogen gas.</text></s> <s sid="89"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, the chips were modified by the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen–immunogold surface.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER>SERS and UV-vis measurements</HEADER><P><s sid="90"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Silver staining enhancement was conducted with silver nitrate reduced by hydroquinone in the dark to coat the nanoparticles (Step 6 in Scheme 1).</text></s> <s sid="91"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The molar ratio of hydroquinone (1 × 10−3 mol L−1) to AgNO3 (1 × 10−3 mol L−1) (v/v) was 1.</text></s> <s sid="92"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The silver staining enhancement step was completed within 20 min.</text></s> <s sid="93"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then, the chips were rinsed with ultrapure water and dried under nitrogen gas.</text></s></P><P><s sid="94"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>SERS spectra were measured with a confocal microscopic Raman spectrometer (Renishaw 1000 model) with a CCD detector and a holographic notch filter.</text></s> <s sid="95"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Radiation of 514.5 nm from an air-cooled argon ion laser (Spectra-Physics model 163-C4260) was used for excitation.</text></s> <s sid="96"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Laser power at the sample position was not more than a few milliwatts.</text></s> <s sid="97"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The microscope attachment was based on a Leica DMLM system, and a 50× objective was used to focus the laser beam onto a spot of approximately 1 µm in diameter.</text></s> <s sid="98"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All the spectra reported were the results of a single 10 s accumulation.</text></s></P><P><s sid="99"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>UV-vis spectra were recorded on a Shimadzu UV-3100 spectrophotometer.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Results and discussion</HEADER><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="1.">The MBA-labelling gold colloid</HEADER><P><s sid="100"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Gold colloid is superior to other colloids in long-term stability and it has widely been used for the researches of immunogold.<REF ID="R-74" REFID="cit28"/></text></s> <s sid="101"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, SERS probe molecules, such as MBA, destroy the double-electronic layer around a colloid particle surface, which has been coated by citrate, because of the stronger adsorbability of the thiol group of MBA.</text></s> <s sid="102"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This leads to the unstability of colloid particles and the aggregation badly disturbs the immuno-identification between antigen and immunogold, thereby disturbing the SERS detection.</text></s> <s sid="103"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore the amount of MBA added to the colloid and the period of stable storage are critical to this method.</text></s></P><P><s sid="104"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met9" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>For optimizing the experimental conditions, we added various quantities of MBA into gold colloid to test the stability of MBA modified gold colloid through centrifugation, and then separated MBA from the solution by centrifugation.</text></s> <s sid="105"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When the added amount of MBA (1 × 10−3 mol L−1) was less than 5 µL in 1 mL gold colloid (2 × 10−4 mol gold L−1), the pink gold colloid did not turn blue and remained unchanged at room temperature for at least a week.</text></s> <s sid="106"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We consider that this quantity of MBA only occupies a portion of the surface of gold sphere according to the calculated result for the surface occupied by a single thiol (about 20 Å2 molecule−1)<REF ID="R-75" REFID="cit32"/> and the calculated result for a gold particle (4π × (13/2 nm)2).</text></s> <s sid="107"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, there is still some space left for MAb.</text></s> <s sid="108"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met10" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>We also carried out the silver staining experiment without MAb by SERS to know how small an amount of MBA can be detected.</text></s></P><P><s sid="109"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 1 shows the SERS spectrum of 2.5 µL of MBA (1 × 10−3 mol L−1) added to 1 mL of gold colloids followed by silver staining enhancement.</text></s> <s sid="110"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met11" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In this experiment the laser beam (514.5 nm) was focused on the colloid in a capillary.</text></s> <s sid="111"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Strong SERS bands at 1586 and 1076 cm−1 are assigned to the ν8a and ν12 aromatic ring vibrations, respectively, and those at 1373 and 841 cm−1 are assigned to ν(COO−) and δ(COO−), respectively.<REF ID="R-76" REFID="cit33"/></text></s> <s sid="112"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As can be seen from the SERS spectrum, Raman signals are well enhanced after the silver staining enhancement.</text></s> <s sid="113"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This experiment also indicates that 2.5 µL of MBA (1 × 10−3 mol L−1) in 1 mL gold colloid (2 × 10−4 mol L−1) is enough for the SERS detection.</text></s> <s sid="114"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Though this amount of MBA is far from the amount for coating all colloid particles, MBA adsorbed by physisorption easily dissociates in the colliods and affects the SERS detection.</text></s> <s sid="115"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, multiple-rinse by centrifugation and resuspension are necessary.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="2.">Characterization of the sandwich structure on a quartz chip via UV-vis absorption spectra</HEADER><P><s sid="116"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met12" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>To confirm the existence of metal gold nanoparticles on the surface of an APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen–immunogold substrate, we repeated all the steps to assembly this sandwich structure on quartz substrates, and then measured UV-vis absorption spectra of Step 5 and Step 6 in Scheme 1.</text></s> <s sid="117"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 2 (a) and (b) respectively show the UV-vis absorption spectra of the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen–immunogold quartz substrate before and after silver staining enhancement.</text></s> <s sid="118"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The UV-vis spectrum of the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen–immunogold quartz substrate (Curve (a) in Fig. 2) shows an absorption peak at 526 nm, which is attributed to the gold nanoparticles.</text></s> <s sid="119"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, based on this characteristic adsorption peak of the gold nanoparticles, we concluded that the MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles reacted with Antigen on the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen substrate.</text></s> <s sid="120"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The UV-vis absorption spectrum of the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen–immunogold substrate after the silver staining enhancement (Curve (b) in Fig. 2) shows an obvious plasmon resonance band at 429 nm due to silver.</text></s> <s sid="121"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This spectrum proves the existence of silver.</text></s> <s sid="122"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, the bandwidth of the silver absorption band suggests that the surface of the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen–immunogold substrate becomes a rough surface after the silver staining enhancement, which is very suitable for the SERS detection also.</text></s></P></DIV><DIV DEPTH="2"><HEADER HEADER_MARKER="3.">Characterization of immunoassays via SERS</HEADER><P><s sid="123"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The spectral features of MBA in SERS spectra can confirm the selective immunoassays.</text></s> <s sid="124"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 3 shows SERS spectra of MBA adsorbed on the immunogold nanoparticles after the silver staining enhancement.</text></s> <s sid="125"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Antigen solutions with different concentrations of 0, 0.5, 1, 2, 10, 20, 40 and 50 µg mL−1 were examined by the method depicted in Scheme 1, and their SERS spectra are shown in Fig. 3(a)–(h).</text></s> <s sid="126"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A comparison between these spectra and the spectrum in Fig. 1 reveals that most of Raman bands in Fig. 3 can be assigned to the vibrational modes of MBA.</text></s> <s sid="127"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We dealt the SERS spectra with the Grams-386 software (The Galactic Industries Corporation, USA), assuming the intensity of the peak at 520 cm−1 due to silicon as the intensity of 10000.</text></s> <s sid="128"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The Antigen concentration-dependent SERS spectral changes in Fig. 3 indicate that after the silver staining enhancement, the higher the concentration of Antigen captured by the substrate is, the stronger the Raman signals observed are.</text></s> <s sid="129"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 4 illustrates the intensity change at 1585 cm−1 due to the ν8a aromatic ring vibration versus the concentration of Antigen.</text></s> <s sid="130"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When the concentration of the Antigen is above 40 µg mL−1, the intensity of the SERS signal at 1585 cm−1 increases rapidly.</text></s> <s sid="131"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>On the other hand, when the concentration of the Antigen is 0.5 µg mL−1, it is difficult to detect the signals of MBA from the SERS spectrum of Fig. 3(b) .</text></s> <s sid="132"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Finally, we developed a calibration model that predicts the concentration of Antigen in the range of 1–40 µg mL−1.</text></s> <s sid="133"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The inset of Fig. 4 depicts the model; the correlation coefficient (R) and standard deviation (SD) are 0.98 (n = 5) and 214, respectively, and the non-optimized detection limit of Hepatitis B virus surface antigen is as low as 0.5 µg mL−1.</text></s></P><P><s sid="134"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>One must notice that some differences exist among the spectra in Fig. 3.</text></s> <s sid="135"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Curve (b) has a poor signal to noise ratio because the concentration of Antigen and the amount of the complementary MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles are very low.</text></s> <s sid="136"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Curve (h) shows a highly increased background from 1800 to 1000 cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="137"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The background due to silver on the Raman spectra increased with the increasing concentration of Antigen.</text></s> <s sid="138"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This may be explained as follows; for the higher concentration of Antigen, there are more immunogold nanoparticles on the chips.</text></s> <s sid="139"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Thus, a great deal of silver aggregates and is deposited onto the immunogold nanoparticles leading to the higher silver background on the Raman spectra.</text></s> <s sid="140"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is noted that the Raman bands in the spectra in Fig. 3 are slightly broader than those in the spectrum in Fig. 1.</text></s> <s sid="141"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is probably caused by the interaction of BSA and MAb with MBA on the gold surface.</text></s></P><P><s sid="142"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Fig. 5 shows SERS spectra of MBA on the APTMS–GA–PAb–Antigen–immunogold substrate where the concentration of Antigen is as low as 0.5 µg mL−1 before (a) and after (b) the silver staining enhancement.</text></s> <s sid="143"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is noted that the intensity of the band at 1585 cm−1 in curve (b) is much stronger than that in curve (a).</text></s> <s sid="144"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This means that the process of silver staining enhancement is the major premise for the detection of significant Raman signals.</text></s> <s sid="145"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After the silver staining enhancement, the Raman signals can be increased by 10–100 times, thereby improving the detection sensitivity of this immunoassay method.</text></s></P><P><s sid="146"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The sensitivity of an immunoassay is substantially affected by a nonspecific binding.</text></s> <s sid="147"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>For comparison, a test has been performed where no Antigen was added to the detection system.</text></s> <s sid="148"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met13" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Because of the lack of the complementary antigens, the MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles are easily removed from the substrate during the rinsing step.</text></s> <s sid="149"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As a result, we obtained a flat baseline (Fig. 3(a)), confirming the fact that the nonspecific binding between the immunogold nanoparticles and the substrate could be avoided.</text></s> <s sid="150"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met14" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Another test was performed by using a goat IgG sample as antigen to check the specificity of the MBA-labelling immunogold in the present system.</text></s> <s sid="151"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>After silver staining enhancement, no band due to MBA was observed in the SERS spectrum in the region of 2000–300 cm−1.</text></s> <s sid="152"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These results are consistent with the expectation that a specific reaction only occurs between MAb onto the MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles and its complementary antigen (Antigen), and that it does not take place between MAb and other antigens.</text></s> <s sid="153"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Both tests mentioned above indicate that nonspecific binding effects can effectively be avoided by BSA and l-lysine.</text></s> <s sid="154"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As already described, BSA occupies the remaining surface of gold nanoparticles after MAb attachment, preventing PAb onto the APTMS–GA–PAb substrate from attaching on the surface of the gold nanoparticles.</text></s> <s sid="155"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In addition, l-lysine blocks the unreactive aldehyde groups of GA.</text></s> <s sid="156"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This partially avoids the adsorption between the aldehyde groups onto the substrate and MAb of the immunogold nanoparticles.</text></s> <s sid="157"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>They are most likely major factors determining the sensitivity of this assay.</text></s></P></DIV></DIV><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER>Conclusions</HEADER><P><s sid="158"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In summary, we have demonstrated a novel method based on MBA-labelling immunogold nanoparticles with the silver staining enhancement for the quantitative detection of Hepatitis B virus surface antigen as a self-assembled sandwich model immobilized on a silicon or quartz substrate.</text></s> <s sid="159"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Based on this method, we have developed a calibration model that predicts the concentration of Hepatitis B virus surface antigen.</text></s> <s sid="160"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This method has combined the advantages of the SERS technique with those of the nano-labelling method.</text></s> <s sid="161"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The silver staining method remarkably enhanced Raman signals by several decuples, improving the detection sensitivity of the immunoassay.</text></s> <s sid="162"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con15" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The advantages of the immunogold nanoparticles, such as their easily controllable-size distribution, long-term stability and friendly biocompatibility confirm the reproducibility of the immunoassay.</text></s> <s sid="163"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con16" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, we are puzzled by the viability of antigens and antibodies after being captured by the substrates in our assay system, which results in the higher detection limit compared with other immune systems.</text></s> <s sid="164"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further experiments on the multifarious antibody-immobilized methods and other immune systems will be carried out.</text></s> <s sid="165"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con17" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, multi-labelled techniques and microarray detections in multiplex immunoassay are now under way in our laboratories.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY><cmlPile><cml xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema" id="cml1"><molecule id="m1"><name>4-mercaptobenzoic acid</name><atomArray><atom id="a1" elementType="C"/><atom id="a2" elementType="C"/><atom id="a3" elementType="C"/><atom id="a4" elementType="C"/><atom id="a5" elementType="C"/><atom id="a6" elementType="C"/><atom id="a7" elementType="C"/><atom id="a8" elementType="O"/><atom id="a9" elementType="O"/><atom id="a10" elementType="S"/></atomArray><bondArray><bond atomRefs2="a1 a2" order="2"/><bond atomRefs2="a2 a3" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a3 a4" order="2"/><bond atomRefs2="a4 a5" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a5 a6" order="2"/><bond atomRefs2="a6 a1" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a7 a1" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a7 a8" order="2"/><bond atomRefs2="a7 a9" order="1"/><bond atomRefs2="a10 a4" order="1"/></bondArray></molecule></cml><cmlUrlEnc idRef="cml1">%3Ccml+xmlns%3D%22http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xml-cml.org%2Fschema%22+id%3D%22cml
1%22%3E%3Cmolecule+id%3D%22m1%22%3E%3Cname%3E4-mercaptobenzoic+acid%3C
%2Fname%3E%3CatomArray%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a1%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3C
atom+id%3D%22a2%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a3%22+eleme
ntType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a4%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom
+id%3D%22a5%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a6%22+elementTy
pe%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a7%22+elementType%3D%22C%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D
%22a8%22+elementType%3D%22O%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a9%22+elementType%3D%22
O%22+%2F%3E%3Catom+id%3D%22a10%22+elementType%3D%22S%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FatomArray%3E
%3CbondArray%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a1+a2%22+order%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%3Cbo
nd+atomRefs2%3D%22a2+a3%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22
a3+a4%22+order%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a4+a5%22+order%3D%22
1%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a5+a6%22+order%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+ato
mRefs2%3D%22a6+a1%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a7+a1%22
+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2%3D%22a7+a8%22+order%3D%222%22+%2F%3E%3C
bond+atomRefs2%3D%22a7+a9%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3Cbond+atomRefs2
%3D%22a10+a4%22+order%3D%221%22+%2F%3E%3C%2FbondArray%3E%3C%2Fmolecule%3E%3C%2Fcml
%3E</cmlUrlEnc></cmlPile></PAPER>