<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE PAPER
  SYSTEM "paper-structure-annotation.dtd">
<PAPER><mode2 name="b704599a" hasDoc="yes" version="1085"/><TITLE><s sid="1"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Cationic corrole derivatives: a new family of G-quadruplex inducing and stabilizing ligands</text></s></TITLE><ABSTRACT><s sid="2"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Water-soluble cationic corrole derivatives were designed and synthesized, and the first observation of their interactions with the telomeric G-quadruplex was made.</text></s></ABSTRACT><BODY><DIV DEPTH="1"><HEADER/><P><s sid="3"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Telomeres exist at the ends of eukaryotic chromosomes and can protect the chromosomes, which play very important roles in many aspects of cells.<REF ID="R-0" REFID="cit1"/><REF ID="R-1" REFID="cit2"/></text></s> <s sid="4"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It is known that telomeric repeats with the single-stranded G-rich overhang can be extended by telomerase.<REF ID="R-2" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="5"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As telomerase is overexpressed in most tumor cells and not in normal cells, such a unique enzyme could be a good target for the design of antitumor drugs with high selectivity.<REF ID="R-3" REFID="cit3"/></text></s> <s sid="6"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Meanwhile, a single-stranded 3′ overhang of telomeric DNA<REF ID="R-4" REFID="cit4a"/><REF ID="R-5" REFID="cit4b"/> can be folded into intramolecular G-quadruplex structures leading to hindrance of the reaction of telomerase.<REF ID="R-6" REFID="cit5"/></text></s> <s sid="7"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Therefore, if a ligand could stabilize the G-quadruplex (Scheme 1A), it could have a potential application as a telomerase inhibitor.</text></s> <s sid="8"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Recently, many G-quadruplex stabilizers have been synthesized and studied for their biological and medicinal activities by many groups.<REF ID="R-7" REFID="cit7a"/><REF ID="R-8" REFID="cit7b"/><REF ID="R-9" REFID="cit7c"/><REF ID="R-10" REFID="cit8a"/><REF ID="R-11" REFID="cit8b"/><REF ID="R-12" REFID="cit9a"/><REF ID="R-13" REFID="cit9b"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="9"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Corroles are tetrapyrrole macrocycles with one of the meso-carbon atoms substituted by a direct pyrrole–pyrrole link.<REF ID="R-14" REFID="cit10a"/><REF ID="R-15" REFID="cit10b"/></text></s> <s sid="10"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It has been found that corroles can be applied in synthesis, catalysis, biological and medicinal studies.<REF ID="R-16" REFID="cit11a"/><REF ID="R-17" REFID="cit11b"/><REF ID="R-18" REFID="cit11c"/><REF ID="R-19" REFID="cit11d"/></text></s> <s sid="11"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Mot" conceptID="Mot1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, few reports of corroles in medicinal or biological applications have been published.<REF ID="R-20" REFID="cit11a"/><REF ID="R-21" REFID="cit11b"/><REF ID="R-22" REFID="cit11c"/><REF ID="R-23" REFID="cit11d"/></text></s> <s sid="12"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In this paper, we shall report our synthesis of cationic corrole derivatives 3 and 5 (Scheme 1B) and our first findings of their good abilities to stabilize the G-quadruplex structure as tested by polymerase stop assay, SPR experiments and CD melting.</text></s> <s sid="13"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Goa" conceptID="Goa1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Furthermore, their capabilities to induce G-quadruplex structure formation were tested by CD.</text></s></P><P><s sid="14"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Gross's group reported a kind of 2-pyridinium pentafluorophenyl corrole.</text></s> <s sid="15"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In our synthesis of 4-pyridinium corrole 3, we obtained this compound in two steps by a modification of the reported method.<REF ID="R-24" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="16"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Pyrrole condensed with 4-pyridyl-carboxaldehyde to form 4-pyridyl corrole 1 in acetic acid, then 4-pyridyl corrole was methylated in DMF to form water-soluble 4-pyridinium corrole 3 in high yield (Scheme 2).</text></s></P><P><s sid="17"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met2" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>Synthesis of corrole 5 was accomplished by condensing pyrrole with 4-nitrobenzaldehyde to form 4-nitrophenyl corrole in acetic acid.<REF ID="R-25" REFID="cit12"/></text></s> <s sid="18"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Then 4-nitrophenyl corrole was reduced by SnCl2 and 4-amino corrole 4 was obtained.</text></s> <s sid="19"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Methylation of corrole 4 was achieved in acetone at 60 °C for seven days and quaternary ammonium corrole 5 was obtained in good yield.</text></s></P><P><s sid="20"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>All the new compounds were fully characterized by NMR, UV, elementary analysis and HRMS (see Supporting Information).</text></s> <s sid="21"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>As in methylation of pyridyl corrole 1 in DMF, mono-anionic forms in the inner nitrogens of corrole 2 were observed by ESIMS.</text></s> <s sid="22"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This is consistent with the early results reported by Gross.<REF ID="R-26" REFID="cit13"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="23"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met3" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>To identify if corroles 3 and 5 could stabilize the G-quadruplex structure, a Taq DNA polymerase stop assay was used to determine the corrole-induced stability of the quadruplex based on the template strand at low K+ concentration.<REF ID="R-27" REFID="cit14"/></text></s> <s sid="24"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The experimental results indicated that the pausing site in the DNA extension process was enhanced by stabilizing the G-quadruplex structure by corrole induction (Fig. 1).</text></s> <s sid="25"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This suggested that corroles 3 and 5 could stabilize the G-quadruplex structure.</text></s></P><P><s sid="26"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further experimental data from the CD melting method supported this conclusion.</text></s> <s sid="27"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Our results indicated that both corroles 3 and 5 were able to induce strongly the stabilization of quadruplex DNA (sequence 5′-CATGG TGGTTT GGGTTA GGGTTA GGGTTA GGGTTA CCAC-′3; Tm = 43 °C in the absence of corrole).</text></s> <s sid="28"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Exp" conceptID="Exp4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>During our experiments, CD-thermal transitions were monitored at 295 nm.</text></s> <s sid="29"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>We found a reverse sigmoidal pattern and this is the property of intramolecular G-quadruplex formation (Fig. 2).<REF ID="R-28" REFID="cit15a"/><REF ID="R-29" REFID="cit15b"/></text></s> <s sid="30"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the presence of corroles 3 and 5, the melting temperature increased by 38 °C and 16 °C respectively.</text></s> <s sid="31"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Data suggested that corroles 3 and 5 strongly stabilized the G-quadruplex in Na+ buffer.</text></s></P><P><s sid="32"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met4" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The binding abilities of corroles 3 and 5 to human telomeric sequence, 5′-AG3TTAG3TTAG3TTAG3 and three other immobilized duplex DNA (GC, AT, ds) were examined by SPR (surface plasmon resonance).<REF ID="R-30" REFID="cit7a"/><REF ID="R-31" REFID="cit7b"/><REF ID="R-32" REFID="cit7c"/></text></s> <s sid="33"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met5" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The steady-state equilibrium binding constants and kinetic constants of corroles 3, 5 with duplex and quadruplex DNA were both measured under previously described experimental conditions.<REF ID="R-33" REFID="cit16a"/><REF ID="R-34" REFID="cit16b"/></text></s> <s sid="34"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res4" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(Fig. 3 and Figs. S1, S2, see Supporting Information) The sensorgrams indicated that corroles 3 and 5 had high binding constants, and obvious selectivity for quadruplex DNA.</text></s> <s sid="35"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(Table S1, see Supporting Information) From our experimental data, we found that the selectivities of corroles 3 and 5 were much better than that of TMPyP4(5,10,15,20-tetrakis-(N-methyl-4-pyridyl)-21H,23H-porphyrin), which is a good G-quadruplex stabilizer.</text></s></P><P><s sid="36"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It has been reported that DNA oligonucleotide with a human telomeric sequence could form an intramolecular basket-type G-quadruplex structure in the presence of Na+, while in K+ solution, the conformation might be a hybrid of parallel/antiparallel G-quadruplex structures.<REF ID="R-35" REFID="cit17a"/><REF ID="R-36" REFID="cit17b"/></text></s> <s sid="37"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These conformation changes could be observed by CD measurement.</text></s> <s sid="38"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>A typical antiparallel G-quadruplex structure of d[T2AG3]4 oligonucleotide was formed in the presence of Na+ which exhibits a positive band near 295 nm and a negative band at 265 nm in CD spectra.<REF ID="R-37" REFID="cit17a"/><REF ID="R-38" REFID="cit17b"/><REF ID="R-39" REFID="cit19"/></text></s> <s sid="39"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In the presence of K+, both a small peak at 265 nm and a stronger positive band around 288 nm are the characteristics of the hybrid G-quadruplex in CD spectra.<REF ID="R-40" REFID="cit18"/><REF ID="R-41" REFID="cit19"/></text></s> <s sid="40"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>On the other hand, for the control experiment, the intrinsic peak of d[T2AG3]4 oligonucleotide at 257 nm without cation was observed in the CD spectra, which suggested that G-quadruplex structures could not be formed without an ion.<REF ID="R-42" REFID="cit10a"/><REF ID="R-43" REFID="cit10b"/></text></s></P><P><s sid="41"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>In our current studies, we surprisingly found that corroles 3 and 5 could induce the formation of the G-quadruplex without an ion.</text></s> <s sid="42"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs5" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The peaks at 257 nm of CD spectra were gradually shifted to 290 nm (Fig. S4 a, see Supporting Information) with the increase of concentration of corrole 3 in d[T2AG3]4 oligonucleotide Tris-HCl solution.</text></s> <s sid="43"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These peaks are consistent with CD spectra of the d[T2AG3]4 oligonucleotide in K+ buffer,<REF ID="R-44" REFID="cit19"/> which suggested the formation of a hybrid parallel/antiparallel G-quadruplex in the buffer without ion.</text></s> <s sid="44"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The same phenomenon was also observed for corrole 5 (Fig. S3, see Supporting Information).</text></s></P><P><s sid="45"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met6" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>Further studies on the G-quadruplex structural transition induced by corrole 3 in the presence of Na+ and observed by CD were carried out.</text></s> <s sid="46"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>When corrole 3 was added, the signal absorbance at 265 nm increased greatly from a negative band to a small peak.</text></s> <s sid="47"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs6" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>However, there are almost no changes in the positive band at 295 nm.</text></s> <s sid="48"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res9" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>(Fig. S4 b, see Supporting Information) These results supported the proposal that the structure transition from antiparallel to mixed-type hybrid G-quadruplex was induced by corrole 3.</text></s></P><P><s sid="49"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>To the best of our knowledge, only a few small molecules can influence the structural transition of a human telomeric sequence and induce the formation of a G-quadruplex structure.<REF ID="R-45" REFID="cit9a"/><REF ID="R-46" REFID="cit9b"/><REF ID="R-47" REFID="cit17a"/><REF ID="R-48" REFID="cit17b"/><REF ID="R-49" REFID="cit20"/><REF ID="R-50" REFID="cit21"/></text></s> <s sid="50"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res10" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The CD spectroscopy measurement demonstrated here that corrole 3 not only could induce human telomeric d[T2AG3]4 oligonucleotide to form the mixed-type hybrid G-quadruplex structures, but also transfer the antiparallel structure to a hybrid parallel/antiparallel G-quadruplex structure.</text></s></P><P><s sid="51"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The compounds were further tested for their inhibiting effect on telomerase activities by the TRAP method.</text></s> <s sid="52"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Met" conceptID="Met7" novelty="Old" advantage="None"/><text>The TRAP assays were performed according to the reported method.<REF ID="R-52" REFID="cit22b"/></text></s> <s sid="53"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs7" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The IC50 values of corroles 3 and 5 are 8.6 µM and 4.4 µM respectively.</text></s></P><P><s sid="54"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obs" conceptID="Obs8" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Qualitative molecular modeling using molecular mechanics energy minimizations was studied and experimental results showed good overlaps between corrole 3 or 5 and guanine quartets (Fig. S4 and Fig. S5, see Supporting Information).</text></s> <s sid="55"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res11" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>It predicted that the aromatic rings with positive charges were tilted from the plane of the ligand to follow the twist of the grooves and the groups with positive charges were directed into the grooves toward the sugar–phosphate backbone.</text></s></P><P><s sid="56"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Obj" conceptID="Obj1" novelty="New" advantage="None"/><text>In conclusion, the water-soluble cationic corroles 3, 5 were designed and synthesized, and the first observations of their interactions with the telomeric G-quadruplex were made.</text></s> <s sid="57"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con1" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Experimental results indicated that these compounds could be a new class of G-quadruplex stabilizers.</text></s> <s sid="58"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>SPR sensorgrams showed the obvious selectivities of corroles 3, 5 for G-quadruplex DNA compared to ds DNA.</text></s> <s sid="59"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Res" conceptID="Res12" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The formation and transition of the G-quadruplex induced by corroles 3 and 5 were observed by CD.</text></s> <s sid="60"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Con" conceptID="Con3" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>The high affinities of corroles 3, 5 for quadruplex DNA are associated with the planar arrangement of the rings, their appropriate spacing and the substituent groups with positive charges based on the molecular modeling results.</text></s> <s sid="61"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Hyp" conceptID="Hyp2" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>These studies suggested that the water-soluble cationic corrole derivatives might be potential candidates for new anticancer agents.</text></s> <s sid="62"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac13" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>Further investigation of their mechanism and biomedical application is underway.</text></s></P><P><s sid="63"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>This work was partially supported by the National Science Fund for Distinguished Young Scholars (No.</text></s> <s sid="64"><CoreSc1 atype="GSC" type="Bac" conceptID="Bac14" novelty="None" advantage="None"/><text>20425206), the Ministry of Education of China, the State Key Laboratory of Natural and Biomimetic Drugs, Beijing University and the State Key Laboratory of Applied Organic Chemistry, Lanzhou University.</text></s></P></DIV></BODY></PAPER>